<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: tools | Brandon Walsh]]></title>
  <link href="https://walshbr.com/blog/categories/tools/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://walshbr.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-01-07T08:56:54-05:00</updated>
  <id>https://walshbr.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brandon Walsh]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prism in the Classroom: Questions to Frame Discussion]]></title>
    <link href="https://walshbr.com/blog/2014/09/16/prism-pedagogy/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-16T13:55:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://walshbr.com/blog/2014/09/16/prism-pedagogy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Crossposted on the <a href="http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/prism-in-the-classroom-questions-to-frame-discussion/">Scholars’ Lab blog</a>.</p>

<p>I have been touting the use of <a href="http://prism.scholarslab.org">Prism</a> in the university classroom for some time now, but a recent exchange with <a href="http://annieswafford.wordpress.com/">Annie Swafford</a> suggested to me that it might be worth explicitly outlining how I would go about doing so. With that in mind, I’ve composed the following set of questions for how I might frame discussion of Prism in the classroom. I’ve admittedly only had very brief chances to implement the tool in the classroom myself, so the thoughts come largely out of speculation and conversation. It should be noted as well that I assume below that you have already chosen a text and categories along which it should be marked (I may write on ways to approach such choices at a later date). In what follows, I move from general questions that I think would be helpful in framing any discussion of the tool to a particular use-case in <a href="http://prism.scholarslab.org/prisms/4213c156-aea5-11e2-80bf-c82a14fffe99/visualize?locale=en">James Joyce’s A Portrait of the Artist as a Young Man</a>. The former questions inform and engage my latter use-case.</p>

<p>I prepare for class discussion by assembling a list of questions to be explored, and I would organize a Prism discussion around two lines of inquiry: tool-specific and visualization-specific. Some of these questions can be helpful for framing your own thoughts. Others could usefully be posed to the class as a whole as a means of framing discussion. </p>

<p><strong>Tool-Specific Questions</strong></p>

<p>How do the tool and our framing of it affect how we read the text? How is Prism’s mode of reading different from what we normally do? Is it the same that we’ve always been doing – close reading in a different form? What are the problems with the form? Can we really boil interpretation down to a series of numbers, visualize it, and move forward? Or is there more to interpretation than that? How do individual interpretations join in with the group reading? How much is the interpretive process encapsulated in the marking of a text? The visualization? The conversation that follows? How do the terms you choose for highlighting (the facets) guide the experience of reading the text? How do the explanations you provide for those terms affect the marking experience? When do the terms break down? If the terms propose a binary, what happens to that opposition over the course of the experience? </p>

<p><strong>Visualization-Specific Questions</strong></p>

<p>Which passages were marked the least for a particular category? The most? Why in either case? Which passages were particularly contentious, marked in many different ways? Where do particular categories cluster? How does the visualization show a relationship between the categories? How does your own interpretation link up to the collected visualization produced by the tool? Do the two visualizations tell us anything meaningful? Would we be able to find these meanings on our own? How does the visualization reflect the interpretive process? Why might we care more about a particular visualization for a particular reading? How is the quantified version of interpretation that Prism generates distinct from what we might learn from a discussion on our own? Can we imagine limits to this approach? </p>

<p>The primary job of an instructor using Prism is to help the students connect the results of the tool to the larger discussions encapsulated by the marking categories. Look at the results with a skeptical eye and ask how they can be meaningfully related to the ideas and provocations of the marking categories. My favorite early use of Prism asked users to mark <a href="http://prism.scholarslab.org/prisms/4213c156-aea5-11e2-80bf-c82a14fffe99/highlight?locale=en">James Joyce’s A Portrait of the Artist</a> as a Young Man along the categories of “modernism” and “realism.” In a class, I would intersperse observations based on the visualizations with a discussion of the passage and the two marking categories. What do we mean by modernism? By realism? How is each expressed at the level of the text? What do we mean by literary experiment? By fragment? By realist details? What different genres does the text move through? Does the text construct a coherent narrative?</p>

<p>Putting realism and modernism alongside one another in Prism forces students to reconsider the binary, which quickly breaks down in practice. We can talk about whole novels or poems as belonging to one or another category, but can we do the same for individual sentences? For words? 80% of users at the time of this writing believe that the first word of the excerpt, “once,” is modernist. But why? If you look at <a href="http://prism.scholarslab.org/prisms/4213c156-aea5-11e2-80bf-c82a14fffe99/visualize?locale=en">the winning facet visualization</a>, people seem primarily to be marking whole passages as one category – they are interpreting realism and modernism in chunks, not in terms of individual words. Readers tend to mark as modernist those generic changes where the excerpt suddenly adopts the form of nursery rhyme or of a fairy tale, suggesting that it is not any one genre but the shift between several in rapid succession that readers find to be modernist. The font size visualization suggests that those passages referencing physical actions by people are more likely to be associated with realist: “His father told him that story” and “When you wet the bed first it is warm then it gets cold” are marked as being especially realist. With this observation in hand, why these details? Why are the body and the bodily detail markers of a realism? Why might an association with the family suggest realism? How do they come under pressure in the face of aesthetic experiment?</p>

<p>Obviously these suggestions are just beginnings for how to approach Prism in the classroom. Many other fascinating examples have already surfaced, particularly those that use the tool to teach basic reading and foreign language skills. Get in touch if you have used the tool in your classroom! I would love to hear how you did so. </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Teaching with Twitter - Part 2]]></title>
    <link href="https://walshbr.com/blog/2014/01/13/twitter-2/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-13T16:07:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://walshbr.com/blog/2014/01/13/twitter-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post is the second in a series reflecting on my experiments using Twitter in the classroom. Be sure to read the <a href="{{ root_url }}/blog/2013/11/02/twitter-1/">first</a> post that began the discussion.</em> </p>

<p>In my previous post, I described the process by which I went about integrating Twitter into my discussion section, but I offered few reasons for why instructors might want to do so. There are good pedagogical justifications for including social media, and it benefits interested instructors to give the move considered thought before integrating Twitter into course syllabi. I was prepared for students to push back against the idea of moving class conversation to Twitter, so I gave an opening pitch for the class activity containing several rationales for the experiment to my students. I encouraged students to think about Twitter as an exercise that would broaden their <strong>audience</strong>, allow them to practice digital <strong>professionalization</strong>, and challenge them to think small in their <strong>writing</strong>.  </p>

<p><strong>Audience</strong><br />
In a typical course, students take in a lot of information from a variety of sources, but the primary audience for their ideas is limited to their instructor and fellow students. This trajectory—all input and no output—can leave the activities of the classroom feeling disconnected from the broader scholarly discussion. With Twitter, a student’s audience expands beyond the people in the room to include potential readers around the world. Student comments can be circulated wildly, and I bring in examples of class Twitter activities managed by colleagues at other universities as a way of illustrating this fact. Retweeting student comments that prove particularly insightful can be a good way of underscoring your commitment to this circulation and the quality of their thinking.   </p>

<p>The broad scholarly Twitter community is especially useful when discussing writing practices. Academics often tweet about writing, and a retweet towards your class of a professional writer discussing her own revision process can pay great dividends. Such self-reflective comments help students to see that writers of all stages struggle with the same problems, that writing is always a process - even for professionals. Outside tweets can also give your paper comments added traction by reinforcing them with the spontaneous thoughts of outside sources far removed from your own course.  </p>

<p><strong>Professionalization</strong><br />
Students are often familiar with anecdotal evidence that employers regularly examine the social media accounts of potential employees, and framing Twitter in terms of this anxiety can further connect the course to the professional world. Students can fear the importance of their digital actions, or they can start managing their digital footprints now in ways that will benefit them in the future. The benefits of creating a professional digital presence have also been well documented: new networks and opportunities can be easily cultivated on Twitter that might be unavailable in real life, and some careers in professional writing and media outreach virtually require strong digital presences. I first came to Twitter in the interests of developing a professional persona, so I used my own experiences as a model for the benefits that can come from doing so. Framed in these terms, the class activity becomes training in a form of professionalization that will become a major part of the rest of students’ lives. By demonstrating intelligent and measured contributions in public for the purposes of the course, students can begin to take control over their digital personae.  </p>

<p><strong>Writing</strong><br />
Twitter forces students to think small. The character limit on responses helps to moderate the size of student comments, keeping them to a relatively standardized length and preventing the sense that a longer response indicates a deeper engagement with the course materials. The format can also offer ongoing practice for students in developing concise, specific thoughts on objects of study. I encourage students to think about twitter comments as a challenge to write micro-essays. Entire, coherent arguments can be constructed in 140 characters, and they will often be clearer for the obscene demand for concision. 140 characters is a short length even for a thesis statement, and the exercise demands no space be wasted—every word must have its place. The genre of the micro-essay can allow conversations about writing into the course on a regular basis as students consistently produce a variety of these mini-thesis statements over the course of a statement. <a href=" https://twitter.com/twitterfiction">@twitterfiction</a> can provide a good example of the power that can be achieved by such a small amount of writing.  </p>

<p>Stating your pedagogical motives for students up front encourages students to engage with Twitter in terms that align with your objectives for including the activity in the course in the first place. For more advice on creating professional digital presences in the context of a scholarly community, see Ryan Cordell’s wonderful ProfHacker post on <a href="http://chronicle.com/blogs/profhacker/creating-and-maintaining-a-professional-presence-online-a-roundup-and-reflection/43030">Creating and Maintaining a Professional Presence Online</a>.  </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Teaching with Twitter - Part One]]></title>
    <link href="https://walshbr.com/blog/2013/11/02/twitter-1/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-02T12:54:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://walshbr.com/blog/2013/11/02/twitter-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post begins a series reflecting on my experiments using Twitter in the classroom. Be sure to read the second post that continues the discussion.</em></p>

<p>I was only recently introduced to Twitter as a part of the <a href="http://praxis.scholarslab.org/">Praxis Program</a>, which encourages its fellows to engage with the social media platform as part of their education in how to engage with the digital humanities. I have become fascinated with Twitter’s ability to generate discussion, facilitate connections, and expand my own sense of the conversation in the field. I wanted to bring all of these elements into my classroom and share them with my students, so this past semester I integrated class Twitter responses into the participation element of my syllabus. Students tweeted several times over the course of the semester rather than post email responses to a private course site. In this post, I offer suggestions for the logistics of setting up such a course requirement and recount my own, while later posts theorize the pedagogical implications of the move and offer suggestions for tweaking student participation.  </p>

<p>The Twitter requirement was not particularly onerous: I required students to tweet at a course hashtag (#ENRN_F or #ENRN_R) seven times over the course of the semester. Students would only be required to respond roughly every other week, so collectively these tweets would barely equal the length of a more typical paragraph response. I asked students to follow the tweets as they came in throughout the week, and I occasionally used the content of student tweets as quiz questions to encourage active engagement. Response tweets could take any form – a link to an image, a film clip from an adaption, a short quote, a thought on a particular character, a theme, etc. – anything that could advance the conversation.  </p>

<p>About half of the students in my courses had used Twitter before, so interested instructors should be prepared to explain the format and offer support for those who are unfamiliar with it. I encouraged students to use <a href="http://tweetdeck.com/">TweetDeck</a> as a free and easy option for following the course hashtag, and we previewed the experience at the first course meeting by putting the app on the class overhead projector. A student tweeted to the hashtag in class at my request, allowing students to see just how instantaneous the class’s twitter engagement could be. I encouraged students to come by office hours during the first week if they wanted help setting up an account, but very few needed the assistance. The activity generated more anxiety up front than actual difficulty in practice.  </p>

<p>I taught two course sections of the same course when I implemented Twitter, so I considered using a shared hashtag for both classes. A single hashtag would allow cross-discussion conversation in ways that would not otherwise be possible. The increased activity that would come from two classes tweeting to the same place could provide a lively sense of community, even if some of those participants remain relative strangers in the context of the course. Separate hashtags make the actual logistics of teaching a bit more manageable: it is easier to lesson plan for the students that will actually be in the room and able to account for thoughts they have expressed online. I eventually opted for separate hashtags, but I encouraged students to follow and tweet at their sister section.  </p>

<p>Some students who already possessed Twitter accounts protected their tweets, but such gestures towards privacy would complicate the course setup: protected tweets would not show up on the course hashtag unless the student allowed every member of the class to follow them. Similarly, while I encouraged students to be excited about the opportunity to engage with a wider community through Twitter, some felt uncomfortable with their ideas exposed to the world. I gave these students the option of creating a new, dummy Twitter account specifically for the purposes of the course. Their name did not have to be associated with the account at all, so long as the rest of the class knew to whom the account belonged. I circulated a list of students’ twitter handles early on so that we could match names to e-identities. Twitter required students to meditate on the public nature of their own intellectual lives and the reach of their own voices, and dummy accounts respected the privacy of concerned students.  </p>

<p>In all, teaching with Twitter requires a relatively small amount of effort to implement, as the barrier to entry for students is quite low. But a little planning about your setup ahead of time goes a long way. For more helpful tips on the logistics of using Twitter in the classroom, check out Mark Sample’s ProfHacker post on “<a href="http://chronicle.com/blogs/profhacker/practical-advice-for-teaching-with-twitter/26416">Practical Advice for Teaching with Twitter</a>.”   </p>

<p><em>Stay tuned for part two in my series on Teaching with Twitter, where I further discuss pedagogical benefits and justifications for class Twitter accounts.</em> </p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing Out Loud: Google Docs for Live Writing, Revision, and Discussion]]></title>
    <link href="https://walshbr.com/blog/2013/09/25/writing-out-loud/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-25T09:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://walshbr.com/blog/2013/09/25/writing-out-loud</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have been using Google Docs as a part of my teaching for almost two years now. The idea first came about in an advanced course on Academic and Professional Writing. We talked a lot about editing in the class, and many of the conversations about style took this shape:</p>

<p>Student A: “Something about this word feels strange, but I don’t know what it is.” <br />
Student B: “What if we moved the phrase to the beginning of the sentence?”<br />
Student C: “We could get rid of that word and use this phrase instead.”  </p>

<p>Hard to wrap your head around, right? Just imagine if those conversations were spoken. <em>Talking</em> about writing can only get you so far: writing is graphic, after all. As I write and edit, I try out different options on the page. I model possibilities, but I do so <em>in</em> writing. Discussing the editing process without visual representations of suggested changes can make things too abstract to be meaningful for students. I developed an exercise that I call “Writing Out Loud” that more closely mirrors my actual editing process. Using a Google Doc as a collaborative writing space, students are able to model alternate revisions visually and in real time for discussion.</p>

<p><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/WOL_settings.jpg" width="60%" class="right" /> </p>

<p>The setup requires a projector-equipped classroom and that students bring their laptops to class. Circulate the link to the Google Doc ahead of time, taking care that anyone with the link can edit the document. </p>

<p>The template of the Google Doc consists of a blank space at the top for displaying the sentence under question and a series of workspaces for each student consisting of their name and a few blank lines. Separate workspaces prevent overlapping revisions, and they also minimize the disorienting effects of having multiple people writing on the same document.</p>

<p><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/WOL_template.jpg" width="60%" class="left" /></p>

<p>We usually turn to the exercise when a student feels a particular sentence is not working but cannot articulate why. When this happens, put the Writing Out Loud template on the projector with the original version of the sentence at the top. Using their own laptops, students sign onto the Doc and type out alternative versions of the sentence, and the multiple possible revisions show up on the overhead for everyone to see and discuss. After each student rewrites the sentence to be something that they feel works better, ask for volunteers to explain how the changes affect meaning. The whole process only takes a few minutes, and it allows you to abstract writing principles from the actual process of revision rather that the other way around. How does the structure of a sentence matter? How can word choice change everything? What pieces of a sentence are repetitive?</p>

<p><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/WOL_filled.jpg" width="60%" class="right" /></p>

<p>Obviously Writing Out Loud works better on micro-edits, revisions at the level of the sentence. The standard process of the exercise—write, collate, and discuss—would take far too long with anything longer than a few lines. The exercise can be particularly useful for those sentences that carry a lot of importance for entire arguments: thesis statements, topic sentences, the first sentences of the document, etc. </p>

<p>I find that students often think of editing as an intense, sweeping process that involves wholesale transformation from the ground up. Modeling multiple, slightly different versions of the same sentence can allow for a more concrete discussion of the sweeping rhetorical changes that even the smallest edits can make.</p>

<p>You can find a copy of the template <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1Dk2GpCqvm6o3K-dbfUazekHbiSlqwJeIoE2OZ-OjL00/edit?usp=sharing">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bash-it Plugins]]></title>
    <link href="https://walshbr.com/blog/2013/08/11/bash-it-plugins-and-symlink-troubles/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-11T16:41:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://walshbr.com/blog/2013/08/11/bash-it-plugins-and-symlink-troubles</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes things go wrong. When this happens, I often find a temporary solution that works fine in the moment, but implementing the fix repeatedly can get annoying over time. Here is something that I had been ignoring for a while and only recently took the time to fix.</p>

<p>I use <a href="https://github.com/revans/bash-it">bash-it</a>, which has lots of neat tricks and functions. Since installing it, however, I had been getting a message every time I open up a terminal window:</p>

<p><code>sorry, the z plugin is incompatible with the fasd plugin. you may use either, but not both.</code></p>

<p>The message doesn’t stop you from going about your business, so I never really read it very closely: bash-it tells you everything you need to know. When installing, bash-it prompts you to make a variety of decisions about how many plugins you will use on a regular basis. I told bash-it to enable everything by default, but this decision caused a conflict between two plugins.</p>

<p>To see which plugins you have enabled, open a terminal window and type:</p>

<p><code>$ bash-it show plugins</code></p>

<p>In the output, you should see some flavor of the following diagnosing the problem:</p>

<p><code>z [x]     maintains a jump-list of the directories you actually use  
z is DEPRECATED, use fasd instead</code></p>

<p>Plugin z causes an error when activated with a newer plugin with the same functionality. Bash-it gives you the fix:</p>

<p><code>$ bash-it disable plugin z</code></p>

<p>After that, your terminal should run free of the message.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
