<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: sound studies | Brandon Walsh]]></title>
  <link href="http://lanyon.getpoole.com/categories/sound-studies/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://lanyon.getpoole.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-04-27T20:11:44-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://lanyon.getpoole.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[{"name"=>"Brandon Walsh", "url"=>"https://twitter.com/mdo", "email"=>"walsh@virginia.edu"}]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reading Speech: Virginia Woolf, Machine Learning, and the Quotation Mark]]></title>
    <link href="http://lanyon.getpoole.com/blog/2016/05/17/reading-speech/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-17T08:46:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lanyon.getpoole.com/blog/2016/05/17/reading-speech</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>[Crossposted on the <a href="http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/reading-speech-virginia-woolf-machine-learning-and-the-quotation-mark/">Scholars’ Lab blog</a> as well as the <a href="http://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/blog/2016/05/17/reading-speech-virginia-woolf-machine-learning-and-the-quotation-mark/">WLUDH blog</a>. What follows is a slightly more fleshed out version of what I presented this past week at <a href="http://hastac2016.org">HASTAC 2016</a> (complete with my memory-inflected transcript of the Q&amp;A). I gave a bit more context for the project at the event than I do here, so it might be helpful to read my past two posts on the project <a href="https://walshbr.github.io/blog/2015/03/23/woolf-huskey/">here</a> and <a href="http://walshbr.github.io/blog/2015/09/10/woolf-and-the-quotation-mark/">here</a> before going forward. This talk continues that conversation.]</em></p>

<p>This year in the <a href="http://www.scholarslab.org">Scholar’s Lab</a> I have been working with Eric on a machine learning project that studies speech in Virginia Woolf’s fiction. I have written elsewhere about the <a href="https://walshbr.github.io/blog/2015/03/23/woolf-huskey/">background for the project</a> and <a href="http://walshbr.github.io/blog/2015/09/10/woolf-and-the-quotation-mark/">initial thoughts  towards its implications</a>. For the purposes of this blog post, I will just present a single example to provide context. Consider the famous first line of <em>Mrs. Dalloway</em>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Mrs Dalloway said, “I will buy the flowers myself.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Nothing to remark on here, except for the fact that this is not how the sentence actually comes down to us. I have modified it from the original:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Mrs Dalloway said she would buy the flowers herself.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>My project concerns moments like these, where Woolf implies the presence of speech without marking it as such with punctuation. I have been working with Eric to lift such moments to the surface using computational methods so that I can study them more closely.</p>

<p>I came to the project by first tagging such moments myself as I read through the text, but I quickly found myself approaching upwards of a hundred instances in a single novel-far too many for me to keep track of in any systematic way. What’s more, the practice made me aware of just how subjective my interpretation could be. Some moments, like this one, parse fairly well as speech. Others complicate distinctions between speech, narrative, and thought and are more difficult to identify. I became interested in the features of such moments. What is it about speech in a text that helps us to recognize it as such, if not for the quotation marks themselves? What could we learn about sound in a text from the ways in which it structures such sound moments?</p>

<p>These interests led me towards a particular kind of machine learning, supervised classification, as an alternate means of discovering similar moments. For those unfamiliar with the concept, an analogy might be helpful. As I am writing this post on a flight to HASTAC and just finished watching a romantic comedy,  these are the tools that I will work with. Think about the genre of the romantic comedy. I only know what this genre is by virtue of having seen my fair share of them over the course of my life. Over time I picked up a sense of the features associated with these films: a serendipitous meeting leads to infatuation, things often seem resolved before they really are, and the films often focus on romantic entanglements more than any other details. You might have other features in mind, and not all romantic comedies will conform to this list. That’s fine: no one’s assumptions about genre hold all of the time. But we can reasonably say that, the more romantic comedies I watch, the better my sense of what a romantic comedy is. My chances of being able to watch a movie and successfully identify it as conforming to this genre will improve with further viewing. Over time, I might also be able to develop a sense of how little or how much a film departs from these conventions.</p>

<p>Supervised classification works on a similar principle. By using the proper tools, we can feed a computer program examples of something in order to have it later identify similar objects. For this project, this process means training the computer to recognize and read for speech by giving it examples to work from. By providing examples of speech occurring within quotation marks, we can teach the program when quotation marks are likely to occur. By giving it examples of what I am calling ‘implied speech,’ it can learn how to identify those as well.</p>

<p>For this project, I analyzed Woolf texts downloaded from <a href="https://www.gutenberg.org/wiki/Main_Page">Project Gutenberg</a>. Eric and I put together scripts in Python 3 that used a package known as the <a href="http://nltk.org/">Natural Language Toolkit</a> for classifying. All of this work can be found at the project’s <a href="https://www.github.com/walshbr/woolf">GitHub repository</a>.</p>

<p>The project is still ongoing, and we are still working out some difficulties in our Python scripts. But I find the complications of the process to be compelling in their own right. For one, when working in this way we have to tell the computer what features we want it to pay attention to: a computer does not intuitively know how to make sense of the examples that we want to train it on. In the example of romantic comedies, I might say something along the lines of “while watching these films, watch out for the scenes and dialogue that use the word ‘love.’” We break down the larger genre into concrete features that can be pulled out so that the program knows what to watch out for.</p>

<p>To return to Woolf, punctuation marks are an obvious feature of interest: the author suggests that we have shifted into the realm of speech by inserting these grammatical markings. Find a quotation mark-you are likely to be looking at speech. But I am interested in just those moments where we lose those marks, so it helps to develop a sense of how they might work. We can then begin to extrapolate those same features to places where the punctuation marks might be missing. We have developed two models for understanding speech in this way: an external and an internal model. To illustrate, I have taken a single sentence and bolded what the model takes to be meaningful features according to each model. Each represents a different way of thinking about how we recognize something as speech.</p>

<p>External Model for Speech:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“I love walking in London,” <strong>said Mrs. Dalloway</strong>.  “Really it’s better than walking in the country.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The external model was our initial attempt to model speech. In it, we take an interest in the narrative context around quotation marks. In any text, we can say that there exist a certain range of keywords that signal a shift into speech: said, recalled, exclaimed, shouted, whispered, etc. Words like these help the narrative attribute speech to a character and are good indicators that speech is taking place. Given a list of words like this, we could reasonably build a sense of the locations around which speech is likely to be happening. So when training the program on this model, we had the classifier first identify locations of quotation marks. Around each quotation mark, the program took note of the diction and parts of speech that occurred within a given distance from the marking. We build up a sense of the context around speech.</p>

<p>Internal Model for Speech:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“<strong>I love walking in London</strong>,” said Mrs. Dalloway.  “<strong>Really it’s better than walking in the country</strong>.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The second model we have been working with works in an inverse direction: instead of taking an interest in the surrounding context of speech, an internal model assumes that there are meaningful characteristics within the quotation itself. In this example, we might notice that the shift to the first-person ‘I’ is a notable feature in a text that is otherwise largely written in the third person. This word suggests a shift in register. Each time this model encounters a quotation mark it continues until it finds a second quotation mark. The model then records the diction and parts of speech inside the pair of markings.</p>

<p>Each model suggests a distinct but related understanding for how sound works in the text. When I set out on this project, I had aimed to use the scripts to give me quantifiable evidence for moments of implied speech in Woolf’s work. The final step in this process, after all, is to actually use these models to identify speech: looking at texts they haven’t seen before, the scripts insert a caret marker every time they believe that a quotation mark should occur. But it quickly became apparent that the construction of the algorithms to describe such moments would be at least as interesting as any results that the project could produce. In the course of constructing them, I have had to think about the relationships among sound, text, and narrative in new ways.</p>

<p>The algorithms are each interpretative in the sense that they reflect my own assumptions about my object of study. The models also reflect assumptions about the process of reading, how it takes place, and about how a reader converts graphic markers into representations of sound. In this sense, the process of preparing for and executing text analysis reflects a certain phenomenology of reading as much as it does a methodology of digital study. The scripting itself is an object of inquiry in its own right and reflects my own interpretation of what speech can be. These assumptions are worked and reworked as I craft algorithms and python scripts, all of which are as shot through with humanistic inquiry and interpretive assumptions as any close readings.</p>

<p>For me, such revelations are the real reasons for pursuing digital study: attempting to describe complex humanities concepts computationally helps me to rethink basic assumptions about them that I had taken for granted. In the end, the pursuit of an algorithm to describe textual speech is nothing more or less than the pursuit of deeper and enriched theories of text and speech themselves.</p>

<p>##Postscript</p>

<p>I managed to take note of the questions I got when I presented this work at HASTAC, so what follows are paraphrases of my memory of them as well as some brief remarks that roughly reflect what I said in the moment. There may have been one other that I cannot quite recall, but alas such is the fallibility of the human condition.</p>

<p>Q: You distinguish between speech and implied speech, but do you account at all for the other types of speech in Woolf’s novels? What about speech that is remembered speech that happened in earlier timelines not reflected in the present tense of the narrative’s events?</p>

<p>A: I definitely encountered this during my first pass at tagging speech and implied speech in the text by hand. Instead of binaries like quoted speech/implied speech, I found myself wanting to mark for a range of speech types: present, actual; remembered, might not have happened; remembered incorrectly; remembered, implied; etc. I decided that a binary was more feasible for the machine learning problems that I was interested in, but the whole process just reinforced how subjective any reading process is: another reader might mark things differently. If these processes shape the construction of the theories that inform the project, then they necessarily also affect the algorithms themselves as well as the results they can produce. And it quickly becomes apparent that these decisions reflect a kind of phenomenology of reading as much as anything: they illlustrate my understanding of how a complicated set of markers and linguistic phenomenon contribute to our understanding that a passage is speech or not.</p>

<p>Q: Did you encounter any variations in the particular markings that Woolf was using to punctuate speech? Single quotes, etc., and how did you account for them?</p>

<p>A: Yes - the version of <em>Orlando</em> that I am working with used single quotes to notate speech. So I was forced to account for such edge cases. But the question points at two larger issues: one authorial and one bibliographical. As I worked on Woolf I was drawn to the idea of being able to run such a script against a wider corpus. Since the project seemed to impinging on how we also understand psychologized speech, it would be fascinating to be able to search for implied speech in other authors. But, if you are familiar with, say, Joyce, you might remember that he hated quotation marks and used dashes to denote speech. The question is how much can you account for such edge cases, and, if not, the study becomes only one of a single author’s idiosyncrasies (which still has value). But from there the question spirals outwards. At least one of my models (the internal one) relies on quotation marks themselves as boundary markers. The model assumes that quotation marks will come in pairs, and this is not always the case. Sometimes authors, intentionally or accidentally, omit a closing quotation mark. I had to massage the data in at least half a dozen places where there was no quotation mark in the text and where its lack was causing my program to fail entirely. As textual criticism has taught us, punctuation marks are the single most likely things to be modified over time during the process of textual transmission by scribes, typesetters, editors, and authors. So in that sense, I am not doing a study of Woolf’s punctuation so much as a study of Woolf’s punctuation in these particular versions of the texts. One can imagine an exhaustive study that works on all versions of all Woolf’s texts as a study that might approach some semblance of a correct and thorough reading. For this project, however, I elected to take the lesser of two evils that would still allow me to work through the material. I worked with the texts that I had. I take all of this as proof that you have to know your corpus and your own shortcomings in order to responsibly work on the materials - such knowledge helps you to validate your responses, question your results, and reframe your approaches.</p>

<p>Q: You talked a lot about text approaching sound, but what about the other way around - how do things like implied speech get reflected in audiobooks, for example? Is there anything in recordings of Woolf that imply a kind of punctuation that you can hear?</p>

<p>A: I wrote about this extensively in my dissertation, but for here I will just say that I think the textual phenomenon the questioner is referencing occurs on a continuum. Some graphic markings, like pictures, shapes, punctuation marks, do not clearly translate to sound. And the reverse is true: the sounded quality of a recording can only ever be remediated by a print text. There are no perfect analogues between different media forms. Audiobook performers might attempt to convey things like punctuation or implied speech (in the audiobook of <em>Ulysses</em>, for example, Jim Norton throws his voice and lowers his volume to suggest free indirect discourse). In the end, I think such moments are playing with an idea of what my dissertation calls audiotextuality, the idea that all texts recordings of texts, to varying degrees, contain both sound and print elements. The two spheres may work in harmony or against each other as a kind of productive friction. The idea is a slippery one, but I think it speaks to moments like the implied punctuation mark that come through in a particularly powerful audiobook recording.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Music Genre and Spotify Metadata]]></title>
    <link href="http://lanyon.getpoole.com/blog/2015/09/20/music-genre-and-spotify-metadata/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-20T16:51:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lanyon.getpoole.com/blog/2015/09/20/music-genre-and-spotify-metadata</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em><a href="http://scholarslab.org/?p=12173">Crossposted on the Scholars’ Lab blog</a></em></p>

<p>For the last couple weeks, I have been exploring APIs useful to sound studies for a sound recording and poetry project I am working on with former Scholars’ Lab fellow <a href="https://annieswafford.wordpress.com/">Annie Swafford</a>. I was especially drawn to playing around with <a href="https://www.spotify.com/us/">Spotify</a>, which has an <a href="https://developer.spotify.com/web-api/">API</a> that allows you to access metadata for the large catalog of music available through their service. The experiment described below focuses on genre: a notoriously messy category that we nonetheless rely on to tell us how to process the materials we read, view, or hear. Genre tells us what to expect from the art we take in, and our construction and reception of generic categories can tell us a lot about ourselves. In music, especially, genres and subgenres can activate fierce debates about authenticity and belonging. Does your favorite group qualify as “authentic” jazz? What composers do you have to know in order to think of yourself as a real classical music aficionado? Playing with an artist’s metadata can expose a lot of the assumptions that were made in its collection, and I was especially interested in the ways in which Spotify models relations among artists.</p>

<p>I wanted to explore Spotify’s metadata in a way that would model the interpretive messiness of generic categories. To do so, I built a program that bounces through Spotify’s metadata to produce multiple readings of the idea of genre in relation to a particular artist. Spotify offers a fairly robust API, and there are a number of handy wrappers that make it easier to work with. I used a Python module called <a href="http://spotipy.readthedocs.org/en/latest/">Spotipy</a> for the material below, and you can find <a href="https://github.com/bmw9t/spotify/blob/master/genre_machine.py">the code for my little genre experiment over on my GitHub page</a>. If you do try to run this on your own machine, note that you will need to clone Spotipy’s repository and manually install it from the terminal with the following command from within the downloaded repository:</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>$ python setup.py install
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Pip will install an older distribution of the code that will only run in Python 2, but Spotipy’s GitHub page has a more recent release that is compatible with Python 3.</p>

<p>When run, the program outputs what I like to think of as the equivalent of music nerds arguing over musical genres. You provide an artist name and a number, and the terminal will work through Spotify’s API to produce the specified number of individual “mappings” of that artist’s genre as well as an aggregate list of all their associated genres. The program starts by pulling out all the genre categories associated with the given artist as well as those given to artists that Spotify flags as related. Once finished, the program picks one of those related artists at random and continues to do the same until the process returns no new genre categories, building up a list of associated genres over time.</p>

<p>So, in short, you give the program an artist and it offers you a few attempts at describing that artist generically using Spotify’s catalog, the computational equivalent of instigating an argument about genre in your local record store. Here are the results for running the program three times for the band New Order:</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Individual genre maps

Just one nerd's opinions on New Order:

['dance rock', 'new wave', 'permanent wave', 'new romantic', 'new wave pop', 'hi nrg', 'europop', 'power pop', 'album rock']

Just one nerd's opinions on New Order:

['dance rock', 'new wave', 'permanent wave', 'gothic metal', 'j-metal', 'visual kei', 'intelligent dance music', 'uk post-punk', 'metropopolis', 'ambient', 'big beat', 'electronic', 'illbient', 'piano rock', 'trance', 'progressive house', 'progressive trance', 'uplifting trance', 'quebecois', 'deep uplifting trance', 'garage rock', 'neo-psychedelic', 'space rock', 'japanese psychedelic']

Just one nerd's opinions on New Order:

['dance rock', 'new wave', 'permanent wave', 'uk post-punk', 'gothic rock', 'discofox', 'madchester', 'britpop', 'latin', 'latin pop', 'teen pop', 'classic colombian pop', 'rai', 'pop rap', 'southern hip hop', 'trap music', 'deep rai']

Aggregate genre map for New Order:

['dance rock', 'new wave', 'permanent wave', 'new romantic', 'new wave pop', 'hi nrg', 'europop', 'power pop', 'album rock', 'gothic metal', 'j-metal', 'visual kei', 'intelligent dance music', 'uk post-punk', 'metropopolis', 'ambient', 'big beat', 'electronic', 'illbient', 'piano rock', 'trance', 'progressive house', 'progressive trance', 'uplifting trance', 'quebecois', 'deep uplifting trance', 'garage rock', 'neo-psychedelic', 'space rock', 'japanese psychedelic', 'gothic rock', 'discofox', 'madchester', 'britpop', 'latin', 'latin pop', 'teen pop', 'classic colombian pop', 'rai', 'pop rap', 'southern hip hop', 'trap music', 'deep rai']
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>In each case, the genre maps all begin the same, with the categories directly assigned to the source artist. Because the process is slightly random, the program eventually maps the same artist’s genre differently each time. For each iteration, the program runs until twenty randomly selected related artists return no new genre categories, which I take to be a kind of threshold of completion for one understanding of an artist’s genre.</p>

<p>The results suggest an amalgam of generic influence, shared characteristics, common lineages, and overlapping angles of approach. The decisions I made in how the program interacts with Spotify’s metadata suggest a definition of genre like the one offered by Alastair Fowler: “Representatives of a genre may then be regarded as making up a family whose septs and individual members are related in various ways, without necessarily having any single feature shared in common by all” (41). Genre is fluid and a matter of interpretive opinion - it is not necessarily based on objective links. The program reflects this in its results: sometimes a particular generic mapping feels very coherent, while at other times the script finds its way to very bizarre tangents. The connections do exist in the metadata if you drill down deeply enough, and it is possible to reproduce the links that brought about such output. But the more leaps the program takes from the original artist the more tenuous the connections appear to be. As I wrote this sentence, the program suggested a connection between garage rock revivalists The Strokes and big band jazz music: such output looks less like a conversation among music nerds and more like the material for a Ph.D. dissertation. As the program illustrates, generic description is the beginning of interpretation - not the ending.</p>

<p>Of course, the program does not actually search all music ever: it only has access to the metadata for artists listed in Spotify, and some artists like Prince or the Beatles are notoriously missing from the catalog. Major figures like these have artist pages that serve as stubs for content drawn largely from compilation CDs, and the program can successfully crawl through these results. But this wrinkle points to a larger fact: the results the program produces are as skewed as the collection of musicians in the service’s catalog. Many of the errors I had to troubleshoot were related to the uneven nature of the catalog: early versions of the script were thrown into disarray when Spotify listed no related artists for a musician. On occasion, the API suggested a related artist who did not actually have an artist page in the system (often the case with new or less-established musicians). I massaged these gaps to make this particular exercise work (you’ll now get a tongue in cheek “Musical dead end” or “Artist deleted from Spotify” output for them), but the silences in the archive offer significant reminders of the commercial politics that go into generic and archival formation, particularly when an archive is proprietary. I can imagine tweaking things slightly to create a script that produces only those archival gaps, but that is work for another day. In the meantime, I’ll be trying to figure out <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yeezus">how Kanye West might be considered Christmas music</a>.</p>

<p>Works Cited:</p>

<p>Fowler, Alastair David Shaw. Kinds of Literature: An Introduction to the Theory of Genres and Modes. Repr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1997. Print.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Virginia Woolf, Natural Language Processing, and the Quotation Mark]]></title>
    <link href="http://lanyon.getpoole.com/blog/2015/09/10/woolf-and-the-quotation-mark/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-10T11:21:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lanyon.getpoole.com/blog/2015/09/10/woolf-and-the-quotation-mark</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Crossposted on the <a href="http://scholarslab.org/?p=12117/">Scholars’ Lab blog</a></em></p>

<p>For my fellowship in the Scholars’ Lab this year I’ll be working with <a href="http://scholarslab.org/people/eric-rochester/">Eric</a> to expand a project we began last year on Virginia Woolf and natural language processing. My dissertation focuses on sound recordings and modernism, and this year I will focus on how Woolf’s quotation marks offer evidence of her engagement with sound as a textual device. In my reading, the quotation mark is the most obvious point at which sound meets text, the most heavily used sound recording technology in use by writers. Patterns in quotation mark usage across large corpora can tell us a lot about the role that sound plays in literature, but, as you might expect, there are <em>lots</em> of quotation marks - hundreds or thousands in any given text. Computational methods can help us make sense of the vast number and turn them into reasonable objects of study.</p>

<p>You can find more information in <a href="http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/hearing-silent-woolf/">this post</a> about my thinking on quotation marks and some preliminary results from thinking about them in relation to Woolf. As I discuss there, finding quotation marks in a text is not especially challenging, but this year Eric and I will be focusing on a particular wrinkle in Woolf’s use of the marks, best conveyed in <em>The Hours</em>, Michael Cunningham’s late-century riff on Virginia Woolf. In <em>The Hours</em>, Cunningham offers a fictionalized version of Woolf meditating on her composition process:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>She passes a couple, a man and woman younger than herself, walking together, leisurely, bent towards each other in the soft lemon-colored glow of a streetlamp, talking (she hears the man, “told me <em>something something something</em> in this establishment, <em>something something</em>, harrumph, indeed”) (166).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The repeated “<em>somethings</em>” of the passage suggest the character’s imperfect experience of the conversation as well as the limits of her senses. As the moment is conveyed through the character’s perspective, the conversation will always be incomplete. Recording technology was largely unreliable during the early days of the twentieth century, and, similarly, the sound record of this conversation as given by the text is already degraded before we hear it. Cunningham points to how the sounded voice is given character in the ears of the listener, and, in a print context, in the pen of the writer. A printed voice can speak in a variety of ways and in a variety of modes.</p>

<p>Cunningham’s passage contains echoes of what will eventually be the famous first sentence of Woolf’s <em>Mrs. Dalloway</em>: “Mrs. Dalloway said she would buy the flowers herself.” The text implies that Mrs. Dalloway speaks, but it does not mark it as such: the same conversational tone in Cunningham remains here, but the narrator does not differentiate sound event from narrative by using quotation marks. We see moments of indirect speech like this all the time, when discourse becomes submerged in the texture of the narrative, but it doesn’t disappear entirely. Speech implies a lot: social relations, the thoughts of a speaking body, among others. Things get muddy when the line between narrative voice and speech becomes unclear. If quotation marks imply a different level of speech than unquoted speech, might they also imply changes in the social relations they represent?</p>

<p><em>Mrs. Dalloway</em> is filled with moments like these, and this year I’ll be working to find ways to float them to the surface of the text. Examining these moments can tell us how conversation changes during the period, what people are talking about and for, how we conceive of the limits of print and sound, and about changing priorities in literary aesthetics. The goal this year is to train the computer to identify moments like this, moments that a human reader would be able to parse as spoken but that are not marked as such. Our first pass will be to work with the quoted material, which we can easily identify to build a series of trigger words that Woolf uses to flag speech as sound (said, asked, called, etc.). With this lexicon, we can then look for instances in her corpus where they pop up without punctuation. Teaching the computer to classify these passages correctly will be a big task, and this process alone will offer me lots of new material to work with as I untangle the relationship between modernist print and sound. In upcoming posts I’ll talk more about the process of learning natural language processing and about some preliminary results and problems. Stay tuned!</p>

<p>Works Cited:</p>

<p>Cunningham, Michael. <em>The Hours</em>. New York: Picador USA : Distributed by Holtzbrinck Publishers, 2002. Print.</p>

<p>Woolf, Virginia. <em>Mrs. Dalloway</em>. 1st Harvest/HBJ ed. San Diego: Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, 1990. Print.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hearing Silent Woolf]]></title>
    <link href="http://lanyon.getpoole.com/blog/2015/03/23/woolf-huskey/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-23T16:37:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lanyon.getpoole.com/blog/2015/03/23/woolf-huskey</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>[This week I presented at the <a href="http://gradcouncil.com/2015-sessions/">2015 Huskey Research Exhibition</a> at UVA. The talk was delivered from very schematic notes, but below is a rough recreation of what I discussed. The talk I gave is a crash course in a new project I’ve started working on with the generous help of the <a href="http://scholarslab.org">Scholars’ Lab</a> that thinks about sound in Virginia Woolf’s career using computational methods. <a href="http://www.ericrochester.com/">Eric Rochester</a>, especially, has been endlessly giving of his time and expertise, helping me think through and prototype work on this material. The talk wound up receiving first prize for the digital humanities panel of which I was a part. The project is still very much inchoate, and I’d welcome thoughts on it.]</em></p>

<p>When I talk to you, you make certain assumptions about me as a person based on what you’re hearing. You decide whether or not I might be worth paying attention to, and you develop a sense of our social relations based around the sound of my voice. The voice conveys and generates assumptions about the body and about power: am I making myself heard? Am I registering as a speaking voice? Am I worth listening to?</p>

<p><a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Day_14_Occupy_Wall_Street_September_30_2011_Shankbone_2.JPG "><img src="/assets/images/occupy.jpg" width="60%" class="left" alt="Occupy Wall Street September 30 2011" /></a></p>

<p>The human microphone, made famous by Occupy Wall Street, nicely encapsulates the social dimensions of sound that interest me: one person speaks, and the people around her repeat what she says more loudly, again and again, amplifying the human voice without technology. Sound literally moves through multiple bodies and structures the social relations between people, and the whole movement is an attempt to make a group of people heard by those who would rather not listen.</p>

<p>As a literary scholar, I am interested in how texts can speak in similar ways. The texts we read frequently contain large amounts of speech within them: conversations, monologues, poetic voice, etc. We talk about sound in texts all the time, and the same social and political dimensions of sound still remain even if a text appears silent on the page. If who can be heard and who gets to speak are both contested questions in the real world, they continue to structure our experiences of printed universes.</p>

<p>All of this brings me to the quotation mark. The humble piece of punctuation does a lot of work for us every day, and I want to think more closely about how it can help us understand how texts speak. The quotation mark is the most obvious point at which sound meets text. Computational methods tend to focus on the vocabulary of a text as the building blocks of meaning, but they can also help us turn quotation marks into objects of inquiry. Quotation marks can tell us a lot about how texts engage with the human voice, but there are <em>lots</em> of them in texts. Digital methods can help us make sense of the scale.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/woolf.jpg" width="40%" class="right" alt="Woolf portrait" />I examine Virginia Woolf’s quotation marks, in particular, for a number of reasons. Aesthetically, we can see her bridging the Victorian and modernist literary periods, though she tends to fall in with the latter of the two. Politically, she lived through periods of intense social and political upheaval at the beginning of the twentieth century. Very few recordings of Woolf remain, but she nonetheless thought deeply about sound recording. The worldwide market for gramophones exploded during her lifetime, and her texts frequently featured technologies of sound reproduction. Woolf’s gramophones frequently malfunction in her novels, and I’m interested in seeing how her quotation marks might analogously be irregular or broken intentionally. Woolf is especially good for thinking about punctuation marks in this way: she owned a printing press, and she often set type herself.</p>

<p>The following series of histograms gives a rough estimation of how Woolf’s use of quotation changes over the course of her career. <a href="https://github.com/erochest/woolf/commits/master">On GitHub</a> you can find the script I’ve been working on with Eric to generate these results. The number of quotations is plotted on the y-axis against their position in the novel on the x-axis, so each histogram represents more quoted speech with higher bars and more concentrated darknesses. If you have an especially good understanding of a particular novel, <em>Mrs. Dalloway</em>, say, you could pick out moments of intense conversation based on sudden spikes in the number of quotations. The histograms are organized in such a way that to read chronologically through Woolf’s career you would read left to right line by line, as you would the text of a book. The top-left histogram is Woolf’s earliest novel, the bottom-right corner her last.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/huskey-histograms/1915_the_voyage_out.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/huskey-histograms/1915_the_voyage_out.jpg" width="32%" alt="Histogram of quotation use in The Voyage Out" /></a>
<a href="/assets/images/huskey-histograms/1919_night_and_day.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/huskey-histograms/1919_night_and_day.jpg" width="32%" alt="Histogram of quotation use in Night and Day" /></a>
<a href="/assets/images/huskey-histograms/1922_jacobs_room.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/huskey-histograms/1922_jacobs_room.jpg" width="32%" alt="Histogram of quotation use in Jacob's Room" /></a>
<a href="/assets/images/huskey-histograms/1925_mrs.dalloway.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/huskey-histograms/1925_mrs.dalloway.jpg" width="32%" alt="Histogram of quotation use in Mrs. Dalloway" /></a>
<a href="/assets/images/huskey-histograms/1927_to_the_lighthouse.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/huskey-histograms/1927_to_the_lighthouse.jpg" alt="Histogram of quotation use in To the Lighthouse" width="32%" /></a>
<a href="/assets/images/huskey-histograms/1928_orlando.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/huskey-histograms/1928_orlando.jpg" width="32%" alt="Histogram of quotation use in Orlando" /></a>
<a href="/assets/images/huskey-histograms/1931_the_waves.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/huskey-histograms/1931_the_waves.jpg" width="32%" alt="Histogram of quotation use in The Waves" /></a>
<a href="/assets/images/huskey-histograms/1937_the_years.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/huskey-histograms/1937_the_years.jpg" width="32%" alt="Histogram of quotation use in The Years" /></a>
<a href="/assets/images/huskey-histograms/1941_between_the_acts.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/huskey-histograms/1941_between_the_acts.jpg" width="32%" alt="Histogram of quotation use in Between the Acts" /></a></p>

<p>To my eye, the output suggests high concentrations of conversation in the novels at the beginning and ending of Woolf’s career. We can see that her middle period, especially, appears to have a significant decrease in the amount of quoted speech. In one sense, this might make sense to someone familiar with Woolf’s career. Her first two novels feel more typically Victorian in their aesthetics, and she really gets into the thick of modernist experiment with her third novel. One way we often describe the shift from Victorian to the modernist period is as a shift inward, away from society and towards the psychology of the self. So it makes sense that we might see the amount of conversation between multiple speaking bodies significantly fall away over the course of those novels. <a href="/assets/images/huskey-histograms/1931_the_waves.jpg">The seventh histogram</a> is especially interesting, because it suggests the least amount of speech of anything in her corpus. But if we visualize things a different way, we see that this novel, <em>The Waves</em>, actually shows a huge spike in punctuated speech. This graph represents the percentage of each text that is contained within quotation marks, the amount of text represented as punctuated speech.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/huskey-histograms/percentage-quoted.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/huskey-histograms/percentage-quoted.jpg" class="right" alt="Graph of percentage of quoted material in The Waves" /></a></p>

<p>This might look like a problem with the data: how could the text with the fewest number of quotations also have the highest percentage of quoted speech? But the script is actually giving me exactly what I asked for: <em>The Waves</em> is a series of monologues by six disembodied voices, and the amount of non-speech text is extremely small. More generally, charting the percentage of quoted speech in the corpus appears to support my general readings of the original nine histograms: roughly three times as much punctuated speech in the early novels as in the middle period, with a slight leveling off in the end of her career.</p>

<p>We could think of <em>The Waves</em> as an anomaly, but I think it more clearly calls for a revision of such a reading of speech in Woolf’s career. The spike in quoted speech is a hint that there is something else going on in Woolf’s work. Perhaps we can use the example of <em>The Waves</em> to propose that there might be a range of discourses, of types of speech in Woolf’s corpus. Before I suggested that speech diminished in the middle of Woolf’s career, but that’s not exactly true. My suspicion is that it just enters a different mode. Consider these two passages, both quoted from <em>Mrs. Dalloway</em>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Mrs. Dalloway said she would buy the flowers herself.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Times without number Clarissa had visited Evelyn Whitbread in a nursing home.  Was Evelyn ill again?  Evelyn was a good deal out of sorts, said Hugh, intimating by a kind of pout or swell of his very well-covered, manly, extremely handsome, perfectly upholstered body (he was almost too well dressed always, but presumably had to be, with his little job at Court) that his wife had some internal ailment, nothing serious, which, as an old friend, Clarissa Dalloway would quite understand without requiring him to specify.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In each case, the text implies speech by Mrs. Dalloway and by Hugh without marking it as such with punctuation marks. Discourse becomes submerged in the texture of the narrative, but it doesn’t disappear entirely. Moments like these suggest a range of discourses in Woolf’s corpus: dialogue, monologue, conversation, punctuated, implied, etc. All of these speech types have different implications, but it’s difficult to get a handle on them because of their scale. I began the project by simply trying to mark down moments of implied speech in <em>Mrs. Dalloway</em> by hand. Once I got to about two hundred, it seemed like it was time to ask the computer for help.</p>

<p>The current plan moving forward is to build a corpus of test passages containing both quoted speech and implied speech, train a python script against this set of passages, and then use this same script to search for instances of implied speech throughout Woolf’s corpus. Theoretically, at least, the script will search for a series of words that flag text as implied speech to a human reader - said, recalled, exclaimed, etc. Using this lexicon as a basis, the script would then pull out the context surrounding these words to produce a database of sentences meant to serve as speech. At Eric’s suggestion, I’m currently exploring the <a href="http://www.nltk.org/index.html">Natural Language Toolkit</a> to take a stab at all of this. My own hypothesis is that there will be an inverse relationship between quoted speech and implied speech in her corpus, that the amount of speech left unflagged by quotation marks will increase in the middle of Woolf’s career. Once I have all this material, I’ll be able to subject the results to further analysis and to think more deeply about speech in Woolf’s work. Who speaks? What about? What counts as a voice, and what is left in an ambiguous, unsounded state?</p>

<p>The project is very much in its beginning stages, but it’s already opening up the way that I think about speech in Woolf’s text. It tries to untangle the relationship between our print record and our sonic record, and further work will help show how discourse is unfolding over time in the modernist period.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Devil in the Recording]]></title>
    <link href="http://lanyon.getpoole.com/blog/2015/01/12/deformance-talk/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-12T10:29:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://lanyon.getpoole.com/blog/2015/01/12/deformance-talk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[The following is an only slightly modified version of the talk I gave at the <a href="http://ach.org/">ACH</a>’s panel on “Digital Deformance and Scholarly Forms” at the 2015 MLA conference. For more details on how to reverse audio recordings, see my <a href="http://walshbr.github.io/blog/2015/01/05/deformance/">previous post on the subject</a>.]</p>

<p><strong>The Devil in the Recording: Deformative Listening and Sound Reproduction</strong></p>

<p>It’s a well-known fact that you can find the devil in popular music. Simply take Led Zeppelin’s “Stairway to Heaven,” play it backwards, and voila. You’ll get messages for, if not by, the Lord of the Flies. Obviously I’m being facetious. Few, if any, take this claim seriously, but it does offer serious ways to think about deformance in the context of sound recordings, particularly those with linguistic or literary content. The digital method of deformance I’ll speak about today, then, is a simple one. Using open source tools like <a href="http://audacity.sourceforge.net/">Audacity</a>, it’s easier than ever to play recordings backwards, to reverse a sound clip with the flip of a switch. I’ll touch just a bit on the history of such methods as they pertain to music and then speculate as to what they can tell us about approaches to thinking about literary sound recordings. I’m a modernist, and my examples will reflect this bias. My ultimate conclusions are as follows. First: reading backwards juxtaposed against audio reversal reveals the unique character of literary sound recordings to be simultaneously sounded and print, to be audiotextual objects as I call them. Second: deformance can offer us new modes for thinking about media failures and malfunctions that actually do exist constantly and all around us. In particular, audio deformance is something that the modernists were keenly interested in, and deformance as a practice can get us closer to the relationships they had with media.</p>

<p>So here is part of “Stairway to Heaven” backwards.</p>

<audio controls=""><source src="/assets/mp3s/mla-2015/zeppelin_reversed.mp3" type="audio/mpeg" /><source src="/assets/ogg/mla-2015/zeppelin_reversed.ogg" type="audio/ogg" />Your browser does not support this audio format.</audio>

<p>Source: <a href="http://youtu.be/zGsUcPdPWBg?t=47s">http://youtu.be/zGsUcPdPWBg?t=47s</a></p>

<p>Can’t you hear the devil? The “Stairway to Satan,” as I will call it, suggests that we can find new linguistic content in an already extant sound message. Detractors of the “Stairway to Satan” narrative (numerous on Youtube if you care to check them out) suggest that this is just a function of our minds wanting to make sense of chaos. Is this gibberish? Or is it a collection of scattered sound components that can be reconstituted into a whole? In <a href="http://www2.iath.virginia.edu/jjm2f/old/deform.html">Lisa Samuels and Jerome McGann’s essay on deformance</a> from which this panel takes its cue, they discuss reading Emily Dickinson’s poetry backwards in a mode not too far removed from this discussion. Reading backwards can throw into sharp relief the linguistic components, the very pieces that make up a poem, and at the end of the day, you still have the lines, the words, or even the component letters. It’s possible to reassemble these into semantic meanings.</p>

<p>But sound recordings are something different. They are bound in time in a different way. Daniel Albright in <em>Untwisting the Serpent</em> describes music by way of “Lessing’s famous distinction between the spatially juxtapositive arts of <em>nebeinander</em>, such as painting, sculpture, and architecture, and the temporally progressive arts of <em>nacheinander</em>, such as poetry and music” (9). Our experience of music and poetry depend upon their ability to move forward in time. To put the distinction in the context of deformance: you can move around a sculpture and view it from different angles, but it remains the same sculpture. Deform a musical recording by reversing its waveform, however, and you end with a different musical artifact entirely, one with different component parts. Hence, it can sound like gibberish.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/waveform-large.jpg" width="50%" class="right" alt="large waveform" /></p>

<p>Here is the waveform for the Zeppelin clip. The waveform here is a charting of intensity over time, and the reversal literally changes the original artifact. It’s a mirror image, but our ears are hard-pressed to be able to reconnect the new object to its original. Many kinds of deformance you can do on an audio recording would work in the same way – alter the pitches, smash them tighter, stretch them out, etc. You alter that wave, and you get something else entirely. At what point does it become something new?</p>

<p>But some reversed audio still sounds like a recognizable tune. Behind the “Stairway to Satan” claim is a long history behind it of musical reversal and mirroring. Musicians and listeners have been fascinated with the vectored nature of sound for centuries, and composers have experimented with reversal as a spur to creativity for ages. Take this melody.</p>

<video width="320" height="240" controls="">
  <source src="/assets/videos/canon-retrogrado.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
Your browser does not support the video tag.
</video>

<p>Source: <a href="http://www.teoria.com/en/reference/q-r/retrograde.php">http://www.teoria.com/en/reference/q-r/retrograde.php</a></p>

<p>The melody of the first ten measures is followed by a retrograde repetition of itself, meaning that it is a musical palindrome. All of the intervals of this first section become reversed and, if you were to fold the melody in upon itself, it would perfectly line up. Playing backwards is itself built into the creative process. The playback reflects this as the bouncing ball literally moves backwards on the page, but, if you were to write it out, it would look quite different. The kind of deformance that I am describing, that Zeppelin conspiracy theorists lament, and that Samuels and McGann suggest – it’s built into the music itself.</p>

<p>The melodic reversal of music like this works because, as Walter Pater taught us, music can be thought of as a “perfect identification of matter and form.” Flip the melody and you do not lose information, you get a new melody. The new object is still discernible as music because it is new music. The addition of linguistic content complicates the question - phonemes when reversed do not necessarily and easily coordinate with other phonemes. A recorded object with linguistic content has two distinct characters, each of which overlap with the other. It’s an obvious point, but one that I think has profound implications.</p>

<p>In Langston Hughes’s 1958 recording of “Motto” in collaboration with Charles Mingus and Leonard Feather, we can start to approach some useful conclusions about what this might all mean. The excerpt starts with an instrumental section and then Hughes comes in. So keep in mind that, in the reversal, we’ll hear the poetry first and then the instrumental part.</p>

<p>“Motto”</p>

<audio controls=""><source src="/assets/mp3s/mla-2015/motto.mp3" type="audio/mpeg" /><source src="/assets/ogg/mla-2015/5_motto.ogg" type="audio/ogg" />Your browser does not support this audio format.</audio>

<p>“Motto” Reversed</p>

<audio controls=""><source src="/assets/mp3s/mla-2015/motto_reversed.mp3" type="audio/mpeg" /><source src="/assets/ogg/mla-2015/motto_reversed.ogg" type="audio/ogg" />Your browser does not support this audio format.</audio>

<p>The recording is a useful analogy for vocal sound recordings more generally in that it has two distinct pieces – a musical (non-verbal sound) component, and a recorded voice (with linguistic content). The two elements often intertwine and are not easily separated (this example not withstanding). You can hear, I think, the stark difference between the reversed poetic content by Hughes and the reversed instrumental content. Hughes reversed sounds like nonsense, while the saxophone in particular still sounds like something of a melody. The digital reversal of sound recordings treats them both as waveforms with no semantic content – it reverses them just as easily and happily as it would any other sound recording.</p>

<p>We might expect the practice of deformance to throw into sharp relief the status of these recordings as sound objects. The pops, silences, and phonetic meanings of a reading suddenly become especially salient, and we might expect this reversal to make us hyper-aware of their sounded nature. In theory the deformance of these recordings more easily allows us to practice what Charles Bernstein has called “close listening,” examining the sounded nature of these objects. But, as the sounds themselves become distorted almost beyond recognition, the method can only provide clues towards such a practice. We might gain general senses, as with the Hughes, of the general prominence of certain registers or frequencies, silences and gaps, or of sections that are particularly filled with sonic activity. All of these might provide hints of content that might bear out fruitful analysis when put forwards again.</p>

<p>Deformance of poetic recordings forces us to consider the nature of recorded literary recordings anew. We might extrapolate from the character of this recording that all recorded voices contain a linguistic element as well an audible one. Not fully audio nor fully textual artifacts, I want to say that they are, instead something we might call audiotextual, a term that Jason Camlot has recently used in relation to the classification of Victorian literary recordings as an expansion of McGann’s own historicist approach to textual criticism.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/audiotextual.jpg" width="40%" class="right" alt="Venn diagram of AudioTextual" /></p>

<p>I want to use the term as a play on audiovisual to describe the state of such sound recordings. Like the Hughes recording, with both an instrumental, sound component as well as a linguistic one, audiotextual recordings exist in sound as well as in print. It’s a fairly simple idea, but I think it is one that often gets concerned as we discuss sound recordings. Literary sound recordings are not reducible to their relationship with a print text: they have both sounded <em>and</em> print components. Audiobooks, in particular, not being “poetic” often seem to get left out of close listenings and treated as mere reproductions of print texts. If you read the reviews of any Amazon audiobook or <a href="http://www.librivox.org">LibriVox</a> recording, you will see hundreds of people who expect an audiobook to be an unmediated, honest representation of the print origin. Audiotextual might be used equally to describe both Hughes’s literary sound recordings as well as Hughes’s poetry itself, saturated as it is with traces of the live performance techniques of jazz and blues musicians.</p>

<p>More profoundly, I think sound recording during the modernist period is an especially good candidate for deformative acts of listening and interpretation. It is well-known and often-noted that modernist authors were obsessed with the gramophone, but consider the nature of such representations. The gramophones are most often marked by the materiality of their failures. In the “Hades” episode of <em>Ulysses</em>, the machine disintegrates into parody at the very moment at which it is meant to revive the voice of a dead relative:  “After dinner on a Sunday. Put on poor old greatgrandfather Kraahraark! Hellohellohello amawfullyglad kraark awfullygladaseeagain hellohello amawf krpthsth” (114). Sound reproduction during the period was not marked by the high fidelity, by the ability to authentically reproduce a deceptively “real” recording of life. It is a flawed act marked, as in Joyce’s case, by skipping needles, locked grooves, and hissing machines. For Joyce, this means uncovering a renewed sense that sound recordings were imperfect things, themselves subject to deformation by their own young technology. Joyce thinks of the gramophone recording as an object that can reach back into the past. He does not play it backwards as such, but the very act of playing the voice reverses time itself. And it does so in a manner that deforms the recording, altering its shape and transmission as a natural and comical part of the playback process.</p>

<p>Woolf’s failing gramophone in <em>Between the Acts</em> draws the elements of my short talk together nicely and can act as a closing image. During the pageant play at the heart of the text, a malfunctioning gramophone provides musical and narrative accompaniment: “The gramophone gurgled Unity-Dispersity. It gurgled Un…dis…And ceased” (201). The words themselves break apart into component syllables; semantic meaning evaporates as the grain of language pushes to the surface, and the heard word gives way to the gurgling materiality of the record itself. Woolf makes us hear the sound of the words as bound with their meanings. Her gramophone falls into locked grooves throughout the novel, transfixing its listeners and forming a community out of the audience of listeners by expanding the time with which they engage with each other. Not reversing time, certainly, but she does meditate on the ability of a malfunctioning gramophone to create anew through performance and deformance.</p>

<p>For Joyce and Woolf, the machines fail as often as they succeed. Deformance is thoroughly entwined with such performances. We may even go so far as to say that sound reproduction of this sort is a always kind of deformance, that no media form provides a pure, unaltered transmission of its content. As a critical practice, deformance, a systematic and intentionally disruptive form of engagement with materials, actually gets us closer to the kinds of media relationships that these authors would have known. The practice can offer us new perspective on literary and sonic materials, sure, but it can also provide us with something older. Deformative listening then, might be a practice of recovery, of attempting to recreate the phenomenological experience of a 1920s gramophone listening. The devil in the recording proves to be not the sort that conspiracy theorists would have you believe. The darkness lurking beneath sound recordings, be they musical or literary in nature, is the shadow of the materials, their very real failures, and the deformance that has always been present anytime we put needle to disc.</p>

<p><strong>Works Cited</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Albright, Daniel. <em>Untwisting the Serpent: Modernism in Music, Literature, and Other Arts</em>. Chicago, Ill: University of Chicago Press, 2000. Print.</li>
<li>Bernstein, Charles, ed. <em>Close Listening: Poetry and the Performed Word</em>. Oxford University Press, USA, 1998. Print.</li>
<li>Hughes, Langston, Leonard Feather, and Charles Mingus. <em>Weary Blues</em>. MGM, 1959. CD.</li>
<li>Joyce, James. <em>Ulysses</em>. Vintage, 1990. Print.</li>
<li>Pater, Walter. “<a href="http://www.victorianweb.org/authors/pater/renaissance/7.html">The School of Giorgione</a>.” <em>The Renaissance: Studies in Art and Poetry</em>. 1873. Web.</li>
<li>Woolf, Virginia. <em>Between the Acts</em>. New York: Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, 1969. Print.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
