<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Brandon Walsh]]></title>
  <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-02T13:57:16-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://bmw9t.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brandon Walsh]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SelfControl for Working on the Web]]></title>
    <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/07/28/working-web/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-28T20:53:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/07/28/working-web</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The web enables virtually all of my work as a graduate student, but it can all too easily become a powerful distraction. Sometimes it helps to have a few practical aids in the war against procrastination. Of the several tools that I’ve tried - <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-us/firefox/addon/foxfilter/">Fox Filter</a>, <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/stayfocusd/laankejkbhbdhmipfmgcngdelahlfoji?hl=en">StayFocused</a>, and <a href="http://macfreedom.com/">Freedom</a> - <a href="http://selfcontrolapp.com/">SelfControl</a> remains my favorite. SelfControl provides relentless self-regulating freedom from procrastination. Best of all, it is free.</p>

<p><img src="http://bmw9t.github.com/images/Self_Control_1.jpg" width="60%" class="left"></p>

<p>SelfControl is an app for Mac OS X that, unlike FoxFilter or StayFocused, works across browsers. When enabled, SelfControl asks you to specify how long you want to block a list of domains, up to 24 hours. The app also sports a “Whitelist” function that works in reverse, disabling everything except for a handful of specified domains.</p>

<p>Once activated, the blocks remain live until a particularly menacing timer runs down, and only some minor computer hacking will allow you to disable the app’s functionality. This relentlessness is SelfControl’s best and worst feature. The timed function is particularly good for short bursts of productivity, ie. an hour or shorter, but disabling the web for any longer feels too risky: it is easy to imagine time-sensitive emails going unanswered because you have blocked access to the internet for the next five hours.</p>

<p><img src="http://bmw9t.github.com/images/Self_Control_2.jpg" class="right"></p>

<p>At its best, SelfControl allows me to temper the impulse to spend a lot of time hovering around my inbox; I tend to use SelfControl in hour long chunks to allow sessions of distraction-free work in between e-mail checks. How do you stay productive during long hours on the computer?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Praxis Posts]]></title>
    <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/07/23/praxis/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-23T21:19:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/07/23/praxis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>All last year I was a <a href="http://praxis.scholarslab.org/">Praxis Fellow</a> in the <a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/">Scholars&#8217; Lab</a>, where they gave us a &#8220;soup to nuts&#8221; crash course in all things digital humanities. As a part of the program, the fellows were asked to reflect periodically on their experiences on the Scholars&#8217; Lab blog.</p>

<p>I did not do a good job of continually cross-posting those blog posts to this site, so I wanted to make sure that they were properly linked here. I posted with the program on a variety of topics from my work as a developer, to reflections on collaborative programming, to our own plan for the year. Many of the posts relate to <a href="http://www.prism.scholarslab.org">Prism</a>, the tool we built over the course of the year. The Scholars&#8217; Lab has <a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/people/brandon-walsh/">a list of all my posts to date</a>. Below I included the posts with a short gloss.</p>

<ol>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/hello-world/">Hello World</a>: I reflect on how our team would interact with the previous year&#8217;s Praxis team.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/failure/">Failure</a>: On the importance of failing in public and my first stab at creating a personal website.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/marking-and-explanation-in-prism-2/">Marking and Explanation in Prism</a>: Thoughts on the marking interface in Prism and its implications for the interpretive process.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/the-direction-of-prism/">The Direction of Prism</a>: Attempts to reflect broadly on how particular types of changes to the project might affect its direction.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/prism-proposal-against-anonymity/">Prism Proposal: Against Anonymity</a>: An argument for the redesign of Prism to track individual users in relation to the total dataset.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/poster-abstract-and-code-camp/">Poster Abstract and Code Camp</a>: Discusses our DH2013 poster abstract and first reflections on learning code.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/your-digital-life-in-140-characters/">Your Digital Life in 140 Characters</a>: I discuss my first foray into Twitter.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/fizzing-buzzing/">Fizzing, Buzzing</a>: Links my solution to the Fizz Buzz programming homework.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/grading-in-ruby/">Grading in Ruby</a>: I develop a very basic program that will compute your end of semester grading for you.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/ruby-grading-2-0/">Ruby Grading 2.0</a>: I attempt to redesign the same grading program to have cleaner, more elegant code.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/looking-forward/">Looking Forward</a>: Possible directions for the project.  </li>
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/on-learning-code/">On Learning Code</a>: Discusses the online tools that I found most helpful for learning coding.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/omniauth/">Omniauth</a>: On implementing Omniauth for Prism.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/out-on-a-small-limb/">Out on a (Small) Limb</a>: Discusses the importance of small feature branches when working collaboratively.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/on-tasks-large-and-small/">On Tasks Large and Small</a>: On realistic expectations and identifying problems.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/experimental-humanities/arduino-rainbow-hack/">Arduino Rainbow Hack</a>: Reflects on an Arduino hackday held in the Scholars&#8217; Lab.</li>
</ul>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Search Bar]]></title>
    <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/07/10/search-bar/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-10T19:41:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/07/10/search-bar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After some tweaking, I managed to get the search bar to play nicely. I unrounded the corners and lightened the borders to match the framing lines elsewhere in the navigation bar. Here is the CSS for it. You&#8217;ll want to give it an id selector of your own, a la #searchform.</p>

<p><a href="https://gist.github.com/bmw9t/5968989">Here</a> is the CSS for the changes to the search bar.</p>

<p>In trying to embed the above gist, I noticed that octopress breaks the styling: <img src="http://bmw9t.github.com/Broken_Gist.jpg"></p>

<p>Now I have something else to work on.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Design Refresh]]></title>
    <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/07/08/design/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-08T00:39:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/07/08/design</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At long last, I am ready to unveil the project that I have been working on over the summer - a design refresh for site. The main drive behind this aesthetic: I noticed the sheer abundance of information that the basic octopress theme gives you. This setup leads to a lot of duplicate information that ultimately makes things feel cluttered. I tried to keep things very minimal in this design, eliminating as much overlapping information and noise as possible.</p>

<p>I used a few different models for the design of the site. The main inspirations came from the sites of <a href="http://aijazansari.com/">Aijaz Ansari</a>, <a href="http://clioweb.org/">Jeremy Boggs</a>, and <a href="http://daniel.inletters.com/">Daniel Carter</a>. Ansari&#8217;s <a href="http://aijazansari.com/2012/08/27/how-to-customize-octopress-theme/">blog post</a> on customizing Octopress, especially, proved essential as I worked through my own setup. There are still a few things that I could stand to change for this current design, but it felt as thought it was time to let the current iteration see the light of day.</p>

<p>A couple issues I ran into:</p>

<p>How minimal is too minimal in an aesthetic like this? I am not crazy about the search bar in the navigation setup, but it does feel necessary to have one. The function there outweighed the desire to keep the aesthetic. In a future refresh, I will probably try to make the search bar a bit more subtle. In addition, at one point I had my links only turn blue when hovered. This looks great, but it presents obvious problems: you never know what is a link. Again, I had to make some sacrifices for the site to function properly.</p>

<p>How to deal with images in a minimal aesthetic? I initially wanted to have some sort of a banner image at the top where my name serves as a heading. I might explore this in the future, but images offer whole new complications. What kind of image texture would keep the aesthetic alive? Content? Color? I punted the issue for now by opting for my name as the banner, but I will be returning to this in the future.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Looking Forward]]></title>
    <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/02/01/looking-forward/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-01T18:25:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/02/01/looking-forward</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cross posted on the <a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/praxis-program/looking-forward/">Scholars&#8217; Lab blog.</a></p>

<p>As we move into the second half of our tenure on the <a href="http://praxis.scholarslab.org/">Praxis squad</a>, we are feeling the pressure to start actually making something. To that end, the <a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/">SLab</a> crew asked us to make a list of our priorities for <a href="http://prism.scholarslab.org/">Prism</a>. Hopefully this will help us make a to do list in the coming weeks. The following was the list that seemed to come out of yesterday’s meeting, though it’s possible that other people could have gotten different impressions from the conversation.</p>

<p>These seem to be our priorities, in no particular order except roughly that in which they were brought up:</p>

<p><strong>Types of texts</strong> – we’re interested in opening up the Prism framework to deal with pictures, music, etc.</p>

<p><strong>Getting a crowd</strong> – we want to get a large group of people working with Prism, however that might be arranged.</p>

<p><strong>Visualizations</strong> – we’re interested in expanding Prism’s visualizations to allow you to see the individual set of markings in relation to the crowd and to let you see one marking category’s visualization beside another.</p>

<p><strong>User uploads</strong> – we want to make it possible for users/instructors to upload a text for marking themselves, which we see as essential for classroom use.</p>

<p><strong>Complicating the sense of how we highlight</strong> – there has been discussion of complicating how the marking system works, allowing for a limit to the number of markings or a type of marking economy that is distributed across your selections to encourage different types of engagement with the data.</p>

<p><strong>Design makeover</strong> – we want to remake the design of the site with an eye to usability.</p>

<p>I think my own priorities lie in making it possible for users to upload their own texts for marking and in possibly adding more visualizations. If forced to choose between the two, I would spend the time on making the tool capable of handling user uploads. As quickly became clear, any one of these goals spins off into dozens of other questions. What do we mean by “upload a text”? Will those texts be public? Private? How will we navigate copyright and fair use? In the coming days we’re aiming to get a sense of our collective ordering of the list.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Teaching]]></title>
    <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/01/25/teaching/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-25T17:26:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/01/25/teaching</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After some Git problems were sorted out and explained to me by the staff of the <a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/">Scholars&#8217; Lab</a>, I can make updates to the site again. I have added some content to the <a href="http://bmw9t.github.com/teaching/index.html">Teaching</a> page: the syllabus for my current writing course among other goodies. Enjoy!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[We're Live!]]></title>
    <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2012/12/21/were-live/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-21T02:58:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2012/12/21/were-live</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The site is officially reborn and is now running on Octopress. In the coming days I will continue tinkering with the design and adding some content here and there, but the basic framework for the site is in place.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
