<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Brandon Walsh</title>
 <link href="http://walshbr.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://walshbr.com/"/>
 <updated>2020-10-19T19:12:13+00:00</updated>
 <id>http://walshbr.com/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Brandon Walsh</name>
   <email>walsh@virginia.edu</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Reading, Not Writing</title>
   <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/reading-not-writing/"/>
   <updated>2020-10-19T13:43:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/reading-not-writing</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Crossposted to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/reading-not-writing&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in January, we in the Scholars’ Lab &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/year-of-book-blogging-digital-humanities-pedagogy-in-kind/&quot;&gt;looked back fondly&lt;/a&gt; on all the public writing we had done together in 2019 and boldly looked ahead to all that we would do in 2020. We had big plans for putting more thoughts out in the world on a variety of topics. Then, of course, 2020 happened. In addition to the ongoing public health emergency, I have also been simmering with bottled rage about the full spectrum of political struggles related to the murder of George Floyd and subsequent protests, the ongoing climate emergency, and the Presidential election. Writing seems far less important now, with everything going on. All of this is to say that I, for one, have not been getting much blogging done. I felt a tremendous amount of guilt around this at first, as one typically does in academia when you have publicly declared yourself to be doing something that you cannot follow through on. But I have been trying to take the advice of Connor Kenaston, a former Praxis student, who advised his cohort at the beginnings of the pandemic to “&lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/praxis-in-a-pandemic/&quot;&gt;be gentle with yourself&lt;/a&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My version of being gentle has involved accepting that now is not the time to worry about putting new ideas into the world. When I had my comprehensive exams during my PhD, my advisor described graduate school to that point as a period of taking information in, as opposed to the new phase I was entering that would redirect that effort outwards as I looked towards the dissertation. Though of course it could be more nuanced, I think there is some truth to that binary: never before or since have I ever read as voraciously as I did during my graduate coursework and while studying for my exams. In the present moment I’ve found myself going backwards in a good way. While I have not been in a mental space conducive to writing, I have been trying to make more time for quiet reflection as I can. I have struggled in the last nine months to understand everything that is going on, in part because it defies easy explanation. I have been turning to others wiser than I am for guidance about how to respond to the ongoing emergencies in my own work, particularly as a means of trying to learn more about the struggles of students and colleagues whose experiences are different than mine. I’ve been spending more time reading, and I wanted to share a few things I have found especially useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Financial Aid&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve written before that your perspective on what it currently is like to be a student is, fundamentally, going to be different from reality unless you are currently a student. And this gulf will deepen the further you age away from your own time as an enrolled student. I have my own experiences with student debt, but I wanted to read more about how students currently experience the financial aid process and its associated burdens. To that end, I read a significant chunk of Sara Goldrick-Rab’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://saragoldrickrab.com/books/&quot;&gt;Paying the Price: College Costs, Financial Aid, and the Betrayal of the American Dream&lt;/a&gt;. The book is exceptional in a number of ways, both for providing clear data that is helpful for informing conversations about student aid and debt as well as for the specific interviews that it offers drawn from students currently living through the process. Most helpful for me was the material that describes exactly how student aid (and, by association, debt) is calculated by financial aid offices. It is wildly more complicated than I ever could have imagined, and reading Goldrick-Rab’s work has helped give me a better understanding of the intersectional context for the student debt crisis and how it extends into graduate education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Food Scarcity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pandemic has, in many ways, drawn attention to system inequalities already in place across the globe. The closure of schools has exacerbated food scarcity among those K-12 students who &lt;a href=&quot;https://eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2020-09/cums-mta091820.php&quot;&gt;rely on school lunches&lt;/a&gt;. Goldrick-Rab’s work with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://hope4college.com/&quot;&gt;Hope Center for College, Community, and Justice&lt;/a&gt; does an excellent job of showing just how much on food scarcity continues to be an issue for higher education. A useful piece that summarizes some of the issues is “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/01/14/opinion/hunger-college-food-insecurity.html&quot;&gt;It’s hard to study if you’re hungry&lt;/a&gt;.” A more pointed line that has been kicking around in my head since reading that piece is “it’s impossible to learn when you’re starving.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Loving Your Job&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Katina Rogers recently published &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dukeupress.edu/putting-the-humanities-phd-to-work&quot;&gt;Putting the Humanities PhD to Work&lt;/a&gt;, a book I found incredibly useful on a broad range of topics related to graduate pedagogy and advising. I found her description of love as it pertains to one’s work especially useful: “the notion that one work’s ‘for love’ reflects a position of privilege that minimizes the struggle many academics face to support themselves, and renders invisible the barriers that exacerbate the challenges for women, people of color, people with disabilities, and others who are not well supported by the structures of academe” (22). The same description, of course, could work for a number of different careers, but that should not diminish the critique’s power as it pertains to higher education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Precarious Labor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been finding it helpful to read about labor advocacy, both in digital humanities and otherwise, as a way of understanding how the pandemic has exacerbated the economic and power disparities that have always existed in the university structure. &lt;a href=&quot;https://muse.jhu.edu/article/704356&quot;&gt;Precarious Labor in the Digital Humanities&lt;/a&gt; by Christina Boyles, Anne Cong-Huyen, Carrie Johnston, Jim McGrath, and Amanda Phillips is an excellent way in for those of us working digital humanities. In addition, the coverage of the University of Michigan graduate students and RAs &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2020/09/16/unrest-and-strikes-hit-university-michigan&quot;&gt;strike over their administration’s response to COVID-19&lt;/a&gt; has been instructive for the kind of solidarity and activism that our current moment calls for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Student Surveillance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It feels like we all live on Zoom now, and I am very grateful to those who have drawn attention to the insidious effects of video technology used for pedagogy on student privacy. Asking students to turn their video on during a call, for example, can involve inviting a student’s instructor and peers into their private economic and social circumstances in &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/5-reasons-to-let-students-keep-their-cameras-off-during-zoom-classes-144111&quot;&gt;ways that can be harmful&lt;/a&gt;. Shea Swauger, writing on the related issue of &lt;a href=&quot;https://hybridpedagogy.org/our-bodies-encoded-algorithmic-test-proctoring-in-higher-education/&quot;&gt;algorithmic test proctoring&lt;/a&gt;, argues that “Cheating is not a technological problem, but a social and pedagogical problem. Technology is often blamed for creating the conditions in which cheating proliferates and is then offered as the solution to the problem it created; both claims are false.” I especially appreciated the ways in which Swauger ties technological solutions to online cheating as ultimately encoding a eugenic gaze into the classroom. Zoom often feels like something I just switch on as a part of starting my working day, but pieces like this have been helpful for thinking through the pedagogical and ethical implications of it and related platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no clear sign that we’re getting back to normal anytime soon, and I’m grateful to these authors for the guidance they offer for navigating our current circumstances. They’ve made me a better teacher and colleague.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A Humanist's Cookbook For Natural Language Processing In Python</title>
   <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/a-humanists-cookbook-for-natural-language-processing-in-python/"/>
   <updated>2020-09-14T08:24:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/a-humanists-cookbook-for-natural-language-processing-in-python</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Crossposted to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/a-humanists-cookbook-for-natural-language-processing-in-python&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab blog&lt;/a&gt; and co-authored with &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/people/rebecca-draughon/&quot;&gt;Rebecca Draughon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re pleased to share the initial release of an open educational resource we worked on over the summer - &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/walshbr/humanists-nlp-cookbook/blob/release/toc.ipynb&quot;&gt;A Humanist’s Cookbook for Natural Language Processing in Python&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project began with the goal of keeping Brandon from reinventing the wheel when working on natural language processing projects. By collecting together common scripts and approaches for personal use, it served as a common reference point that would be easier to consult than searching back through older repositories on GitHub when presented with new iterations of old problems. Eventually and once Rebecca came onboard the project, we started documenting the methods with a more generalized audience in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project is presented as a series of notebooks, a series of Python 3 recipes for common problems and issues associated with preparing data for text analysis and natural language processing. The target audience is students—intermediate programmers who have begun to learn their way around Python but who need a little help pulling the pieces together to get something done. The project has two main goals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Present code blocks for common problems.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Contextualize those blocks with humanists in mind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The text, at this point at least, makes no real attempt at coverage. Nor is there a real sequence through which someone should be expected to work. It simply gather scripts relevant to our work as we came to them in a way that is presented for a more generalized audience. There are a number of ways to approach any NLP problem, and any tweak can have big ramifications for the results. Hopefully this text will help intermediate programmers get going and give them the knowledge to have a little better understanding of what they’re working with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial set of notebooks covers the following topics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-steps&quot;&gt;First Steps&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set up&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Working with the file structure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-data&quot;&gt;Getting Data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Working with plain text files&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Getting data from websites&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Working with TEI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;preparing-data&quot;&gt;Preparing Data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stopwords&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dividing your text&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Preparing a corpus pipeline&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll periodically add news things as we get to them, and we already have plans for at least one future section that we couldn’t get to yet. Issues found with the text can be logged on the issue tracker for our &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/walshbr/humanists-nlp-cookbook/issues/new&quot;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Teaching with Big Ears</title>
   <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/teaching-with-big-ears/"/>
   <updated>2020-08-10T16:36:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/teaching-with-big-ears</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Crossposted to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/teaching-with-big-ears&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I studied music in school, we were all given a listening placement test. First, the graduate student in charge would play a series of melodies and harmonies for us, and we were asked to notate them. The second test exercised the inverse skills: given a sheet of music we were asked to sing what we saw in front of us. In each case, we were graded on how accurately we were able to convert sound to written notation and back again. All incoming music majors were slotted into one of six sections based on the results of our ear training test, and I placed into the bottom one. Even the most basic skill–pitch matching, or the ability to hear a note and sing that same note back–was a challenge for me. Twice a week for the rest of the semester, the students in my section filed into a basement classroom and made noise around a piano in what must have been an excruciating experience for the trained music doctoral student who taught us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the year, that teacher worked with us to develop “big ears.” This term refers to a number of overlapping concepts from the music industry that, together, represent an exceptionally strong attention to the nuances of musicmaking and the collaborations required for performance. Ashley Capps, organizer of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bigearsfestival.org/&quot;&gt;Big Ears Festival&lt;/a&gt; in Knoxville, Tennessee, described it in this way: “The term ‘big ears’ is also slang in the music industry that describes being an especially acute and perceptive listener […] So, a great sound engineer, a DJ who has an affinity for picking hit songs or simply someone who listens broadly and deeply—they’re all said to have big ears.” I’ve heard the term a few times over the years. Most recently, on &lt;a href=&quot;https://cubidesartists.com/podcast&quot;&gt;The Musician’s Guide to Being Healthy, Wealthy &amp;amp; Wise&lt;/a&gt;, a podcast about the music industry, it was used to describe a performer who was especially strong at perceiving what others were playing. In that context, it was specifically used to refer to someone with strong &lt;em&gt;aural skills&lt;/em&gt;, a term that refers to the ability to hear pitch, harmony, intervals, melodies, and similar characteristics of music and identify them based solely or primarily on hearing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listening in this way—with big ears—is challenging, but it is a skill that can be learned. Each semester as a music student, I had to take a version of that same ear training placement test. Each time I got a lot wrong, but the care and attention of the instructors helped me, over time, to get a little more right. By my sixth semester I made it into the fifth section—not quite the top group of students but close! My last undergraduate semester involved singing a lot of Bach chorales twice a week each morning. I am still far from the best, but I continue to improve to this day. I don’t have a musicianship class anymore, but I do have an &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/ear-trainer/id358733250&quot;&gt;app for my phone&lt;/a&gt; that helps me to keep practicing. You can always get better at listening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of my favorite stories about learning because it takes something that appears magical and wholly out of reach and shows that, with time and practice, it is a skill that can be developed by anyone. It’s also a story, I think, about teaching. How easy would it have been for my instructor to belittle me as I struggled to get started with singing? Instead, my teacher listened—however hard that might have been for them. The story feels especially relevant for the present moment, because it’s fundamentally about how those in power do or do not listen to those in their care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It feels impossible to work right now, let alone teach, when so many people are barely holding families, institutions, and themselves together. How can we work with students under these conditions, when it feels, so often, as though the important voices of those doing the work go unheard? The students and staff that inhabit our educational spaces, that maintain them, and that labor in them are struggling through catastrophe. We are bodies, dealing with the physical and emotional strain of a public health emergency. Now, more than ever, the work of the classroom requires careful attention and, I think, a pedagogy of radical empathy. A renewed focus on intentional and purposeful listening, even—and especially—as it is devalued around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we moved online this spring, I, like many instructors, struggled to transition my work to an entirely virtual format. But I also knew it was entirely necessary. My students in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/&quot;&gt;Praxis Program&lt;/a&gt; were in the thick of shaping what their developing project would look like and how to implement it. When the students and I were able to touch base in our first online Zoom meeting, I made one thing clear: their well-being came first. Even if the students produced no final project as originally planned, that was perfectly acceptable. They were already successes to us. Then, I asked them to take some time to think together about what they wanted to do as a team. These were not empty promises: I was prepared to fully back up whatever choice the students made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a number ways, our ability to focus heavily on students’ well-being was enabled by privilege. Because the Scholars’ Lab operates a fellowship program from the library, I don’t have to give grades and the outcomes can be quite flexible. There are, however, a range of thinkers in critical digital pedagogy, including &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jessestommel.com/how-to-ungrade/&quot;&gt;Jesse Stommel&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.seanmichaelmorris.com/late-work/&quot;&gt;Sean Michael Morris&lt;/a&gt;, who have written eloquently on how such choices are good, ethical pedagogy that can and should be explored by all teachers such as they are able. Other critics, too, have talked about the importance of empathetic attention to students’ needs during the present moment. Pedagogy and American Literary Studies has suggested that &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/PedagogyAmLitSt/status/1287817872794882055&quot;&gt;you might not need that absence policy right now&lt;/a&gt;. Michelle Pacansky-Brock has offered a &lt;a href=&quot;https://brocansky.com/humanizing/student-info&quot;&gt;model survey&lt;/a&gt; for checking on your students’ needs during this difficult time. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.syllabusjournal.org/syllabus/article/view/301&quot;&gt;Matthew Cheney&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://hybridpedagogy.org/pedagogy-of-kindness/&quot;&gt;Catherine Denial&lt;/a&gt; have each argued for modifying our syllabi and our pedagogies to be founded on kindness rather than abuse. There are many more ideas in circulation, and the ones that most resonate with me are those that accommodate the urgent and pressing needs of others, of those students and collaborators who are caring for children, lack access to broadband internet, or are worried for loved ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we resumed meetings, it was clear that the students wanted to forge ahead and complete their project, but we also recognized that the nature of the community had changed. I think by offering the possibility of an extreme (though, in my view, ethical) response to the pandemic, they, an already cohesive and close group, became even more caring for one another. For the rest of the semester, we had regular check-ins, individually and collectively on personal well-being. We cared for each other as people even as the work carried forward. The project resulted in &lt;a href=&quot;http://landandlegacy.scholarslab.org/&quot;&gt;Land and Legacy&lt;/a&gt;, an incisive look at the University of Virginia’s and the University of Virginia Foundation’s land expansion in Charlottesville and Albemarle County since the 1980s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, these ideas are part of a broad pedagogy of deep listening—that is, of hearing students’ needs as both thinkers &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; people and structuring a learning environment to accommodate them. Listening in this way is not passive. Instead, it borrows from musicians, for whom listening is always a process of attention and response. In their collection entitled, appropriately enough, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.dukeupress.edu/books/book/1150/Big-EarsListening-for-Gender-in-Jazz-Studies&quot;&gt;Big Ears: Listening for Gender in Jazz Studies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Nichole T. Rustin and Sherrie Tucker quote Ingrid Monson on listening: “[jazz musicians] mean it in a very active sense: they must listen closely because they are continually called upon to respond to and participate in an ongoing flow of musical action that can change or surprise them at any moment” (1). Listening—real listening—is about careful attention to the whole, your part in the collective, and how you can grow together. Sometimes that means staying silent. Sometimes that means making noise. It always means paying attention to what the group needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listening, in these terms, is the action by which the collective forms itself. Whether teaching in-person, hybrid, or online this fall, whether talking about the classroom, the administrative planning meeting, or the ballot box in November: voices are likely to be silenced. Committing to listening does not mean inaction in the face of these oppressive systems. Sean Michael Morris gets at a similar point in “&lt;a href=&quot;https://criticaldigitalpedagogy.pressbooks.com/chapter/not-enough-voices/&quot;&gt;Not Enough Voices&lt;/a&gt;,” when he discusses his own anxiety over speaking too much: “The answer doesn’t lie in turn-taking, but in changing what it means to speak. Make speaking a collaborative event. Join your voice with the voice of students. Join your voice with the voice of other teachers.” In these terms, a pedagogy of listening is one that attends to voices, one that helps make space for equitable terms of engagement. This sense of listening, one that is born of and that leads to collective action, is something we need now more than ever. Right now, we need teachers and administrators who are ready to listen, to make space, and to speak up. To hear, echo, and amplify the voices of their students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is much more to say about pedagogies of listening. For now I will end with one last quote, this one from Igor Stravinsky: “To listen is an effort, and just to hear is no merit. A duck hears also.” Don’t be a duck. People aren’t born good at listening. Teaching with big ears is a skill you can practice, and there’s no better time than the present.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Your Budget Is a Question of Pedagogy and Equity</title>
   <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/your-budget-is-a-question-of-pedagogy-and-equity/"/>
   <updated>2020-04-15T11:29:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/your-budget-is-a-question-of-pedagogy-and-equity</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Crossposted to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/your-budget-is-a-question-of-pedagogy-and-equity&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finished drafting this post back before the extent of the coronavirus pandemic was becoming known. And now, of course, the impact of the virus around the globe—and on higher education in particular—continues to evolve. So I had been sitting on this post for some time; I wasn’t sure how a rapidly changing landscape of higher education, replete with hiring freezes and bleak budgetary outlooks, might impact these conversations. I’m still uncertain. But I’m publishing this now in the expectation that ethical conversations about budgets as they pertain to students and teaching are likely to become more important now than ever. I’m grateful to &lt;a href=&quot;https://mackenziekbrooks.info/&quot;&gt;Mackenzie Brooks&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/&quot;&gt;Amanda Visconti&lt;/a&gt;, and Elizabeth Fox for reading the post over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caveats aside—this post is part of a larger project I’m working on over the course of the year about the intersections of digital humanities pedagogy as it can reflect and enact infrastructural change in higher education. While each post is meant to stand on its own, they do participate in a longer conversation. It might be helpful to explore the &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/year-of-book-blogging-digital-humanities-pedagogy-in-kind/&quot;&gt;framing post for the series&lt;/a&gt; for context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will talk elsewhere about opportunities for pedagogical interventions in the context of credit-bearing courses. For now, I wanted to speak primarily from my own institutional perspective. As the Head of Student Programs for a library-based center for digital research, the teaching that I do tends not to happen in for-credit courses. Instead, my teaching takes place in a range of activities: year-long student fellowships that carry a stipend that I design and administer in collaboration with the rest of the Scholars’ Lab, one-on-one consultations, one-off workshops, and more. Roughly half of my working life is spent on the actual work of theorizing and carrying out teaching. The other half is spent on developing the administrative infrastructure to allow such work to happen, for myself and others. With that in mind, I wanted to pause over the kinds of pedagogical interventions that can be made by people in these kinds of positions—whether we describe them as alt-academic, para-academic, academic, or otherwise. For that reason, the following does not apply so much to teaching in credit bearing courses, though it might offer useful food for thought as it applies to a range of pedagogical situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.seanmichaelmorris.com/the-habitus-of-critical-imagination/&quot;&gt;Sean Michael Morris&lt;/a&gt; refers to a pedagogical habitus, “embodied practice, often uninspected or subterranean to a person’s own thinking about themselves,” that forms the “genetic makeup” of an instructor’s teaching. In this line of thought, pedagogy is not just a practice–it is more properly thought of as your general attitude towards the work of teaching that you do. Put simply, your pedagogy is reflected in every action you take that could potentially affect students and your attitudes towards all such actions. It’s not too much of an exaggeration, I think, to say that with this frame of thinking every action can be considered a pedagogical one. No administrative decision is too small to affect students in some way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often point to budgets as the clearest example of how mundane administrative details, seemingly disconnected from the work of the classroom, have profound ramifications for teachers and learners. To put the finest point on it: your budget is a pedagogical issue. It’s also a question of equity. The economic circumstances your program creates or participates in directly affect the kinds of people able to participate in your programs and the work they can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Higher education is a time of enormous financial uncertainty for many students. Sara Goldrick-Rab’s work with &lt;a href=&quot;https://realcollege.org/&quot;&gt;#realcollege&lt;/a&gt;, for example, has brought attention to the number of college students that struggle with food and housing insecurity. The situation is often no better for graduate students who, even if their programs offer tuition remission and stipends, are frequently forced to live in poverty. B. Mano’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://thetech.com/2019/10/31/mit-grad-students-poverty&quot;&gt;piece on their particular circumstances&lt;/a&gt; at MIT sheds light, in particular, on how specific institutional policies can intersect with national labor and immigration law to produce especially dire situations for students. In these circumstances, any decision that we make as administrators can have dire consequences for the lives of the students around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, every situation is different and subject to different pressures. Many institutions doing digital work simply don’t have any budget or funding at all. If you’re in a position like this, it might feel difficult to imagine how you could structure financial circumstances for your students in a more equitable manner when you’re still trying to find any kind of firm structure at all. In what follows I don’t mean to propose the perfect as the enemy of the good. Instead, I’d suggest taking the following as opportunities to examine where you’re at in the hopes of finding a way towards better outcomes—whatever “better” means for you and your circumstances. At the very least, I hope that the following discussion can supply resources and questions to use as we all try to advocate for better labor conditions for students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four pedagogical questions that you might ask of the student side of your budget are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does it exist?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is it stable?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is it transparent?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is it what my students need?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;does-it-exist&quot;&gt;Does it exist?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are students a part of your budget? If not, why? In Elissa Frankle’s ignite talk entitled “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0niIskfLpdE&amp;amp;list=PLl7V7chP13lBSnSyYpEp6g6lpu7pZftrC&quot;&gt;Pay Your F-ing Interns&lt;/a&gt;,” she describes how unpaid internships reinforce whiteness and homogenous, privileged communities in museum workers. Frankle goes on: “We may say that we value diversity, that of course we want to treat our workers well, but do our core documents and budgets reflect that fact?” Our decisions about infrastructure, at their best, should reflect what our organizations believe in. A first useful question you can ask of your budget, then, is, whether and to what degree your work with students rises to the level of budget lines and conversations during allocations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you can pay is, of course, a local issue. But it is worth questioning whether your current payment practices are the result of habit or limitations. At UVA, we are subject to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://provost.virginia.edu/wage-authorization-academic-areas&quot;&gt;range of policies&lt;/a&gt; that impact what we can offer students. It’s important to know what these are at your institution so that you can answer statements like “we can only pay X” with “actually, the policy states we can pay X+Y.” I often find state and local policies as a useful first tool when advocating for students, and they can also provide common language for working with financial administrators elsewhere in your institution who might be more removed from the day-to-day lives of your students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you’re not instituting something as formal as an internship or an hourly position, it’s worth considering how much unpaid time you’re asking of your students. Asking students to drive visiting speakers to events, for example, might appear negligible for the amount of effort it requires. But this small ask still takes a student’s time, time that they could be applying to their own work, to another paid position, or to personal needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, recognize the economic impact you are likely already having on students and decide whether you can do better. Recognize what you ask of them, first, and second ask what you can pay them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-it-stable&quot;&gt;Is it stable?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students need to be able to plan their finances. If they cannot, only students from affluent backgrounds will be able to make decisions about their educations in the face of such uncertainty. If we want to design programs for students that will be as inclusive as possible, we need to strive for better stability in what we can offer. I am well aware that stable budgets are a luxury in most institutions, including my own. This is especially true in digital humanities, where people and organizations have successfully lobbied IMLS, CLIR, the Mellon Foundation, and the NEH ODH for substantial grants to support their work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grant funding can provide valuable experience for students and resources for paying them for their labor. And at some institutions these avenues might be the only ones available for funding the work of you and your students. Grants come with the disadvantage, of course, that they will eventually run their course. Soft money can provide useful supplemental resources for employing students, but the associated instability can cause long-term issues for students and staff. For example, a term-limited grant-funded student position might be listed as one year with year extension contingent on successful performance. In such a situation, the student or postdoctoral worker will spend a significant portion of their time planning and searching for what comes next when the grant-funded position ends. Extensions to a contracted position might, of course, be more dependent on successful lobbying for continued funding than on faith in an already carefully vetted candidate. But it’s still worth considering the real-life ramifications these positions can have for candidates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth noting the benefits of stable student programs founded on hard money. Through a combination of advocacy and strategic planning, the Lab has been fortunate enough to offer two stable fellowships for several years now. Praxis is completing its ninth year, and our Graduate Fellowship in Digital Humanities is in its thirteenth year. This means that students can plan on these programs as possibilities for them as they plot out not just their research agenda during their time with us, but also their plans for applying for supplemental funding. It is truly unfortunate that we cannot accept everyone who applies, but we work hard to try to bring as many people as we can into our community. It takes time for research agendas to develop, and students need time to decide if such things are right for them. The Scholars’ Lab has application cycles that run virtually all year long for its various programs, and students discuss their intention to apply well in advance of when they are eligible to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stable programs lead to better support for students as well. Supporting students requires time and energy from staff, no matter how experienced and skilled they might be. Thoughtful and considerate planning that includes student support as part of the regular workload for staff ensures that teaching and pedagogy will not become afterthoughts. Even if suddenly presented with the financial option to take on new students, one should ask if they can be supported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good teaching follows from well-supported and energized staff who are empowered to decide if they have the bandwidth to take on new students. Good learning follows from students who can make informed decisions about their lives and have the time and space to commit to learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-it-transparent&quot;&gt;Is it transparent?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often find that students have received no real information about the systems by which their finances get processed. On the one hand, this is understandable—university budgeting processes are byzantine, and information about payment processing might seem like a means to an end and less crucial to students’ day-to-day lives. But providing knowledge about these systems can help students plan their own lives more capably. I have found it helpful to make sure students are aware of a range of different components related to how their payments are processed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;University payroll calendars&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The length of time it takes for a payment to process&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whether a payment will be taxed up front or not&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whether a certain amount of payment during the year triggers automatic taxation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When payments are likely to come through, how often, and in what amount&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of these elements can help students plan their time and finances. In addition, I’ve found that it can be difficult for us to track when something goes wrong in a payment that we’ve issued. We know when we issue it, and we find out if a student gets their funds. But there are many steps along the way. With many, many links in the administrative chain before the money actually gets dispersed to students, there are many places where things could go wrong. So I have regular appointments on my calendar when I ask students to make sure that they’ve been paid as expected. I often find students are really patient and willing to wait even if it appears that something might be amiss. But, as payments take time to process, I would rather we be in constant communication and transparent about where things stand so that we can reduce the burden on students already living in states of financial precarity. A transparent budgeting and dispersal process is a more ethical one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-it-what-they-need&quot;&gt;Is it what they need?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, any administrative process can be enhanced by student input. As is often the case with teaching, I find the best way to grow is to ask students for their insights. Put simply, unless you were a student &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; recently, you probably do not know what sorts of pressures your students are subject to. Unless you recently lived paycheck to paycheck, it might be easy to forget the sort of financial precarity that a number of our students live under. And it is impossible for any one person to have personal experience that tracks with every possible student experience in the world. In short, be wary of invoking Students with a capital ‘s’, as one broad monolithic community. In order to take a broad, intersectional approach to your teaching and administration, you must talk with students themselves. They are experts on their own situations, and talking with your students about their needs can help to inform your decisions. They’ll learn more about how the university works, and the teaching and pedagogy you can offer will be enhanced as it more closely matches the real-world experiences of your community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We address this same point in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/student-programs-charter/&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab Student Programs Charter&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We teach in public, meaning that we talk openly about our pedagogical process. When possible, we write about it as well. If something is not working, we will change it and adapt based on the needs of the students and our colleagues. Accordingly, we expect our students to talk and write about their work and the learning process for them, to engage in the experience, and help us shape a pedagogical experience that works for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To engage your students directly in conversations like those above is to treat them as peers, as collaborators in the learning process in all of its messiness. Details like these might seem removed from teaching or overly specific. But they have material effects on the day-to-live lives of your student collaborators. A conversation with a student about how the uncertainties around a particular fellowship payment, for example, helped us to understand that a different distribution calendar would offer students more cushion if payments were delayed. We wouldn’t have gotten the idea had we not talked with the student directly about their needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, it can be difficult to balance these conversations against the realities of trying to do this work. We don’t live in a perfect world, and we’re all working with limited resources. Talking with students directly can be a way of sussing out whether your budgetary situation is operating for them and their lives and how it might work better for them. Students can help us all find our way to more equitable pedagogies and budgets that reflect them. You cannot do everything, but you might be able to adjust a few things. In the current climate of higher education, when many are faced with hiring freezes, across-the-board budget cuts, the prospect of layoffs, and withdrawn job offers, such conversations might seem small. But small decisions can matter in big ways for your students. And they can help us care for our vulnerable community members during chaotic times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Resources for further reading on the topic:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://humtech.ucla.edu/news/a-student-collaborators-bill-of-rights/&quot;&gt;UCLA Student Collaborators Bill of Rights&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1bKpiqX9LPGJsKJsLopFW5vvEgwS3koXZJQU3nv-iuWw/edit&quot;&gt;Postdoctoral Bill of Rights&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dhwogem.org/&quot;&gt;Women and Gender Minorities in Digital Humanities group&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Year Of Book Blogging: Digital Humanities Pedagogy in Kind</title>
   <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/year-of-book-blogging-digital-humanities-pedagogy-in-kind/"/>
   <updated>2020-01-28T09:41:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/year-of-book-blogging:-digital-humanities-pedagogy-in-kind</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Crossposted to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/year-of-book-blogging-digital-humanities-pedagogy-in-kind&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amanda, Ammon, and I have been discussing our plans for the upcoming year of blogging. While last year’s blogging push was invigorating and exciting, we wanted things to be slightly different in the coming year. In particular, we’ve been talking about wanting more continuity in the things we publish. Speaking for myself, it often felt like I was blogging just in time and on deadline. Some good things came out of that work, but I liked the idea of putting just a little more thinking into the project ahead of time so that I could blog around a central topic for the year. Amanda and Ammon have been incredibly helpful in talking about all this with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Truthfully, I’ve been feeling the lack of a large writing project lately. After my &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.18130/V3R27G&quot;&gt;dissertation&lt;/a&gt;, I worked on a &lt;a href=&quot;http://walshbr.com/textanalysiscoursebook&quot;&gt;text analysis coursebook&lt;/a&gt; with Sarah Horowitz, a faculty colleague at W&amp;amp;L. I adore blogging, but I feel the lure of a large project I can chip away at over the next year and that can draw together my energy. Am I talking about writing a book? Maybe? We’ll see. I’m certainly not the first person to write a book in public, but the idea of revealing what I was aiming for made me feel a little uneasy. What if my ideas didn’t cohere (I tend to write in multiple sections of a project at once)? What if I didn’t actually produce anything or finish? What if the project turned out to be empty (easier to dismiss a single blog post)? Does what I’m interested in working on even need to be a book? What do I mean by book - is it a published thing with a press or just something big that lives online?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had initially planned on just quietly blogging around a cluster of ideas over the next year and then potentially revealing at the end that they were part of a coherent project in progress. But as I started to write the first post on imposter syndrome (seriously)- and in the midst of talking with my students about the very topic - I thought I should put my money where my mouth is from the outset. So here you go! Here are my notes on the large, ongoing, multifaceted writing project that I’ll be trying to cohere together over the course of the next year. If it winds up being something I try to actually turn into a book so be it. If it just winds up being a series of blog posts, then I’ll at least be happy to have written about topics I felt were urgent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last note on process: in my PhD program we did an activity where we repeatedly drafted a fantasy table of contents for our dissertation. No abstracts necessary at that stage - just a title for the project and titles for the chapters. I found it enormously useful as a means for thinking through the different shapes a large writing project could take. That’s essentially what I do below. I try on a provisional title for the large project and take a spin at some rough chapter ideas. Since this is a blogging endeavor to begin with, within each chapter title I offer some titles, topics, or questions for blog posts that might intersect with it. I flag a few thinkers and discourses that I see this all drawing upon and engaging with. I also offer a few beginning thoughts towards a topic (nothing surprising, if you’ve read other posts by me on here). My arguments always tend to emerge in the process of writing, though, so it will be interesting to see how this develops over the course of a year. So take this for what it is - a sketch of a sketch of things I find urgent and will be trying to attend to over the coming months. Stay tuned for a look into my messy process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought I might start by close reading this provisional, draft-y title as a way of getting at the ideas I want to explore. For now, at least, I’m thinking about it as called &lt;em&gt;Digital Humanities Pedagogy in Kind&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;digital-humanities-pedagogy-in-kind&quot;&gt;Digital Humanities Pedagogy in Kind&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our pedagogies model and reflect the kind of academic community we want to see in the  world. Academia is toxic in numerous ways. Teaching and the ways we theorize and practice it can be interventions in the culture around us. The project hopes to connect classroom practice broadly construed with the kinds of infrastructural changes they reflect and enact.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kindness is at the core of the project. I’m trying to formulate a theory of DH pedagogy that is, at its core, one about developing a less toxic and more affirmative space for students in higher education. It’s about developing empathy and kindness as teachers and how DH can (or cannot?) offer us the space to do so within and against the infrastructures of academia.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finally, at least in this title, I wanted to get at the idea of paying a debt in goods and services rather than in cash. For starters, I like this formulation because it draws in a range of topics. What do we owe our students? It raises the specter of student debt. And it draws in Paulo Freire and questions of neoliberal, zero-sum teaching. Is digital humanities fundamentally bound up in neoliberal politics of the university? Yes. How can we develop an ethical, just, and progressive pedagogy anyway and in the face of this?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A starting list of thinkers I imagine the project in dialogue with: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cathydavidson.com/books/the-new-education/&quot;&gt;Cathy Davidson&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dukeupress.edu/putting-the-humanities-phd-to-work&quot;&gt;Katina Rogers&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://jhupbooks.press.jhu.edu/title/generous-thinking&quot;&gt;Kathleen Fitzpatrick&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mith.umd.edu/advocacy-design-moving-theory-practice-part-1/&quot;&gt;Jeremy Boggs and Purdom Lindblad&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.halperta.com/&quot;&gt;Hannah Alpert-Abrams&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://akhenrichs.com/blog/&quot;&gt;Amanda Henrichs&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.roopikarisam.com/&quot;&gt;Roopika Risam&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://saragoldrickrab.com/&quot;&gt;Sara Goldrick-Rab&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://urgencyofteachers.com/&quot;&gt;Jesse Stommel and Sean Michael Morris&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/finiteeyes/status/1217175390491295744&quot;&gt;Matthew Cheney&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://hybridpedagogy.org/author/catherine/&quot;&gt;Catherine Denial&lt;/a&gt;, bell hooks, Paulo Freire; &lt;a href=&quot;https://thedigitalpress.org/failing-gloriously/&quot;&gt;Shawn Graham&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://digitalpedagogy.mla.hcommons.org/&quot;&gt;Rebecca Frost Davis, Matthew K. Gold, Katherine D. Harris, and Jentery Sayers&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://briancroxall.net/&quot;&gt;Brian Croxall&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://artepublicopress.com/carolina-villarroel/&quot;&gt;Carolina Villarroel&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uh.edu/class/spanish/faculty/baeza-ventura_g/&quot;&gt;Gabriela Baeza Ventura&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mith.umd.edu/people/person/trevor-munoz/&quot;&gt;Trevor Muñoz&lt;/a&gt; (and more). Significant projects that I’d examine and reflect on would include the &lt;a href=&quot;https://humtech.ucla.edu/news/a-student-collaborators-bill-of-rights/&quot;&gt;UCLA Student Collaborators’ Bill of Rights&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.mith.umd.edu/offthetracks/recommendations/index.html&quot;&gt;Collaborators Bill of Rights&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://futuresinitiative.org/&quot;&gt;The Futures Initiative&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hastac.org/&quot;&gt;HASTAC&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://digitalpedagogy.mla.hcommons.org/&quot;&gt;Digital Pedagogy in the Humanities&lt;/a&gt;,  &lt;a href=&quot;https://iliads.org/&quot;&gt;ILiADS&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/generousthinking?src=hash&quot;&gt;#generousthinking&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/deposits/item/hc:26741/&quot;&gt;The Postdoctoral Laborers Bill of Rights&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/groups/academic-job-market-support-network/&quot;&gt;Academic Job Market Support Network&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://aadhum.umd.edu/&quot;&gt;AADHum&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://usldhrecovery.uh.edu/&quot;&gt;USLDH&lt;/a&gt;, among others. In my mind I want to tie together questions of higher education reform, critical digital pedagogy, and DH pedagogy. I’m certain I’m leaving people and projects out in this short and initial list - such is the nature of blogging about a work in progress. I’ll be working on a Zotero bibliography that collects these resources for myself and others as I continue reading around about the important work already being done in these areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imagine the project offering a theory and praxis of DH teaching and pedagogy - very broadly construed, as it tries to develop a theory of pedagogy far beyond the classroom -  as an intervention in academic culture. DH pedagogy offers a number of great interventions to begin with – meditations on failure, teaching as activism, rethinking the professional futures of humanities students – and I’d like to join those conversations with others from critical digital pedagogy that emphasize radically student-centered teaching. With these frameworks, I’ll focus the work on the conditions of being a DH student – the material labor and working circumstances, the conditions of professional development and career prospects, the intersections of administrative decisions and the economic conditions of student life. I think doing so will help to give a better sense of the lives at the core of DH pedagogy as they intersect with the administrative infrastructures of DH. And perhaps ultimately the project aims to argue for a pedagogy that teaches with and alongside students and with kindness that happens together (a lot of echoes of Kathleen Fitzpatrick’s &lt;em&gt;Generous Thinking&lt;/em&gt; here).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s where I’m at right now at least. Lots of loose threads and jumbled thoughts but at least a place to get started. One unresolved question for me is what makes this an argument about DH and not just pedagogy in general? Is it DH just because I am a DH person? Or does DH specifically have something to say about this? Is the DH audience, in particular, a good one for this? Or not? Things I’ll want to think further about in the future for certain. Without further ado, though, I’ll close with the draft table of contents and associated blog topics / questions. The arc of the project as I’m thinking it at the moment moves from micro to macro, from the classroom to larger questions of professional climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;draft-table-of-contents-and-ideas&quot;&gt;Draft Table of Contents and Ideas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Introduction
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Where does DH teaching happen?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Where does infrastructural change happen?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Classroom experience
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Kindness and generosity as skills that require training&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pedagogies of listening&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How do we make the classroom a space where students can be sheltered from the academy and also create the conditions to transform it a la &lt;a href=&quot;https://jwernimont.com/&quot;&gt;Jacqueline Wernimont&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What are the spaces of teaching, for DH in particular?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Labor
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;DH students as DH teachers&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Neoliberal DH pedagogies&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Expanding on the UCLA Student Collaborators’ Bill of Rights&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Precarious labor and the labor of teaching&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Infrastructure
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;As it impacts pedagogy and student life and teaching in particular; how do the small decisions we make at the level of administration reflect out pedagogies?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How can pedagogy be enacted beyond the classroom? How can we take teacherly actions as administrators?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How can those teacherly administrative actions address issues of precarity among the student population?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Your budget is a question of pedagogy and justice&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Profession
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Imposter syndrome. Where does imposter syndrome start for students? How can we address it?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Professional Development / Career Paths&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Professional Imposters&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Small changes / big changes&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conclusion – on inclusivity
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How do we invite students into the profession and into higher education in a way that makes their voices heard and valued?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How can we ensure students are valued in online spaces? Or welcomed in spaces of open peer review?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Where to go from here?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seems like plenty to go on for now. Now to get blogging!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Digital Humanities Job Talks: Some Case Studies</title>
   <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/digital-humanities-job-talks-some-case-studies/"/>
   <updated>2019-12-16T11:15:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/digital-humanities-job-talks:-some-case-studies</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Co-authored with &lt;a href=&quot;http://amandavisconti.com/&quot;&gt;Amanda Visconti&lt;/a&gt;. Crossposted to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/digital-humanities-job-talks/&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab blog&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2019/12/16/digital-humanities-job-talks&quot;&gt;Amanda’s personal blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To follow up on sharing and annotating &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/dh-cover-letters/&quot;&gt;our past cover letters&lt;/a&gt; for DHy academic jobs, in this post we share how we’ve thought through past job talk prompts and the experience of giving the resulting presentations. (To learn more about Brandon’s practical workflow to drafting and memorizing talks, check out his &lt;a href=&quot;http://walshbr.com/blog/dh-public-speaking/&quot;&gt;post on DH public speaking&lt;/a&gt;! To learn about Amanda’s workflow, prod her to finally publish a now-too-long post about DH and public speaking anxiety before 2020 ends…)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you dive in, though, you may wish to read our October 2019 blog post &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/dh-cover-letters/&quot;&gt;“How We Talk and Write about DH Jobs”&lt;/a&gt; if you haven’t already. Well intentioned academic job advice can be and often is harmful—so in that post’s “Slightly Better Job Advice, Take Two” section, we discuss how we’re trying to share what we know about job searches in a way that affirms any readers as valued peers and scholars, just as they are. We hope sharing our experiences here can be useful and not overly prescriptive. Our perspectives are shaped by our own particular contexts, and we trust that readers will know their own circumstances - and what will work for them - better than we do. With this in mind, we share the following in the hopes that resources and transparency about our own thinking on the process of preparing for job presentations can help others getting started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;brandon&quot;&gt;Brandon:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should note outright that my experience pertains to giving job talks for what might be called alternative academic positions in DH working in libraries. And, while I have seen a number of presentations by job candidates for a range of library positions, I have always wondered how my own background and experiences affect how I evaluate candidate presentations. For example, I do not have a library degree: I did my graduate work in literature before coming to work in libraries, and this different orientation undoubtedly shapes how I view job presentations and prepare for them. When applying for any position, it’s a good idea to talk with someone who is familiar with that discipline or field so that they can give you a sense of the generic expectations that your audience will bring to your presentation. I would not take any of my thoughts on job talks as prescriptive in the least. Your mileage will vary. But I remember my own experiences as a student felt largely as though I was trying to approach a job presentation without any context or sense of how to think about them. Hopefully seeing how I do so can help someone in the same position formulate their own approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re often raised to think of writing and, by association, presentations, as having a clear and direct point. But, to me, the difficulty with alt-ac job talks is that they often seem to address a number of different issues at once. When I prepare one, I try to think of the presentation as working to convey a few things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;my response to a prompt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;my experience&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;my understanding of the job&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;my vision for the position&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find the &lt;a href=&quot;https://walshbr.com/blog/in-out-across-with/&quot;&gt;job talk&lt;/a&gt; for my current position as Head of Student Programs in the Scholars’ Lab on my website. As I discuss elements of that job talk below, readers might find that full text helpful for context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prompts&quot;&gt;Prompts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many positions that ask you to give a presentation will also give you some kind of prompt for the job talk. To a greater or lesser degree depending on the audience, they will expect you to respond to it. For my position as Head of Student Programs in the Scholars’ Lab, I was given a prompt that broadly addressed education in digital humanities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;What does a student (from undergraduate to doctoral levels) need to learn or experience in order to add “DH” to his or her skill set? Is that an end or a means of graduate education? Can short-term digital assignments in discipline-specific courses go beyond “teaching with technology”? Why not refer everyone to online tutorials? Are there risks for doctoral students or the untenured in undertaking digital projects? Drawing on your own experience, and offering examples or demonstrations of digital research projects, pedagogical approaches, or initiatives or organizations that you admire, make a case for a vision of collaborative education in advanced digital scholarship in the arts and humanities.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a lot of feelings about this prompt, as you can imagine. As Amanda mentions below, prompts are often abstract and vague because they are not written with any particular candidate in mind. By trying to offer something for everyone, they sometimes seem intentionally amorphous so that anyone can find a way to latch onto the material. But this means that a prompt can go anywhere, really, and trying to devise a response to it can feel very difficult. So my first point of advice is simply that the difficulty with the prompt is not you! It’s a strange genre, and recognizing this can hopefully help begin to mitigate feelings of imposter syndrome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, I remember feeling pretty convinced that every question on my prompt could be its own talk. There was just so much to work with, so many topics to address! In the face of this issue, I explicitly framed my own talk as only responding to the first question listed - “What does a student (from undergraduate to doctoral levels) need to learn or experience in order to add “DH” to his or her skill set?” I thought responding to all pieces of the prompt was an impossible task, and I leaned into a talk that did more with less. For what it’s worth, I remember one person approaching me after the presentation and softly noting that I had not responded to all of the questions in the prompt (but they still appreciated the talk). Fair enough, but I did what made the most sense to me. Noting the parts of the prompt you will or won’t address can be a useful way of articulating the intentionality of your response for the audience, and it can also be useful for people in the audience who might not be as familiar with the text of the prompt. After all, in an open job talk you are likely to have some members of the search committee in attendance as well as those who might be more removed from the search process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Amanda describes, I framed my response to the prompt as a critique of it. In essence, I argued that framing DH education as about acquiring a set of skills would undercut the prospect for DH pedagogy to make real, transformative change in the lives of students and institutions. There were a few reasons I took such a perpendicular approach to the question. I had worked in the Scholars’ Lab as a student, so I had some sense of the philosophy of the institution at which I was interviewing. I knew at least a portion of the room would be open to the kind of critique I wanted to offer. For better or worse, I also wanted the talk to show the kind of hire I would be. In other words, I didn’t want to present myself as having one set of views at the interview stage only to be hired and reveal myself to have a set of opinions and beliefs that wouldn’t fit with the institution. If the search committee was looking for someone who really thought of DH education in terms of skills acquisition, I was not that person. They would not be happy with me in this position, and I would not be happy trying to act in it. Better, I thought, to get it all out there. Like Amanda says below, it’s worth noting that not all candidates have the comfort and privilege of being able to make a decision like this as part of the interview process. The approach worked for me, but it might not work for others in different situations. You best know your own circumstances. I do think it’s worth trying to use the hiring process to suss out in small ways the kind of environment in which you would be employed and whether you can be happy there, but you don’t necessarily need to use your job talk to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;experiences&quot;&gt;Experiences&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The audience for a job talk is going to show up to learn about you and your qualifications in relation to the job for which they’ve brought you in. This can be tricky, as in a public talk the audience will contain a diverse range of people. The search committee can be expected to have spent time with your CV and cover letter, but, while those documents are typically circulated in advance, you cannot assume that everyone at a public talk will have given the same attention to those documents. So, while you don’t want to wholly reiterate your background, you do need to share some of your qualifications. I think of this as an opportunity to contextualize some of your experiences in a richer way so that your work can play for the whole audience regardless of how familiar they are with your work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By richer context, I mean that a job talk is a good place to take the things listed on a CV, select two or three, and deploy them in service of a larger vision for the position (more on that below). What did you learn from working with X? How does Y connect to the kinds of work you will be doing at institution Z? I often find it useful to pick a few things from my background and ask “so what?” of them repeatedly until I feel that they stand on their own as a self-reflective moment in the talk. You can use an otherwise boring and rote listing of experiences to show an audience &lt;strong&gt;how&lt;/strong&gt; you will work in a position by reflecting on the work you have already done. In the Scholars’ Lab talk, I talked about my work at &lt;a href=&quot;https://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/&quot;&gt;WLUDH&lt;/a&gt;, a coursebook I was co-writing with a faculty collaborator, and my experiences with curriculum design. But examples like these wouldn’t stand on their own - I thought of them as evidence in the larger argument I was making about how I think about DH teaching. Another way to think about all this: in an essay, you are likely to cite other authors or texts as you make your argument. In job talks I think of the evidence as potentially drawing from either your own experiences or other example projects/texts in DH. By weaving these together, your job talk can show both your personal qualifications and your sense of how your work connects to the broader field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;understanding&quot;&gt;Understanding&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To some degree, the audience will expect you to signal that you know what the job will entail. It’s always difficult to know exactly what the day to day life at a place will be like, and most of the time a candidate won’t actually make it to the job talk stage if their understanding of the position is in question. But conveying your understanding of the position can help nonetheless. I often tell students to think of it as a roleplaying challenge. You have imperfect knowledge of what the position will be like, but you have evidence from websites, projects, descriptions, and postings. Search committees are always trying to imagine each candidate into the position. Why not meet them halfway and start to imagine yourself into the position in your job talk? There are, of course, ways to do this poorly - I would not go into a talk saying “I will entirely transform everything in my first week. Only I have the solutions to your problems.” You will never have all the answers. Furthermore, positions always have pressures and needs that are difficult to perceive from the outside, and it can be useful to acknowledge that. I like to offer this formulation: “Given that I know you are working on X, I would take my experiences with Y to work towards Z with you all.” Syntactically it’s not actually a formula I would recommend, but as an exercise in thinking it can get you in the direction of good thinking about yourself in relation to a job. In that way, you’re making transparent the kind of thought process that you will bring to the position. And you’re helping the search committee by shaping the imaginative exercise of hiring for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this well, you’ll need to do research on the position but also the institution. If the position has existed before, what kind of work did they previously do? What kind of projects did they take on? Does the job description appear to be different in some way from that previous body of work? The institution can also offer clues: libraries, small liberal arts colleges, and cultural heritage institutions (to name a few) each carry with them certain assumptions about the work that they do, and these categories can offer evidence for you as you start to determine what kind of work the place values. You might also look at projects undertaken, grants and new initiatives that might be in process, recent hires, and the like. Some institutions might even offer explicit statements of values that you can explore. The Scholars’ Lab, for example, has published a series of &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/charter/&quot;&gt;charters&lt;/a&gt; describing how we think about our work. I had the benefit for my presentation of having worked with the Scholars’ Lab as a student. So I knew something of how they thought of themselves, and I similarly tried to frame my interest in working with DH students towards progressive, transformative reform in higher education. But I only knew the Scholars’ Lab from the student’s perspective - I had to make a lot of educated guesses about how they thought of their work and their students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One further thought: applying for jobs can be especially scary as a student. It’s all too easy to think, “I am a PhD student in literature! What do I know about institutional collaboration for DH education?” But you probably know more than you think! You’ve likely experienced a number of these issues from the student side, so you actually have valuable experiences with them. Many administrators are desperate to get student voices on a range of issues, and your direct experience can provide a useful perspective when combined with research about the other sorts of stakes, pressures, and questions that the position might engage with. It’s just a matter of imagining yourself from the other side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vision&quot;&gt;Vision&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This point is not one that I’m sure is required by the generic conventions of general DH staff jobs. Lots of people leave it off. But it is an element that I often think about, and I know that, of the job presentations that I’ve attended, all of the ones I considered the best included some sense of a vision for the work they will do. I was trained that a piece - be it an essay or a talk - should have an argument to it. So it’s difficult for me to imagine preparing a job talk that doesn’t also offer an argument, a philosophy, a vision for the work. In the context of the Scholars’ Lab talk, I explicitly framed the position I was applying for as someone who thinks past and beyond the prompt I was given. This was my closing sentence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Foremost, then, I see the Head of Graduate Programs as someone who takes the lists, documents, and curricula that I have discussed and connects them to the people that serve them and that they are meant to speak to. This person is one who builds relationships, who navigates the prepositions of my title.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I presented a vision of the position as one that fundamentally cared about the people and their development more than the skills associated with digital humanities. For me at least, it’s important that a talk say something, even in a genre as strange as a job presentation. “Vision” can be a big baggy term with little meaning to it. But you might approach it by asking a series of questions of yourself - why is this position important? what do I see as the fundamental role of this position? What are the top three verbs I would associate with this position? How can I frame this position as being vital to the mission of the institution? A job description answers the “what” of a position - what about the “why”? In trying to work in a sense of your philosophy for the work, you’re helping a search committee to further imagine what kind of a colleague you would be. I think it will also make for a more engaging job talk. And that job talk is also likely to be easier to write if you’re engaged with the topic of it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last note on DH / alt-ac public speaking. In some disciplines it is common to read your talk. Job presentations often seem to be done from notes instead. I try to operate somewhere in the middle. For my longer presentations I write my talk, memorize as much as I can, and then give some version of it more or less off the cuff but with the talk in front of me for reference. The result is something that is bloggable, has a shape to it, is more engaging than reading from a paper, but more polished than a presentation fully off the cuff. I’ve written about this elsewhere if you want more detail about &lt;a href=&quot;https://walshbr.com/blog/dh-public-speaking/&quot;&gt;my process&lt;/a&gt; for preparing for talks. It feels a bit idiosyncratic, but it could work for you as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;amanda&quot;&gt;Amanda:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My job talk thoughts are biased toward the roles I’ve given a candidate’s talk for—tenure-track faculty roles (interdisciplinary lab; library with digital humanities focus) and the SLab co-director role (library staff). You might also wish to check out talks from others who’ve applied to related DHy and library roles for more approaches—&lt;a href=&quot;https://readywriting.org/faculty-development/faculty-development-for-the-21st-century-and-beyond/&quot;&gt;Lee Skallerup Bessette&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://celestesharpe.com/onward/&quot;&gt;Celeste Tuong Vy Sharpe&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrisbourg.wordpress.com/2015/07/12/infrastructure-and-culture-a-job-talk/&quot;&gt;Chris Bourg&lt;/a&gt;—or visit the &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/groups/academic-job-market-support-network/documents/&quot;&gt;Academic Job Market Support Network&lt;/a&gt; on Humanities Commons, a forum created by Hannah Alpert-Abrams where folks have uploaded a variety of humanities-related job materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;responding-to-job-talk-prompts-in-general&quot;&gt;Responding to job talk prompts, in general&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll likely be given a prompt to reply to via your talk. In both of the talks shared below, I took a mild risk in explaining why I was responding a bit differently than probably expected to each prompt. I’ll talk about the privileges that allowed me to take these small risks below; if you do not have those privileges, you’ll probably want to respond more directly to prompts than I did, yet still with some changes from how you might answer the prompt if, for example, someone asked you the same thing during Q&amp;amp;A or a panel interview. That is: a job talk prompt is intended to be something that each candidate should be able to answer, and is thus often fairly abstracted and open to interpretation. Sometimes, creating a question that will work for all candidates results in a franken-prompt containing multiple questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might just be a question of how you frame your response to yourself, but my recommendation is to not treat this as you would an essay question on a test: no one is scoring you for explicitly mentioning or responding to the letter of each question in a prompt. An explicit answer to all portions of a prompt can be fine, but it can also make for a poorly structured, hard to listen to talk. I’ve found it more useful to use the prompt as a prompt, rather than as a question—that is, a suggestion of topics your audience might want to know your thoughts on. (In combination with the HR-approved job ad, it might offer more specific clues to local contexts or challenges you could ask about…) I try to give a talk that shares both the philosophies guiding my professional practice and very specific examples from my past work as illustrations. What your audience may remember is whether your talk presented you as 1) someone up to the job’s tasks, and 2) someone who would be a good and healthy addition to the local community. I’m guessing most people won’t even notice, much less care, if your talk isn’t an explicit response to the prompt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below, I’ll discuss how I worked through a response to the prompts for two of my past successful job talks, and then comment on the structure and contents of each talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;scholars-lab-managing-director-talk&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab Managing Director Talk&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read the full text and slides of this talk &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/disrupt-the-humanities-managing-director-job-talk/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talk prompt was:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;The digital has the potential to be a disruptive force in humanities scholarship, giving scholars the means to critique, reimagine, and transform ideas, theories, material artifacts, and even interpersonal relationships. Using examples from your own collaborations with faculty, graduate students, and staff, please discuss how this disruption can be successfully embodied in scholarly inquiry, as well as in the cultivation of people and organizations.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was recruited to apply to this job while working in a comfortable role (tenure-track library faculty) with some stellar colleagues and local resources, so it was safe for me to take some risks in my interview. Because paying my rent did not depend on receiving a job offer, I was able to pay more attention to whether the role would be good for me, to be more open about my values and what I wanted in a workplace. So when something in the prompt made me uncomfortable, I decided I wanted to speak to that from the very start of my talk. This turned out well, but could have gone badly, had I failed to convince the audience of the worth of my perspective, or offended the folks who wrote the prompt (assumedly, these were the folks on my search committee and/or folks I’d be reporting through).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prompt wasn’t explicitly positioning “disruption” as a positive force, but that assumption felt at least implicit enough (disruption allowing reform, wanting that to be “successful”) that I was uncomfortable not speaking specifically to the problems with that. (Part of my reaction was from past experience giving a job talk at a “demo or die” pro-language-of-disruption institution, and my discomfort about how that place’s mixture of amazing colleagues but also very shiny resources temporarily pushed me more toward more disregard for the harms of disruption.) I’ve learned that most terms invoke both positive and negative possibilities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valuing openness does harm to cultural practices intended for limited access (see e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://localcontexts.org/tk-labels/&quot;&gt;Traditional Knowledge labels’&lt;/a&gt; approach to this issue)
Speaking at a highly abstracted level about “diversity” or “social justice” can disadvantage acting on specific harms including racism and classism.
In Data Feminism, Catherine D’Ignazio and Lauren Klein discuss a number of terms that connote “imagined objectivity” and alternative terms that better “strengthen real objectivity”, e.g. “ethics” =&amp;gt; “justice”, “bias” =&amp;gt; “oppression”, “fairness” =&amp;gt; “equity” (I learned this from Neil Selwyn’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://data-smart-schools.net/2019/02/03/data-feminism-introductory-thoughts/&quot;&gt;review of their book&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to avoid the harm often done in the name of “disruption” treated as a context-less good. And I knew that Scholars’ Lab had a history of publicly valuing many of the same things I valued, e.g. from reading the &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/charter/&quot;&gt;staff charter&lt;/a&gt;, and appreciating staff’s tweets and conference talks. So my approach wasn’t actually a huge risk, but enough had recently changed in terms of the lab and library’s staff and work that if those values had shifted unbeknownst to me, I would probably be able to choose not to work there without harm to my livelihood. And I was applying to co-direct the lab, so there was more space to safely share thinking that might be a change to the institution’s current values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is all to say, the first sentence of my SLab job talk was: “My digital humanities is not disruptive.” I won’t repeat the rest of my talk, as the first few slides explain why I diverged from the prompt, how I thought about the positive potentials of DH. I did respond to the part of the prompt that indicated what the desired outcomes of (a positive definition of) disruption were to them, and in particular noted that people were mentioned multiple times (relationships, specifics examples of collaboration, organizations). After defining what my definition and goals for DH were against a negative read of “disruption”, I spoke to the prompt’s emphasis on people by structuring the rest of my talk around two examples of people-centric work (my &lt;a href=&quot;https://infiniteulysses.com&quot;&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/a&gt; participatory edition, and founding the &lt;a href=&quot;https://tinyurl.com/DHSlack&quot;&gt;Digital Humanities Slack&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attending to the people behind scholarship was a way for me to give the audience a sense of how I might be as a colleague. In my talk, I cited people who impacted how I think and work, regardless of the format (book, article, tweet, panel discussion, lunch conversation, something someone pointedly didn’t say) and regardless of if that person identifies as a scholar. If they contributed to how you think, you should cite them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I need to mention privilege again: Some people think less of you for having co-authors or other collaborators, as if that shows your effort was smaller rather than greater. If you aren’t read as male, some people may assume you didn’t do the coding or other technical work on your DH project. If you’re hurting for a job and/or already have other biases working against how people treat you, you might need to be more emphatic about your individual contributions to scholarship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this job talk, I tried to speak to people who value or assume different things than me, e.g. folks who would appreciate an explicit discussion of how something functions as scholarship, rather than assuming that people recognize the work behind &lt;a href=&quot;http://InfiniteUlysses.com&quot;&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&quot;https://tinyurl.com/DHSlack&quot;&gt;DH Slack&lt;/a&gt; as scholarship. And given I’ve had some experiences that are likely to be construed as academic success, like my dissertation project being cited in The New York Times, I think it’s reasonable to make sure your interviewers know about that—even if you’re kind of uncomfortable with that being seen as a metric toward whether you should be hired. But I also spoke to things I was proud of that others might not value or see as relevant to scholarship, like receiving emails from a variety of non-faculty strangers happy about discovering my DH project. Interviewing necessitates anxiety, and it’s a privilege to be safe and comfortable sharing some pieces of yourself during a job visit—but I’ve found myself happiest after interviews, including an interview where I did not get offered the job, when I felt I brought and shared more of my full self during the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I was basically going to rewrite Brandon and my post about how to share our job-market knowledge without prescriptively reinforcing classist, sexist, etc. notions of individual value and what counts as scholarship, so instead I’ll just link to &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/dh-cover-letters/&quot;&gt;that post&lt;/a&gt; again—I learned a lot from the discussions we had before deciding to continue blogging our past job search experiences and advice, and we tried to capture those ideas about a more just and affirming way of supporting jobseekers in that post.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;purdue-tenure-track-faculty-dh-specialist-talk&quot;&gt;Purdue Tenure-Track Faculty DH Specialist Talk&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the full text and slides of this talk &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/02/28/DHjobtalk&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talk prompt was:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Digital humanities and the research library: opportunities and challenges for academic libraries and librarians. Draw upon your experience and knowledge as well as citing research literature in library/archival/information science, and/or disciplinary literature relating to digital humanities. (Audience: Libraries staff and faculty)

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with my SLab job talk, I quibbled mildly with this prompt, and explained why at the start of the job talk:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;There are already many recent voices defining what the digital humanities (or DH) is, what a library does, and exactly how much DH and libraries overlap as academic fields. I didn’t want to rehash those debates, so I put together an online Zotero bibliography with bunch of pertinent readings, which you can access via [tinyurl.com/dhlibraries](https://tinyurl.com/dhlibraries). You’ll also be able to find any work I cite in this talk there…Pulling together over fifty works defining DH and libraries, and strategizing this combination, wasn’t difficult.&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I wanted to focus on what DH might look like locally, given how I’d function if hired:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt; It was harder to find case studies of the specific, day-to-day tactics of successful combinations of DH and libraries. So, in wanting to discuss the specific question of DH library service today, I’ll try to give some specific examples, spoken and on screen, of the types of events, workflows, and services I’m envisioning. I’d like to focus on what both the strategy and the tactics of a user-focused service ethic look like, when combined with 1) the digital humanities commitment to collaboration, and 2) recognizing scholarship in all areas of professional practice.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small thing, but I like that I included an explicit reference to caring about timekeeping while outlining my talk (“I’ll be talking for around 15 minutes, after which we’ll have a lot of time for discussion”) to help the audience pace their attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I know that community, I think the audience would have appreciated more time spent on what DH is and what the arguments about DH and libraries are than I gave them. It’s hard to gauge that, or know who will be at your talk! I think I did okay by defining what DH would look like locally if I were hired, but sharing a few specific projects that show the breadth of what DH can be would have improved the talk. I’d recommend focusing on what DH is to you, and what you hope for DH to be (inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/elikaortega/status/618097310505938944&quot;&gt;Élika Ortega&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Digital Humanities Pedagogy and Opportunities for Hope</title>
   <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/digital-humanities-pedagogy-and-opportunities-for-hope/"/>
   <updated>2019-10-16T09:45:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/digital-humanities-pedagogy-and-opportunities-for-hope</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Crossposted to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/digital-humanities-pedagogy-and-opportunities-for-hope&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In September, I visited Emory University in conjunction with the launch of their &lt;a href=&quot;http://digitalscholarship.emory.edu/partner/learn/ddsp.html&quot;&gt;new graduate fellowship&lt;/a&gt; for students aiming to incorporate digital projects in their dissertations. This is the second of two posts sharing materials from the events I took part in while there. I was asked to give &lt;a href=&quot;http://walshbr.com/blog/getting-from-here-to-there/&quot;&gt;a workshop on project development for graduate students&lt;/a&gt; as well as an open talk on digital humanities pedagogy. The text of what follows pertains to the open talk I gave, where I was asked to give a broad overview of how the Scholars’ Lab works with students. I write a talk for situations like these, but I try to avoid straight-up reading the text (&lt;a href=&quot;http://walshbr.com/blog/dh-public-speaking/&quot;&gt;more info on how I approach public speaking in DH available here&lt;/a&gt;). So what you will see below is more like a roadmap of the general gist of what we talked about. I did not consult the text too much in the moment. The only other relevant piece of framing that you will need is that I added the phrase “he works for the students” to the end of the bio I gave Sarah McKee (Senior Associate Director for Publishing at the Bill and Carol Fox Center for Humanistic Inquiry) to read when she introduced me. Talk begins below!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Title slide&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello! I’m Brandon Walsh. I am the Head of Student Programs at the Scholars’ Lab, a community lab for experimental scholarship in all fields, particularly informed by digital humanities, spatial technologies, and cultural heritage. You will hear a lot more about what we mean by that in the talk to come, one that I have titled “Digital Humanities Pedagogy and Opportunities for Hope.” Thank you so much for having me and for coming today to hear me talk. I am truly grateful for the opportunity to speak with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/2.png&quot; alt=&quot;zotero collection, links, and acknowledments&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to first start out by offering a couple links and thanks. If you need access to the slides or the transcript of this talk (or you’re interested in what I shared with your students in &lt;a href=&quot;http://walshbr.com/blog/getting-from-here-to-there/&quot;&gt;the workshop&lt;/a&gt; earlier today), you can find those resources at &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/Emory-Talks&quot;&gt;this top link&lt;/a&gt;. I have also made a &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/DHPedagogyAndHope&quot;&gt;Zotero collection&lt;/a&gt; here with all the resources I mention in the talk in case you want to take a look at them later on. And finally, most importantly, I wanted to take a moment to express gratitude to everyone whose work has brought me here today. I’m very grateful to all my colleagues in the Scholars’ Lab whose work you will hear about in a moment, especially Amanda Visconti, Ronda Grizzle, Jeremy Boggs, Laura Miller, and Shane Lin. And I would also like to express my thanks to Sarah McKee, Lisa Flowers, Anandi Silva Knuppel, and all the ECDS students for making this trip possible and invigorating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sarah asked me to give a high-level overview of the Scholars’ Lab and how we work with students. I will do that today, but my standard disclaimer about the Scholars’ Lab is that we are a complex entity with many different folks doing many kinds of jobs. And you will get a different path through our work depending on who you ask. I am the Head of Student Programs, so given my work and interests you might come away from this talk thinking, “they only work with students.” This is not true! We have an R&amp;amp;D team and spatial technologies staff that work with the entire university, students, faculty, and library staff alike on a variety of different projects related to digital scholarship, digital preservation, and digital project development. So what you will hear about today is about my own particular corner of the lab. One of my colleagues might have a different, overlapping story. My story is about our students, though I am happy to help flesh the full picture out for you if you would like during discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Overview of what is to come, text to follow&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the risk of tipping my hand too early, I wanted to offer an overview of what is to come. I’ll move back and forth between example and theory, but the main takeaways, if I had to offer them are these. First, DH pedagogy does not just take place in the classroom, and it’s not just about DH. Second, digital humanities pedagogy is pedagogy. Third, DH pedagogy at every level should consider, intersect with, and reconstruct desire paths through the academy. I’ll talk more about all of these ideas in a moment. I’m not going to be offering any practical thoughts on how to carry out DH pedagogy, though I’m happy to do so in the discussion afterwards. This is more a talk about the animating philosophy for DH and pedagogy as we try to practice it in the lab, about the idea that teaching can offer spaces for hope in the university.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chad Sansing bio page&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Sarah invited me here today, as is usually the case for things like this, she asked me to send her a bio. I always dread this part of giving talks. When I was a student, I always felt like I hadn’t done enough, and I hated hearing people read my short list back to me. Now that I have been working in the field for a bit longer, I still find it embarrassing for different reasons. So I decided to take a cue from Chad Sansing of the Mozilla Foundation and do something with this moment of discomfort. In his &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@chadsansing&quot;&gt;bio on Medium&lt;/a&gt; he mentions, a bit tongue in cheek, “I teach for the users.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tron movie poster&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to spend my entire time here reiterating the plot of the 1982 movie Tron, but, in my reading at least, Sansing’s bio is a riff on a line from that movie: “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8kcgosLwPDE&quot;&gt;he fights for the users&lt;/a&gt;.” The line describes the titular character of the movie, a security program who fights other fascist computer programs on behalf of the users who have been locked out of the computing world. It’s a lot. But I like Sansing’s adoption of it here, and I wanted to try it out for myself. I like the way that his bio ties up his identity into a kind of mission statement. “Who am I” becomes “why am I here?” He is here to teach, and he’s here to teach the users how to take back control of the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bio I gave Sarah ended with the phrase “he works for the students.” That phrase is a mission statement and also the subject of this talk, which will deal with how we work in the Scholars’ Lab to have care and consideration towards our student collaborators suffuse everything we do. I’ll talk against the ideas that teaching only takes place in the classroom and that administrative work has nothing to do with teaching.  I’ll start with what we do in the lab “for the students” and why. Second, I’ll contextualize this briefly as happening against the backdrop of a larger crisis in higher education. Third, I’ll offer thoughts about how we can shape a DH pedagogy that responds to such emergencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/7.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of a desire path - a paved path to the left with barriers on it to prevent speeding cyclists. To right, a trodden path made by pedestrians and cyclists avoiding the barriers and paved section entirely.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin. In the Scholars’ Lab, we try to start by approaching the whole student. We try to think about how our decisions affect lives and need to be informed by lives. Because administrative choices matter in big ways for people. When an application date gets set, who is eligible for a fellowship, or what kinds of work we allow as permissible in a particular context - choices like these affect the journeys our students are on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I would like to start by talking about paths. This image by an English Councillor circulated on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://digitalpedagogylab.com&quot;&gt;Digital Pedagogy Lab&lt;/a&gt; hashtag last month, and it illustrates a phenomenon called a “desire path” or a “desire line” – I would wager we have all seen them before. Desire lines are the paths made, over time, by people stepping on the same, unplanned path. They typically represent the organic actions of pedestrians as opposed to what was planned by the city designer. In this case, based on the Twitter conversation, the path you’re looking at appears to have been made over time by cyclists in response to the constructions you see on the left, obstacles deliberately put in place to discourage cyclists speeding along on this paved path. It is not difficult to imagine the accessibility issues caused by this same construction choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m taken with this image as a metaphor for the life of a graduate student in academia (caveat here that most of my comments will be about graduate students given who I tend to work with, but I think they are relevant for students generally as well). The image certainly resonates with me, coming as I do to work in the library without a library professional degree but instead with a PhD in English. In short, our students might get into this space for one reason, and we might imagine paths through it on their behalf. But everyone finds their own way through their own education and often through different means and to different ends than we anticipate. I certainly got pulled sideways at a certain point and wound up in a place I could not have envisioned at the beginning of my time at UVA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often wonder in related ways about my own activities in the administration of the Scholars’ Lab and in higher education more generally. In my role, I’m often making or offering small choices that are likely to affect the course of someone’s journey through their time as a student. These individual, local interventions in a person’s path - how do they fit into the larger journey for them? Am I helping people to form their own desire paths? Or am I the one throwing up barriers? How can I take those barriers down or help pave a new path to help the route be a little easier? Who am I to be making such decisions for other people? How can I take the responsibility of these choices as seriously as possible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this logic of the desire path, for student programs to service your community in a perfect world you will be offering a diverse slate of opportunities. Because your student population does not just have broad and diverse disciplinary research questions – they also come from a range of different backgrounds and life situations. An MA student, at UVA at least, has a different course load and does not typically teach. This puts them in a fundamentally different category financially, with different pressures and needs, from a PhD student. And what works for one will not work for the other. That is to say, any conversation about DH pedagogy, for me, starts and ends with a discussion of the lived circumstances of the students. Our student activities in the lab are foremost informed by a consideration for the diverse contexts and backgrounds that our students represent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/8.png&quot; alt=&quot;For students page of the slab site&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We try to make our programs fit those many needs, and we try to offer a number of different ways in to do so. The phrase “for the students” that I mentioned earlier is also pretty close to a page on our website where I try to collect everything that a student might be interested in knowing about us. This is the “For Students” page of the Scholars’ Lab website if you would like to check it out at &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/for-students&quot;&gt;http://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/for-students&lt;/a&gt;. I will talk about a few of these pieces in detail first from a nuts and bolts standpoint and then a theoretical one, though I am happy to talk in more depth about any one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/9.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of our makerspace&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We regularly offer two hourly wage positions for students in the lab. The first is that we employ hourly students in our makerspace as technologists assisting community members with 3D printing jobs, experimental electronics, or sewing and wearable electronics. No experience is necessary for a student to take on the role, and we typically train people up on the job. There are a number of makerspaces on campus, but ours is distinct for being committed to teaching folks how to do the printing themselves. So you don’t drop off a file and pick up a print - you learn how the technologies work. And our makerspace primarily caters to humanities students, though we do get a fair amount of traffic from science students who tend to find our space less crowded than the ones provided by the Engineering School.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/10.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mapping of Anne Whitney abroad&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, our GIS specialists &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/people/drew-macqueen/&quot;&gt;Drew McQueen&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/people/chris-gist/&quot;&gt;Chris Gist&lt;/a&gt; service needs related to spatial technologies for the entire University, and they regularly employ a GIS student collaborator to assist them in doing so. This student and these projects can come from across the university – not just the humanities. And they also frequently collaborate with local and regional governmental organizations on a variety of different geospatial projects. Our students are there at each step along the way as collaborators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/11.png&quot; alt=&quot;Will Rourk's Twitter account on scanning&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also engage students in an internship for course credit through the architecture school, where our 3D Data and Content Specialist, &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/people/will-rourk/&quot;&gt;Will Rourk&lt;/a&gt;, collaborates with them on the scanning of artifacts and spaces that are significant for cultural heritage purposes. They often carry out site visits in the region, and Will also collaborates with local museums on scanning objects of importance to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/12.png&quot; alt=&quot;3D model that resulted from scanning&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will then engages those same students in the production of 3D data based on these objects. Through the process, our student interns get a deep introduction to all different parts of a 3D data pipeline, and the work that they all do together is truly impressive. The previous tweet and this 3D model all relate to the McCormick observatory on UVA’s campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/13.png&quot; alt=&quot;Summary of the two year-long fellowship programs in the Scholars' Lab&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond these opportunities, we also offer two yearlong fellowship programs that offer deeper dives into digital humanities. These are the programs that I most directly supervise. Our higher-level DH fellowship is for advanced PhD students at the dissertation stage who want to work on a project related to their research. They teach some, but they are largely doing a deep dive into developing a professional portfolio that will serve them on the job market. And our &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org&quot;&gt;Praxis Program&lt;/a&gt; is something of an introduction to digital humanities by way of project-based pedagogy. The six students in this fellowship each year form a cohort and work collaboratively on a self-designed project over the course of two semesters. The students drive the program: the fall feels more like a seminar or workshop with us at the front of the room, but the spring is owned by them. We flick them in a direction, but they take the project and develop it in a way that feels authentically theirs both in spirit, scope, and shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s a piece of what we do in the lab, and you might have noticed just how much we do for students. I am well aware that the Scholars’ Lab is in a privileged position as far as resources go, both for centers for digital research and even within our own library. Over 2/3 of our budget goes directly to students, and we work directly with about 50 students each year. That’s a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt;. As anyone who works with budgets knows, our own budget is the result of longstanding and ongoing campaigns for more resources. I am grateful for allies in the library who recognize the value of supporting students and especially to those who fought for years before I was involved to get those numbers to where they are. These numbers are not settled, and we have to work to keep them every year. But I bring these points up to ask - what can an institution without this level of support do? What can an individual without the support of an institution do? What are small actions we can take in our pedagogy - particularly our DH pedagogy - to help the desire paths our students are trying to make for themselves, even when we’re limited by resource scarcity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/15.png&quot; alt=&quot;&amp;quot;I don't teach - quote from a colleague&amp;quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, one way of approaching these questions is to think more deeply about what we mean when we think of pedagogy. I remember one conversation I had about teaching, when a colleague offhandedly said, “Oh well I don’t teach.” And a nearby colleague agreed as well. I remember doing a double take. These were people who, to my mind, were constantly engaged in the work of teaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/16.png&quot; alt=&quot;&amp;quot;I don't teach - you who teach all the time.&amp;quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even besides the workshops they regularly give, these were people who mentored students, helped with their projects, and pair programmed beside them to help them learn. Furthermore, they’re fantastic teachers. The general culture in the Scholars’ Lab is one in which we constantly engage in peer mentoring. Digital Humanities is hard - there are so many fields. No one knows all of it, and we try to offer a spirit of generous assistance to each other every day as we find our way through this field. How, then, did I have an entirely different view of these colleagues than they did of their own work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think my colleagues were equating teaching with teaching classes as instructors of record. And, to be fair, sometimes I’m asked whether I am teaching or not in the upcoming semester, and I don’t quite know how to respond either. While I sometimes teach semester-long courses, my primary work is not in such traditional modes of instruction. While it’s not really the question they’re asking, my gut response is usually to think, “when am I not teaching?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/17.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pedagogy as habitus&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is to say that pedagogy is not something that only happens in the classroom. I especially like the way that Sean Michael Morris describes this notion in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insidehighered.com/digital-learning/article/2018/10/10/digital-learning-experts-reflect-evolving-field-new-book&quot;&gt;an interview&lt;/a&gt; with Jesse Stommel. They’re two prominent scholar-practitioners of critical digital pedagogy, and they’re the chief instigators behind Digital Pedagogy Lab. In an interview about their new collection An &lt;a href=&quot;https://urgencyofteachers.com/&quot;&gt;Urgency of Teachers&lt;/a&gt;, Morris describes pedagogy as not something we just enact in the classroom. Instead, it’s a system of beliefs that we carry with us. A way of orienting ourselves in the world. Or at least it should be. If we think about teaching and pedagogy as things that only take place when we’re in front of a classroom or with our names in an LMS, then I would argue that we’re not thinking of teaching in the fullest possible sense. The spaces for teaching are vast, and our students many. To be “for the students,” we need to think of education as a way of life. As something that runs deeper than sharing material with students. This about how we view them and their work. We’re always teaching, whether or not we’re in front of students for a whole semester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/18.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of charters&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s one thing to believe having values like these are important. But in the Lab we also believe it’s important to share them, and now we’re getting into the philosophy behind what we do. We believe it is important to write our work philosophies down and to explicitly say them in public. In the Scholars’ Lab, we believe in explicit statements of values called charters, documents that spell out your beliefs, goals, and ambitions. We have had our cohorts of Praxis students put charters together describing their shared ambitions and values each year for the last nine years. &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/charter/charter-2011-2012/&quot;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; you have one of the Praxis charters from one of the early cohorts. They cite free and generous credit, transparency, and an awareness of each other’s diverse backgrounds and disciplinary interests as important markers for them. The hope is that by encouraging our students to examine their shared group identity we will draw out a richer sense of themselves and each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year in conversation with &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/people/jeremy-boggs/&quot;&gt;Jeremy Boggs&lt;/a&gt; we realized that, even though we have our students write a charter every year, we hadn’t actually done one of our own, as a staff, for our student programs. We possessed a general charter for the lab, but we thought our student programs needed to explicitly share their own pedagogical philosophy and promises. It was time to make things clear and explicit. So we wrote one together. For the students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/19.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of student programs charter in particular&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find the whole charter on our website at &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/student-programs-charter&quot;&gt;http://scholarslab.org/student-programs-charter&lt;/a&gt;, and I’d encourage you to read it. It’s a document that is not perfect, but it’s one that I’m glad is out in the world. Here are a few excerpts from it that describe our approach to teaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/20.png&quot; alt=&quot;Excerpts from the student programs charter&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re here, and we care. We trust in students. We teach the whole person. We’re committed to advancing pedagogical practices that are equitable, just, and ethical. It’s important that our students know where we stand, and one of the first things I have our students do is read this document along with the more &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/charter/&quot;&gt;general charter for the Scholars’ Lab&lt;/a&gt;. Our pedagogies, the ways we think about our work with students, should be shared with them. In the Lab we believe they should be part of the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lest you think this is an artifact of the quotes I chose to emphasize, the charter doesn’t actually talk an awful lot about technology. It does occasionally, but only in oblique ways. We want our students to own their projects as well as their domains. We want them to fail in public in a way that pushes their comfort zone but not their safety. We all feel like imposters - many of us everyday. Some of you probably feel like imposters right now. I know I do. These points imply a certain interdisciplinary approach to technology, even though they are not specific to digital humanities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s also not lost on me that I’ve spent most of this talk on digital humanities pedagogy not talking all that much about &lt;em&gt;digital humanities&lt;/em&gt; pedagogy. And that’s part of the point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/21.png&quot; alt=&quot;DH pedagogy is pedagogy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digital humanities pedagogy is pedagogy. I’ll say that again. Digital humanities pedagogy is pedagogy. Similarly, to go back to Digital Pedagogy Lab, I’ve heard Sean Michael Morris say that the “digital” part of DPL is just an excuse to get people in the room to talk about pedagogy. The definition of digital humanities I usually give to students is one I draw from &lt;a href=&quot;https://isearch.asu.edu/profile/3146756&quot;&gt;Elizabeth Grumbach&lt;/a&gt;: DH is asking humanities questions &lt;em&gt;of&lt;/em&gt; technology and asking humanities questions &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; technology. DH pedagogy is certainly teaching that engages with those topics, materials, and methods, but leaving it there is akin to saying that you only teach if you’re an instructor of record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I feel a tad guilty staying wholly theoretical I want to pause for a moment to say that there are great resources for digital humanities pedagogy from a practical perspective: I highly recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomsbury.com/uk/using-digital-humanities-in-the-classroom-9781350029750/&quot;&gt;Using Digital Humanities in the Classroom&lt;/a&gt;, co-authored by Claire Battershill and Shawna Ross, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://digitalpedagogy.mla.hcommons.org/&quot;&gt;Digital Pedagogy in the Humanities&lt;/a&gt;, edited by Rebecca Frost Davis, Matthew K. Gold, Katherine D. Harris, and Jentery Sayers. These resources are exemplary for those seeking practical advice and examples on how to teach digital humanities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what I mean by “DH pedagogy is pedagogy” is that, for us in the Scholars’ Lab, a digital humanities pedagogy is one that thinks deeply and critically about the teaching itself and the interpersonal, societal, and institutional changes it purports to make. It’s not just about the classroom. That is to say, we certainly teach DH methods, tools, and thinking, but we’re more directly trying to think about how and why we do this work and what larger implications it might have. Digital humanities might be an especially good opportunity to make these sorts of interventions, and that brings me to the quote that the title of this talk is riffing on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/22.png&quot; alt=&quot;Henry Giroux quoting Freire, text to follow.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Opportunities for Hope” is a play on Henry Giroux quoting the work of Paulo Freire. In full it reads: “Hope demanded an anchoring in transformative practices, and one of the tasks of the progressive educator was to ‘unveil opportunities for hope, no matter what the obstacles may be.’” For Freire, education in its best shape was always about social reform, and he called for new forms of teaching that empowered students and upended traditional modes of instruction like the banking model for education that assumes students are empty vessels who need to have the knowledge of the instructor given to them only to regurgitate it back. And it’s this same spirit of transformation that we bring to the students who work with us in the Scholars’ Lab. How can our pedagogical practices as digital humanists open up space for new ideas for students, but more importantly, for imagining new lives? How can we unveil opportunities for hope, no matter the difficulties? Beyond simply giving them tools and methods, how can we go further and make the teaching we do be a political intervention?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/23.png&quot; alt=&quot;But it's all on fire&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More specifically, how do we unveil opportunities for hope in a climate like the one in which we all live, where it often feels higher education is on fire? Tenure track positions are vanishing, adjunctification is on the rise, and an enormous number of students and staff are in precarious positions. A so-called “free speech” crisis threatens actual free expression and freethinking in our classrooms. I could go on and on. I spoke about the privileged position the Scholars’ Lab is in, in terms of funding. But, no matter how much funding we’re able to direct to students, it’s never enough. There are always more students applying for fellowships than we have spots to give. Since I’ve been teaching, students have spoken with me about homelessness, food insecurity, precarious finances, uncertain job futures, mental health crises, chronic health conditions, and more. And I know the student populations I’ve worked with are not unique in higher education. How do we find hope for ourselves and for our students in the face of these situations? And what can pedagogy do here? I’ll offer three provisional responses to this question. In the face of a crisis in higher education, we should think of the work we do as creating spaces of shelter and intervention, as empowering student voices, and as changing culture more broadly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/24.png&quot; alt=&quot;Feminist lab symposium&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first response is that we can think of the teaching work that we do in digital humanities spaces as work that seeks to shelter and also to intervene. “&lt;a href=&quot;https://whatisafeministlab.online/&quot;&gt;What is a feminist lab?&lt;/a&gt;” was a symposium that took place at University of Colorado Boulder earlier this year. I got permission from &lt;a href=&quot;https://jwernimont.com/&quot;&gt;Jacqueline Wernimont&lt;/a&gt; to cite her remarks, quoted here: “A lab can be a technology to survive the institutions we work in while we seek to transform them.” Our students in the Scholars’ Lab frequently refer to it as an oasis in the larger academy, by which I take them to mean that we value their futures, their concerns, and anxieties in ways that are not as well supported elsewhere. As they develop charters and have conversations about the values they want to develop and promote during their time with us, I often encourage them to think of it as an opportunity to shape the sort of kind, generous, and transformative space they want to see in the academy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is to say, we also engage students in a wide variety of support that is not particular to wage employment or research. Some of these are programmatic. We offer mock interviews if students wind up applying for library or digital humanities related jobs. We read materials. We circulate job postings relevant to this kind of work. But more generally we have frank conversations with students about our lives and theirs and try to make space for them in ways that might otherwise be difficult in other parts of the university. Our fellowships don’t carry grades, we allow deferment of our fellowships, and we generally try to make lives a little easier. For us, this is the work of pedagogy, and the fact that we are operating in a library-based digital humanities space helps facilitate this. Your own mileage may vary, as your circumstances are likely to be different. Given your own limitations, how can you use your position as teachers to inject more kindness into the academy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/25.png&quot; alt=&quot;UCLA Student Collaborators Bill of Rights&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second – we can respond by asking, “where are the students?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important that we keep student interests and needs in mind. They are an important audience for our work, but sometimes they can disappear from the conversation when we discuss long-term strategy. So simply asking how students fit in is a place to start, and even small actions like making sure the word “student” appears on mission statements can be important interventions. But we can go further.  Student voices need to be included in discussions about their own education. Digital humanities pedagogy is often quite amenable to this, as project-based pedagogy of the sort that is common in DH can often invite students to have an active role in shaping their experiences. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://humtech.ucla.edu/news/a-student-collaborators-bill-of-rights/&quot;&gt;UCLA Student Collaborator Bill of Rights&lt;/a&gt; has other good advice for how to engage student voices and to make sure that you’re doing so in an ethical way. It’s a touchstone for us in the Lab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/26.png&quot; alt=&quot;ILIADS splash page&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Small Liberal Arts Community (as exemplified by &lt;a href=&quot;http://iliads.org&quot;&gt;ILiADS&lt;/a&gt;) offers fantastic models for how you can engage students as true partners in research projects and disrupt the labor distinctions that all too often exist in our work. I’d encourage you to explore the ILiADS site for examples of projects that might offer models as you think through how to work with students. For my money, the SLAC community is offering some of the most exciting digital pedagogy work. This kind of flattened distinction between student and teacher, as much as possible, is something we try to aim for in the Scholars’ Lab. It’s expressed in a concise way, I think, in this Instagram story by Nicholas Payton, a prominent jazz trumpet player and composer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/27.png&quot; alt=&quot;Quote by Nicholas Payton, text to follow&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a recent “ask me anything” session on Instagram, Payton was asked, “Who are the best trumpet teachers alive right now?” He responded, “There are no great teachers, only great students who give tools to other students.” That is the world I want to live in. A world in which the Scholars’ Lab students see themselves as experts, and in which their staff and faculty see themselves as equal partners in the pursuit of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re all students at the end of the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/28.png&quot; alt=&quot;Praxis program splash page&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can sometimes feel difficult to square with digital humanities, though, where often we quite literally have things we need to share with students that they are encountering for the first time. One thing we try to do in the Lab, beyond adapting our curriculum to the needs of the students, is talk to our students about the work of teaching and learning in which we are all engaged. We talk to them about why we are doing what we are doing, what difficulties we’re having, and what thoughts they might have for making a better experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I mentioned the Praxis Program, our yearlong fellowship where our students go from soup-to-nuts with digital humanities, from knowing little to launching their own collaborative digital project by the end. For years, the interdisciplinary makeup of the team has been a recipe for real interpersonal conflict. Usually in March. Every year, right when the rubber hits the road and they’re trying to launch their project. Finally this past year we decided to talk to the team about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the second session of Praxis this year, Amanda Visconti and I ran a discussion for our new cohort of Praxis students on good collaboration and community. And we laid this pedagogical problem out – we talked about issues we had in the program in the past not as interpersonal issues between specific people but as expressions of larger difficulties in collaborative work. We discussed what seemed to help and what did not. What’s more, we also talked about what good collaboration looked like for each other and how the students could make sure they treated each other with respect and kindness first. The students took the conversation very seriously. Last year was the best year yet as far as collaboration is concerned, and Amanda and I just ran the conversation for a new cohort last week. In short, there’s no need to treat pedagogy like something that has to be hidden from your students. Particularly in DH, as it asks so much of students professionally, interpersonally, and emotionally, we need to involve student voices in the development of good teaching practices. They deserve it, and everyone’s experience will be enriched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, and I think it’s apparent from this talk, we have to think about the work that we do, even at the level of the individual assignment, as engaged in a larger project of shifting the culture of the university. When I spoke to the graduate students earlier today, we ended our workshop by talking about values. The workshop was called “getting from here to there” with a digital project, but the point was that there is always going to be another project. Another semester. Another student. It’s more important to think about why you’re doing this work: what are the animating philosophies behind what you’re doing? I’ve tried to give you a glimpse today of the “why” for the Scholars’ Lab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I encouraged the students earlier to think about their work as opportunities to open up small spaces for more generous, kind, and productive spaces in the academy, to imagine the future they want to see into the world. In the Lab we see our work as part of a larger attempt to shift the culture of the university, both in terms of what graduate training in the humanities can look like but also in terms of what kinds of conversations are acceptable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/30.png&quot; alt=&quot;PHD Plus Splash Page&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At UVA, we’re plugged into a larger network of like-minded programs working to train graduate students for a broad range of lives and future careers. This program, called &lt;a href=&quot;https://phdplus.virginia.edu/index&quot;&gt;PHD+&lt;/a&gt;, has been instrumental for us in helping to see that the work we’re doing as being part of a larger movement to rethink what graduate education can look like. Thinkers like &lt;a href=&quot;https://katinarogers.com&quot;&gt;Katina Rogers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cathydavidson.com/&quot;&gt;Cathy Davidson&lt;/a&gt;, both at CUNY, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.seanmichaelmorris.com/&quot;&gt;Sean Michael Morris&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jessestommel.com/&quot;&gt;Jesse Stommel&lt;/a&gt;, co-founders of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digitalpedagogylab.com/&quot;&gt;Digital Pedagogy Lab&lt;/a&gt;, have been instrumental for me in seeing the work of the classroom as intimately connected to the work outside it. And, to go back to my point about student voices, we talk about these issues explicitly with our students. We have a session on diverse career options for them, on labor precarity and employment in digital humanities. We’re not solely interested in getting them jobs; we want to make sure that they can find their ways to happy futures no matter the outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/31.png&quot; alt=&quot;Desire path image again.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to bring it back to an earlier image and earlier questions - when working on DH pedagogy decisions I’d encourage you to think about this image. I know I will. How are our decisions helping people navigate their own desire paths through the university? Throwing up new barriers for them? Paving new roads? How can we make even small assignments part of larger culture shifts? How might digital humanities pedagogy, in libraries and out of them, make space for these conversations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s my talk. Thanks for listening. I’m happy to talk more about Tron, the Scholars’ Lab, nuts and bolts of digital humanities pedagogy, other opportunities for hope, and anything else you’d like.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>DH Cover Letters</title>
   <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/dh-cover-letters/"/>
   <updated>2019-10-09T10:03:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/dh-cover-letters</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Co-authored with &lt;a href=&quot;http://amandavisconti.com/&quot;&gt;Amanda Visconti&lt;/a&gt;. Crossposted to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/dh-cover-letters/&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab blog&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://academicjobmarketsupportnetwork.hcommons.org/2019/10/09/how-we-talk-and-write-about-dh-jobs/&quot;&gt;the Academic Job Market Support Network&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://literaturegeek.com/2019/10/10/digital-humanities-cover-letters-job-advice&quot;&gt;Amanda’s personal blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early this summer, we (authors Brandon and Amanda!) planned a post about job search materials, but finishing up the draft got delayed by several weeks. In the intervening time, a small Twitter debate on the subject of academic job advice occurred, and we ended up holding off this post for a few months while discussing how to do it well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The debate in question: someone shared the job advice they generally give students on the academic job market, and folks responded with frustrations about the prescriptiveness, privilege, and goals of the academic job advice genre. Since then, we’ve also appreciated &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hralperta/status/1143557245168476160?s=21&quot;&gt;inspiring work being done on the topic by Hannah Alpert-Abrams&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/groups/academic-job-market-support-network/&quot;&gt;The Academic Job Market Support Network&lt;/a&gt; that she spearheads shares a lot of the spirit behind what we intended to do with our job search materials, so we’re taking this as an opportunity to revisit the post we had planned. We have both uploaded cover letters from our pasts to the AJMSN (Brandon’s letter &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/?get_group_doc=1003473/1570202258-HeadofGraduateProgramsCoverLetter.docx&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and Amanda’s letter &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/?get_group_doc=1003473/1570038081-CoverLetter.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), and we talk a bit about our reasoning below. We’ll offer some general thoughts about job searches in digital humanities, and annotate each other’s cover letters. We thought the latter might be a useful exercise beyond just sharing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;slightly-better-job-advice-take-two&quot;&gt;Slightly Better Job Advice, Take Two&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Framing an academic job search exclusively in terms of handy tips undervalues the degree of luck that goes into any search. &lt;em&gt;Do these things&lt;/em&gt;, such advice seems to suggest, &lt;em&gt;and the just and right meritocracy will reward you with a job&lt;/em&gt;. But the academic job market is anything but just, and anything but a pure measure of merit&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The same is true, of course, for job markets beyond academia. Digital humanities job searches, be they for faculty positions or otherwise, suffer from the same issues. Internally we’ve had a lot of conversation about how to share job advice with our students. We’re frequently called upon to do so, and we want to do it well. So we thought it worth sharing a few of the things we try to consider below. Keep in mind, of course, that this is not an exhaustive list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The academic job market is not identical with all job markets in academia. There is a range of different careers that engage in intellectual work, careers that might be called alt-ac (though there are good reasons for not using that term to describe them). Paths to these careers are often just as obscured as paths to professorships, and resources for how to navigate these types of job searches are scarce. Resources for finding and thinking about these kinds of careers are one of the key things we can provide students.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Students need our support. In particular, refusing to share resources about job searches, even if the act is well meaning, can reinforce privileged access to those same materials. Our initial reason for writing this post was that we noticed we were repeatedly sharing the same cover letters with folks looking for work. We found ourselves wondering how many other people at UVA or elsewhere might not know to ask for such resources.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Offers to aid in job searches, on and off the tenure track, are better when they go beyond lists of advice. In particular, we try to help folks think through backup plans and suggest talking with a career center as part of the conversation about how to seek positions in the digital humanities. We try to speak from our own experiences but also to recognize our own limitations as resources. We do not have all the answers, but we still might be able to help in some way.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Student support like this necessarily includes emotional labor. For us (the authors), this has proven unavoidable. In conversations we try to emphasize that the student is smart enough and good enough for this work, that the job market is not a reflection on them, and that our current jobs are the results of luck in a lottery system (where every time you win a lottery it makes winning future lotteries a bit more tipped in your favor…). The fact that we have jobs does not necessarily mean our advice will be helpful (CW for war: see e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Survivorship_bias#In_the_military&quot;&gt;Abraham Wald on survivorship bias&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;). In short, it is not enough to tell students that they need do X and Y in order to be successful. In the Lab we believe these conversations need to engage with the messy work of what the job search entails.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Advice about any job market should come with a frank discussion about all the factors involved in being offered a job (i.e. how many factors are out of candidates’ hands), and about the precarious nature of employment in the field that the particular position may or may not play into.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re not sure how we share our cover letters given this context, but it still seems worth doing; we’re going to continue advising the local students who work with us, and we’d like to help students who are elsewhere if we can. Some of the ways we try to make our advising do more good than harm include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thinking about intent vs. impact: job advice is often “well meaning”, but what matters is the environment it builds up or dismantles, who it tells is worthwhile as they already are vs. who it tells to change, who it empowers with information. Consider whether telling a student that &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; don’t judge them for XYZ, but that interviewers will, has the same impact as you judging them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not posting job ads to the SLab Slack fellows channels (where they might be regular, unwanted reminders of job market stress to folks who aren’t even looking for work right now, or otherwise want to limit when they’re thinking about jobs). We’ve moved to including a list of interesting jobs to the end of our lab newsletter instead, where students can regularly choose to look at them if they choose.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moving to a public newsletter as a means of distributing these posts means that students can opt in without self-declaring themselves as on the job market, which allows for greater transparency about the process. It becomes less about knowing who you have to ask - anyone (even non-UVA people) can get access to that newsletter if they choose.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focusing our commentary not on “what others will expect” or “the right way to do things” (e.g. how to write the salutation), but instead on examples of how to best communicate one’s personal strengths via cover letter. In this way, we hope to keep the focus on the individual person and how they can take ownership of their own background rather than on how to please an anonymous committee (this can be a moving target).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leavening advice with affirmation of students as scholars and humans; helping them think about how to do what they value in life, even if they can’t do that as their main job. In short, academia has a way of encouraging people to think about their academic work and academic “merit” as deep reflections of their “worth” as a person. We try to reaffirm the fact that every person is worthwhile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thoughts-on-some-specific-dh-cover-letters&quot;&gt;Thoughts on some specific DH cover letters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below, each of us shares the text of one of our cover letters for the other to annotate. The comments below reflect what we’ve tried to do when we have served on hiring committees and reviewed cover letters: avoid the stuff we feel we &lt;em&gt;shouldn’t&lt;/em&gt; evaluate on, and what we &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; look for. Of course, these should be taken with a grain of salt. Our hope is that sharing the letters in this format will offer a bit more insight into how we think about DH job searches. It’s also worth noting that we each clearly read for different things. Similarly, other people serving on DH hiring committees might look for different things. We’ll focus on the hiring experience for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brandon’s current role: Head of Student Programs at the University of Virginia Library’s Scholars’ Lab&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Amanda’s previous role: tenure-track assistant professor and DH specialist at Purdue University Libraries&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While our comments below are about our cover letters, you might be interested in checking out other hiring and school info we’ve shared: Brandon’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/in-out-across-with-collaborative-education-and-digital-humanities-job-talk-for-head-of-graduate-programs/&quot;&gt;job talk&lt;/a&gt; for his current role, Amanda’s job talks for &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/disrupt-the-humanities-managing-director-job-talk/&quot;&gt;her current role&lt;/a&gt; (with links to job talks shared by three other scholars as well!) and &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/02/28/DHjobtalk&quot;&gt;her previous faculty role&lt;/a&gt;; and Amanda’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/06/20/digital-humanities-dissertation-defense-talk&quot;&gt;doctoral defense talk&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/06/14/digital-humanities-dissertation-defense-advice&quot;&gt;advice about defense talks&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2012/11/27/info-dump-humanities-doctoral-candidacy-exams-advice/&quot;&gt;literature/DH PhD exams list and advice&lt;/a&gt;. We’ve added the cover letters to &lt;a href=&quot;https://academicjobmarketsupportnetwork.hcommons.org/&quot;&gt;an existing effort&lt;/a&gt; to gather and contextualize job materials led by Hannah Alpert-Abrams on &lt;em&gt;Humanities Commons&lt;/em&gt;—check out their &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/groups/academic-job-market-support-network/documents/&quot;&gt;files page&lt;/a&gt; for other cover letters, various types of written statement, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started working at SLab on the same day and were not involved in the hiring of each other, so all comments are views from outside the search committee. You can check out the full cover letters on &lt;em&gt;Humanities Commons&lt;/em&gt;, and reading them in full first might be useful: &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/?get_group_doc=1003473/1570202258-HeadofGraduateProgramsCoverLetter.docx&quot;&gt;Brandon’s cover letter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/?get_group_doc=1003473/1570038081-CoverLetter.pdf&quot;&gt;Amanda’s cover letter&lt;/a&gt;. You might wish to compare these to how the job ads described these roles: &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/are-you-our-next-head-of-graduate-programs/&quot;&gt;Head of Graduate Programs&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/assets/DigitalHumanitiesSpecialist.pdf&quot;&gt;Digital Humanities Specialist Assistant or Associate Professor&lt;/a&gt;. In what follows, we intersperse inset text of our letters with short, bulleted lists of comments from the other person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;brandons-cover-letter&quot;&gt;Brandon’s cover letter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/?get_group_doc=1003473/1570202258-HeadofGraduateProgramsCoverLetter.docx&quot;&gt;Brandon’s cover letter&lt;/a&gt;, notes by Amanda&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I am writing to apply for the position of Head of Graduate Programs in the Scholars’ Lab at the University of Virginia. As an alumnus of both the Praxis Program and the Graduate Fellowship in Digital Humanities, I have a deep appreciation for the Scholars’ Lab’s commitment to experimental forms of collaborative, project-based pedagogy.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you have past experience or knowledge of what the place does, share that! You don’t have to have worked/learned at the place (as Brandon did at UVA) to speak to what specifically draws you there. E.g. maybe you’ve gotten a sense from their social media, a project or conference talk, or a blog post about what’s important to how the place works?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brandon shows awareness and mutual commitment to some of the lab’s values here; he shares this in a way that lets the search committee learn something about &lt;em&gt;him&lt;/em&gt; (that he digs experimentation, collaboration), rather than something more abstract like “I would be honored to work at such a great place” that doesn’t give the committee info but does take up some of your limited space.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most of the cover letters I’ve seen use the first paragraph to deliver information that isn’t really new—&lt;em&gt;this is my name, I’m not confused what position I’m applying for, I think I would be a good fit&lt;/em&gt;—so I like how he leads with a framing that &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; tell us more about him as a candidate.
    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I believe that my own extensive teaching record and my experiences as a digital humanities developer and project manager, all of which are shaped by my understanding of the Scholars’ Lab’s values, make me uniquely qualified for this position.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There’s limited space to tell the search committee about yourself, so rather than make his cover letter repeat his CV, Brandon connects up items in his past that could help him successfully fill this role’s goals. Rather than using himself as a reference (e.g. “I am very good at x” or “I am xyz adjectives”), Brandon points out that the past roles listed on his CV are connected as different approaches in DH, suggesting he’s both learned skills from being in a variety of different roles, and can probably work in an informed way with colleagues in those roles.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He again recognizes specifics about the lab—that through our staff charter, choices, etc. we try to be attentive to how our values shape our work. Some institutions make learning about how they do work difficult, unfortunately.
    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Student mentoring has been my first priority for the duration of my career.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brandon shares who he is as a professional and community member: articulating what matters to him, showing he understands what matters to this job, and going on to explicitly demonstrate how the two overlap.
    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I have taught a number of digital humanities workshops and classes, but I am proudest of my recent work as co-administrator of the Undergraduate Digital Humanities Fellows program at Washington and Lee University, where I currently serve as Mellon Digital Humanities Fellow. This initiative attempts to adapt the principles of the Praxis Program to a liberal arts context by allowing undergraduates to engage in collaborative research projects of their own design. I serve in both supervisory and technical roles in this program, and my daily tasks range from scoping student projects to teaching technical lessons on GitHub or programming concepts in PHP. During the past year, I have worked with humanities students to design and implement digital archives, editions, and storytelling projects through a combination of hands-on training and mentoring.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first half of this sentence (“I have taught a number of digital humanities workshops and classes”) could mean anything from teaching two small workshops ever, to multiple courses designed and taught himself—when hiring, readers may assume the lowest possible situation that your statement might mean, unless shown otherwise via specifics. Brandon helps us not need to guess—he doesn’t rehash his whole list of DHy skills here, but mentions a few in context in a way that suggests familiarity with other DH practices as well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Specific examples, including names of methods, tech, approaches showing familiarity. A good way to demonstrate knowledge of an area is to describe what daily work practices look like—specific tools or methods, what your involvement in a project specifically looked like.
    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I recognize that the vitality of a program depends upon a student community that extends beyond the bounds of the fellowship years, so I have created an outreach plan that builds our student network by having fellows visit other courses and mentor others as digital experts.
This student community can – and should – contribute to life beyond the walls of the academy: this year I am piloting a program that sends our fellows to a local High School AP Computer Science class to collaborate on digital projects. Drawing on the lessons I learned during my own training, my efforts always aim to teach the person not the material. Helping students to find the confidence to speak, act, and sometimes fail productively in public in roles like these is as important to me as any temporary success afforded by a project.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brandon states some of his values and goals, then immediately identifies how he acted on these. This both backs up claimed values in his letter, and demonstrates experience reflecting on and iterating one’s practices to bring them into line with what you identify as important.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There’s use in defining commonplace terms. Everyone knows what “teaching” means, right? But is this someone who cares about “filling young minds” and also mocks their current students on social media, vs. someone who sees students as colleagues, fellow scholars, humans? Brandon’s approach in this paragraph helps the reader see if we’re actually talking about the same thing when we say “teaching” (same for “research”, “scholarship”, “service”, etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;As a member of Washington and Lee’s digital humanities faculty committee, I have helped to develop the school’s digital humanities curriculum, which aims to provide students at all levels of expertise with an intellectual and practical understanding of innovative digital work. In particular, I have focused on collaborations that raise the skillsets of my colleagues as long-term investments in growing our resources. Working with Professor Sarah Horowitz and a student researcher on her interest in text analysis, for example, has led to both a co-taught class on digital history as well as a co-authored open access textbook.

The book is, foremost, a pedagogical exploration, an attempt to write an accessible introduction to digital text analysis for complete newcomers. The writing of this textbook was also, in itself, a teaching exercise: the writing process required Professor Horowitz to learn version control and Markdown in addition to a number of text analysis techniques. These experiences were part of a larger experiment that I spearheaded in collaborative writing and publishing that has led to invitations for presentations and workshops at DLF and Bucknell Digital Scholarship with our Digital Humanities Librarian.

As an experienced project manager and digital humanities developer, I also offer an advanced skillset to augment my teaching.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brandon shows how he invests in people around him, making the place he works better for colleagues in different roles (here: student, staff, faculty).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When applying for a staff job from a doctoral and/or faculty background, it can be useful to demonstrate how those experiences don’t disadvantage you—i.e.  you don’t understand what the staff position will be like. Brandon manages to both show the skills he learned from his past work experiences, while also aiming them at the kinds of work he’d be doing if hired.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brandon notes skills that might not be in the job ad, but are critical: collaboration, managing projects, a broad understanding of tech.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I served for several years as the project manager of NINES, and I have given invited talks on project development at the University of Michigan, SUNY New Paltz, the University of Central Florida, and the Center for Networked Information. I have consistently worked to supplement this supervisory experience with the skills necessary to implement projects myself. During my time at Washington and Lee, I have deployed and maintained three Rails applications, supervised Omeka customizations, and designed text analyses in Python, in addition to carrying out my own research in machine learning and sound studies. These skills will allow me not only to lead workshops on the technical aspects of digital humanities research, but also to supplement the resources of the Scholars’ Lab by providing technical support to fellows myself.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s very good to share things you’re proud of! If you don’t highlight these, your search committee might never know about them. If you have trouble doing this, you might have friends or a supportive teacher who can help you remember experiences or decisions worth sharing here. Julia Evans has a good &lt;a href=&quot;https://jvns.ca/blog/brag-documents/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; about how to get comfortable talking about your strengths.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brandon does a good job pitching his achievements for this staff role—sharing the things faculty hiring committees value, like invited talks, but coupling those with tech skills and his broader learning from those experiences. He comes across as someone who wants to be in a staff job that’s heavy on mentoring, collaborating, experimenting, rather than someone treating this job as an alternative to another career goal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I know first-hand how transformative the right interventions can be in the lives of graduate students. The Scholars’ Lab’s commitment to equipping students at all levels for both the kinds of careers that they will find and the intellectual provocations they can make in the digital age has shaped my own thinking, and it continues to inform all of my work. I see this position in the Scholars’ Lab as the perfect opportunity for me to help others learn as I once did, and to use my skills and experiences to extend the excellent work of the Scholars’ Lab’s fellowship programs.

I look forward to discussing the great potential of the position with you.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I like the wording in the final sentence—”great potential” reminds me that I’ve gotten a sense from this letter that this is someone who’s thought hard about the strategy and tactics of student-focused DH, who is ready to do good in this role.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;amandas-cover-letter&quot;&gt;Amanda’s cover letter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/?get_group_doc=1003473/1570038081-CoverLetter.pdf&quot;&gt;Amanda’s cover letter&lt;/a&gt;, notes by Brandon&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Dear Purdue University Libraries team,

I'm a digital humanist with an Information M.S. (University of Michigan), new Literature Ph.D. (University of Maryland), and over eight years as a professional DH web developer and public-focused DH scholar, working since 2009 in multiple staff roles at the Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities (MITH). I write to apply for the Digital Humanities Specialist role.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first thing I notice is how Amanda structured her letter differently than how I typically do so. I tend to treat cover letters like essays, where the structure of the thing to come will be laid out in the final sentence of the first paragraph. Amanda leads with her experience here, which is likely to make sure her cover letter gets past an initial quick read.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s perhaps also worth noting how wild and varied the paths often are for digital humanists. In this field maybe more than others it is not uncommon to tie together many seemingly disconnected life experiences into a narrative about yourself. The connections between library degrees, and PhD in English, and positions at a DH center all speak to each other in clear ways. But I can easily imagine a need to pull together a variety of different experiences that might not parse so easily for people. This seems fine to me. More on diverse life experiences below!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Another thing that stands out here is that Amanda does not just point out what she has done - she points out different experiences from very different contexts. Research experience as a graduate student, library experience, and hands-on experiences. It’s helpful to think in these terms when presenting yourself to a search committee. It’s not just about the work you’ve done. It’s also about the kinds of contexts and audiences to which this work exposes you.
    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;As an example of my work, my recent dissertation project is InfiniteUlysses.com—an interface that brings scholars, teachers, and readers of all backgrounds together in annotating and discussing a challenging book, personalizing the annotations displayed to any given reader by their backgrounds, interests, and needs. Infinite Ulysses achieved sizable impact for a literature dissertation, with over 13,000 unique visitors during its first month of open beta. The challenge of helping everyone feel empowered to participate in the humanities drives my research and project design.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To underscore what Amanda says above - I usually tell people to make sure their letter is not an extension of their CV. When addressing things that appear in both, I usually try to make sure the things in the letter expand or provide context that you might not otherwise get in a CV. This text is great, because she expands on a project that might otherwise only get a line and not have the same impact.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I also like how she takes the work and expands upon it to describe what she learned from it. That sort of self-reflection is something I usually look for in cover letters and try to represent in my own.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Amanda’s accomplishments here and as articulated in the letter are impressive, but I often think it’s a matter of selling yourself regardless of whether or not you have done a lot, whether or not your blog has thousands of hits. Take the things you have done and use them as an opportunity to spin a story about yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Successfully completing a non-monograph dissertation taught me how to champion others embarking on digital scholarship, both in educating their colleagues on their digital work, and in the practical aspects of project design, technical learning, and planning for the full life cycle of the project. I dealt with this last—DH long-term thinking and digital preservation—as MITH's Webmaster, auditing our two servers full of projects, files, and databases ranging back to 1999, and in my training and experience doing digital preservation work with MITH's early e-lit collection.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Another thing I often look for - the letter is a space to offer reflections on your experience. I like that Amanda takes the experience with the dissertation and goes a step further to show what it means in the broader narrative of how she approaches people and her work. In other words - it answers the “so what?” question. These moments of reflection can also be a chance to connect yourself to the values of the institution and position for which you are applying.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As a student, it can often feel like you have no experience. But you do! It’s just a matter of taking those experiences you do have and extrapolating to how they would apply to other circumstances. So in this case, Amanda does a great job of showing how working as a dissertation and webmaster apply to other circumstances and to the position for which she’s applying. I often tell students to think of it like roleplaying. If you were in the position, what experiences have you had that you could imagine helping you? Write about them. Sometimes trying to imagine yourself doing the work can help you think further about how to present yourself for the application.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lastly I would note that it’s important to consider the practical skills you gain from doing digital work as distinct from the research aspects of that work. To be sure, they’re both tightly joined in practice. But it’s all too easy to get to the end of a digital project on Victorian archives and think, “this has given me experience with Victorian research and digital archives.” But there is also a whole range of other “soft skills” that such work gives you experience in - project management, software development, project promotion, etc. These are all things you can have experience in and they are also things you can discuss critically! Reflections on these parts of the process are often of immense use to other scholar practitioners. Think of them as experiences but also as potential objects of scholarly inquiry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;My work has always been interdisciplinary in both topic and methodology. A few of my diverse past DH projects include:

* Co-organizing the first digital humanities and games unconference (THATCamp Games)  
* Developer on the &quot;Making DH More Open&quot; team's Braille Wordpress plugin  
* Data visualization and topic modeling of Digital Humanities Quarterly to explore DH citation networks (recipient of the inaugural ACH Microgrant)  
* Team teaching and design of a DH course for UMD's Digital Cultures and Creativity undergrads  
* Librarian-aimed user testing and documentation for BitCurator's archival digital forensics tools  

I offer excellent communication, teaching, and presentation skills, and am especially deft at research use of social media (over 2,000 Twitter followers) and blogging (over 22,000 unique blog visitors to date). I’ve worked in a number of pertinent roles: as a librarian and digital archivist, university teacher and student, web developer, and DH center staff, as well as alongside others in these roles. This background gives me inside experience of the different needs and values of these important scholarly constituents. After working on interdisciplinary teams for six years at one of the world's top digital humanities research centers, I'm a skilled translator between tech and non-tech colleagues, and my research best thrives through collaboration.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I think the reference to social media work here is useful. When I was hired at the Lab, they specifically cited my blogging and presence on Twitter as assets. You might not think about that kind of public outreach as tangible work, but it is! It’s often helpful to think about the value you bring to the institution beyond your research and teaching. This framing can be especially useful for positions beyond the tenure track in libraries or otherwise.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One thing I notice about Amanda’s letter is that it really speaks to the diverse experiences she had when she applied to the position. That’s great! In academia I think we are sometimes challenged to think of ourselves as this coherent narrative where all roads lead to a single path. But, in practice, we have all sorts of experiences. And that broad background can be part of your narrative. We don’t all fit into neat boxes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I'd love to discuss how my background in digital humanities service, training, research, and building would complement the Purdue University Libraries' learner-centered mission! Thank you for your time and consideration.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Small point, but it’s often quite clear when a single cover letter has been sent out to multiple institutions with the name of one simply subbed for another. There are small ways to flag that you actually are applying for this &lt;em&gt;specific position at this specific place&lt;/em&gt;, and this is an example of them. That’s to say, I like that Amanda doesn’t just say she is a good fit, she connects her experience to the mission of the institution in this last moment. It can be difficult to figure out what that mission is (in the Scholars’ Lab we have an explicit statement about &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.org/charter&quot;&gt;our values&lt;/a&gt;), but you could get clues from events, projects, research, and similar initiatives undertaken by the institution. If they’re committing time and energy to it, they care about it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In terms of thinking about how to find out the character of an institution, specific events or projects can help. But there are often large, general questions you could ask about a place that could help you think about their mission. Is it a small liberal arts college or an R1 institution? Is this a DH center you would be hired into or a single position apart from a larger network of support? Is the position part of a library? Is the position hired for a particular grant or is it sourced on hard money? Are we talking about an institution of teaching? higher education? cultural heritage? What sort of audience / public does the institution tend to cater to? There are a number of large buckets like these that institutions tend to fall into. While each organization is unique, thinking about large categories like these can help provide clues to what this particular one is about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;endnotes&quot;&gt;Endnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The coiner of the word “meritocracy” intended it to ridicule the very ideas folks now use the term to convey. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I remember seeing a tweet recently where someone connected the infamous image of the bullet hole locations on the surviving planes to listening to some kind of job advice selectively—maybe listening to folks who got hired about what not to ask during interviews? If you know who tweeted this and wouldn’t mind, please let me know so I can cite them (@literature_geek on Twitter/visconti@virginia.edu). It’s important to record where ideas came from, even in smaller things like this post. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Brandon’s title has been expanded over the course of his work here; at the time of hiring, it was “Head of Graduate Programs”. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We thought this be more broadly useful to students than the cover letter for her current job, as that fits leaving a faculty role to direct a lab, rather than locating one’s first post-PhD job. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Getting from Here to There</title>
   <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/getting-from-here-to-there/"/>
   <updated>2019-09-19T11:31:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/getting-from-here-to-there</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Crossposted to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/getting-from-here-to-there/&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I visited Emory University in conjunction with the launch of their &lt;a href=&quot;http://digitalscholarship.emory.edu/partner/learn/ddsp.html&quot;&gt;new graduate fellowship&lt;/a&gt; for students aiming to incorporate digital projects in their dissertations. This is the first of two posts sharing materials from the two events I took part in while there. I was asked to give a workshop on project development for graduate students as well as an open talk on digital humanities pedagogy. The text of what follows pertains to the workshop for students, where I was asked to give a broad overview of how to approach project planning and some activities for helping them think through their work for the year. I essentially tried to condense the greatest hits of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/&quot;&gt;Praxis Program&lt;/a&gt; into 90 minutes. I was asked to give a 30 minute talk and 60 minute workshop, but I’ll get into how we shifted things around below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, a few caveats. For one, I write a talk for situations like these, but I try to avoid straight-up reading the text (&lt;a href=&quot;http://walshbr.com/blog/dh-public-speaking/&quot;&gt;more info on how I approach public speaking in DH available here&lt;/a&gt;). So what you’ll see below is more like a roadmap of the general gist of what we talked about. I don’t remember consulting the text too much in the moment, and I know for a fact that the last few paragraphs were dramatically different in person. Second, and related - since this was meant to be a workshop and not a lecture I planned on a fair amount of discussion with the really thoughtful and engaged students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this is to say that I planned on deviating from my plan, and I tried to represent that below. In the text that follows you’ll find the actual running text of a talk and workshop plan along with notes to you, the reader, marked with [sidebar: brackets] describing how I modified things in the moment to adapt to the group and the conversation as it unfolded. You’ll get a mix of both the script for the presentation and some notes on how I managed things as it diverted from expectations. It might get a little confusing, but I imagine it could be interesting to see how things got restructured and shifted around in the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning for a span of time as long as 90 minutes is difficult, so I deliberately planned far more than I could cover in the allotted time just in case. I went into it knowing I’d need to be flexible. If I had to offer any suggestions for workshops in general it would be this - plan more than you need but do not try to rush to make it through your material. Let the conversation and the discussion shape the pace of your teaching, not a need to cover a particular amount of content. I always find it more helpful to do more with less. In this case, it meant that I was watching the clock from the beginning and looking for milestones along the way where, if needed, I could wrap things up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Sidebar: we’re in talk land now. What follows is the rough script of the talk and discussion that Anandi Silva Knuppel, Sarah McKee, and I fielded together.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-from-here-to-there&quot;&gt;Getting from Here to There&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Title slide&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hey friends! How is it going? I’m Brandon Walsh, the Head of Student Programs in the Scholars’ Lab in the UVA Library. The Scholars’ Lab is a center for experimental scholarship informed by digital humanities, spatial technologies, and cultural heritage thinking. For the purposes of our conversation today, my work with students is probably most relevant. I facilitate a number of different fellowship programs and student opportunities in the lab, where I’m in charge of everything from mundane administrative tasks to more abstract things like constructing our pedagogical mission. And I collaborate with a range of people in the Lab and the Library to carry out different kinds of teaching for our community. I work with students from a range of disciplines, which means I have a fair amount of experience helping people plan, scope, and execute projects. I’ve titled this workshop “Getting from Here to There.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Slide of my cat&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[First sidebar: Anandi Silva Knuppel was the one who invited me to speak at Emory, and she gave a general orientation to their fellowship program before I started my piece. She included several photos of her children and family in the talk, and I quickly realized that the tone of my section would feel like a weird shift from hers. So, while she was presenting, I threw in a bunch of photos of the cat my partner and I recently adopted. This is Pepper, and he makes numerous appearances in what follows.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Thanks slide&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we get started, I wanted to offer some resources and gratitude. If you need the text or slides of this talk for any reason, you can find them at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/Emory-Talks&quot;&gt;first link&lt;/a&gt; here. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zotero.org/bmw9t/items/collectionKey/UVA6I35D&quot;&gt;second link&lt;/a&gt; will take you to a Zotero collection for this talk, so you don’t necessarily need to rapidly write down the links to things as we’re going. I’ve collected them for you. I wanted to credit my colleagues at the Scholars’ Lab, whose work I’ll discuss in what follows. Amanda Visconti, Ronda Grizzle, Jeremy Boggs, Laura Miller, and Shane Lin especially show up in the following slides. And, finally, I wanted to thank Sarah McKee, Lisa Flowers, Anandi Silva Knuppel, and everyone at ECDS and the Fox Center for the Humanities for the invitation to talk here. I’m truly flattered and grateful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Plan for proceeding&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of what we’ll cover today, I’m planning on taking you through a series of questions related to DH project planning roughly organized around questions pertaining to the how, what, who, and why of digital projects. This is my roadmap through the topic, and I’m happy to just lecture at you. But it’d be great to have questions and discussion as relevant and necessary. So please do interrupt. The conversation will be better for your contributions and better for your ideas. Ultimately this is about making it useful for you. So tell me what you need, and I’m happy to go where you want. I won’t necessarily have all the answers, but I’m happy to talk together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Sidebar: I had planned on running some icebreakers to get to know the students and their work, but Sarah and Anandi actually did this during their opening orientation for the program. So the slide I had planned on getting to know each other became wholly irrelevant. Instead, I realized that I should share a little bit about my own background as it pertained to the topic at hand. So during Anandi’s orientation I inserted a couple slides about the Lab and myself.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Who am I?&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’ve learned a little about you, but &lt;a href=&quot;http://youtube.com/watch?v=izuD30Cp5Ao&quot;&gt;who am I&lt;/a&gt;? I work in digital humanities now, but I didn’t actually start doing anything with DH until I was a graduate student myself. I didn’t even know of it as a term until I became interested in the fellowships that my friends were doing in the Scholars’ Lab. It took a few years of finding my feet, but the digital project I worked on for my dissertation had to with &lt;a href=&quot;http://walshbr.com/blog/woolf-huskey/&quot;&gt;Virginia Woolf and machine learning&lt;/a&gt;, and it was a project that taught me a lot about myself, my work, and what I wanted out of life. So believe me when I say that you are all far more advanced than I was at the same point in my career. You’re doing great! And you are well prepared for the projects you’re working on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Sidebar: During Anandi’s orientation, one of the fellows asked a question about how their own program at Emory compared to the larger landscape of digital humanities graduate programs. Was it unique? How did it compare to other fellowships? So I called another audible and inserted the following slide about the Scholars’ Lab programs so that the students could get context for how things might be structured differently. It’s different aesthetically because, well, it’s from a different talk! I copied and pasted it in quickly from the talk I’d be giving at Emory later that evening.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Scholar's Lab Programs&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on your question about other graduate programs in DH, I thought it might be worth pausing for just a moment to share what our students do with us in the Scholars’ Lab. At the Lab, we have two year-long fellowship programs. The Praxis Program is something of a soup to nuts introduction to digital humanities for students early in their graduate career. These students typically come in without much experience in digital technologies, but the goal for us over the course of a year is to get them in a position for them to launch their own collaborative digital project. The second fellowship listed here is our year-long Graduate Fellowship in Digital Humanities, a program for people with more experience and who are working to tie DH to their dissertation projects in some way. These students work with a point of contact on our R&amp;amp;D team for the year to develop their project, and students in both programs give public presentations by the end of the year. If you’re interested in learning more, I’m happy to talk at greater length about our individual programs. &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis-network.org/&quot;&gt;The Praxis Network&lt;/a&gt; might also be a useful resource - it’s a website that archives snapshots of several like-minded programs at one point in time, so on that project you get glimpses at several different approaches to graduate education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/7.png&quot; alt=&quot;Man standing in hallway&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s get started. I titled this talk “Getting from here to there” because, to me, that’s the most difficult thing about planning any project. And this is particularly true for a student digital humanities project. I like this image because the alt text for it, the text meant to describe its contents for accessibility purposes, is “man standing in hallway.” It showed up when I did a search on Unsplash for “future.” I don’t know about you, but I have a hard time seeing a person in that photo. And when you’re starting out with any kind of digital project that’s part of the challenge. How do you get from point A to point B? How do you get your project from here to there? And how do you place yourself within it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/8.png&quot; alt=&quot;Baby on steps&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’m just trying to show you snazzy images, but starting a digital project often puts me in this position. I feel like I’m learning to walk for the first time, and each step seems insurmountable. Each step brings new anxieties, and I’d like to know more about yours. I learned a little about your work, but I’d like to know a little more about your questions. What is the single biggest question you have right now about getting started? What is your single biggest anxiety about the year to come?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Sidebar: I had budgeted a little time to have the students discuss concerns, but we wound up talking for longer than I anticipated (it turns out I really wanted to help them work through things). At this point, because we had started the workshop a tad late after lunch, I was already becoming aware that we were going to run out of time. We were only about 15 minutes into the 90-minute session, but I had already changed my sense of the timeline for the talk. The questions the students asked were very good. So good, that it seemed as though they were plants. They talked broadly about concerns that they might not have meaningful contributions to make to the field more broadly at this stage in their work, anxieties about finding their way into the DH community, questions about professionalization, and more. Sarah and I fielded them together. The questions worked well as a transition, because I correctly anticipated that some of them would feel like imposters.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those are all excellent questions. And part of the message I want you to take away today is that questions like that are all normal. &lt;em&gt;It is normal not to know the answers&lt;/em&gt;. Behind all of your questions I heard implied another, particular anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/9.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pepper studying&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Sidebar: insert joke about Pepper looking stressed while working.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/10.png&quot; alt=&quot;Imposter syndrome&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behind your concerns, really at their core, I heard questions about imposterdom. When am I going to be exposed for the fraud that I am? I have no idea what I’m doing – when am I going to be found out? I am here to tell you today that almost everyone feels this way. And if you don’t – you’re a Dunning-Kruger, as this chart explains. This feeling – imposter syndrome – is something we live with all through our lives. I’m feeling it right now! And I think it shows that you’re a good, thoughtful, reflective, well-meaning person. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gamasutra.com/blogs/TanyaXShort/20140716/220938/Overcoming_Impostors_Syndrome.php&quot;&gt;This article&lt;/a&gt; by Tanya X. Short has some excellent strategies for working through your feelings of imposterdom. I recommend it. But I also recommend you take a deep breath, close your eyes, and recognize that you belong here. You can do this project, and you have a community of people here to help you. I’m also happy to help in any way I can if you want to reach out after this event. But more practically, there are some helpful resources and methods I can share with you for how you can get started. Because one way you can address imposter syndrome is by doing what you always do as academics. Do research. Prepare. Use the resources available to you. The process for digital work does have key differences that I can help you think through. But it is not so wholly alien and different as it might seem at first glance. I have a series of questions that I usually talk through with newcomers to digital projects as they’re thinking for the first time about this kind of work, and I’ll be giving you a version of that conversation today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reminder: interrupt me at any time. To begin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/11.png&quot; alt=&quot;How will you go about your work?&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How will you go about your work? On a day-to-day basis, what is the process by which you will carry out your work? You might be getting to the point where you have good,  personal project management styles that work for you as you’re writing your dissertation. If you don’t, now is a good time to develop them. But it can always be helpful to hear about other strategies. Know thyself in the first instance – find what works for you and stick to it. But don’t be afraid to try out something new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/12.png&quot; alt=&quot;Trello Dashboard&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who here has heard of Trello? We don’t explicitly use this tool in the Scholars’ Lab as a whole staff, but we use it on the technical board for one of the journals I’m involved with – the Journal of Interactive Technology and Pedagogy. It’s pretty simple - the idea is that each task gets a card associated with it that you can comment on and move around. Nothing too earth shattering here, but these task management systems become increasingly important as your projects grow in complexity and as you begin to work with collaborators. They’re especially good for humanities projects, in particular, because we’re not used to thinking in terms like this. How do you take a complicated humanities problem and break it into smaller, completable steps? Doing this with technical work can help keep you from burning out and help you feel that you’re moving forward. It can make the whole process of getting from here to there feel doable. You’ll likely be bad at it at first and have trouble with task managing. That’s OK! It’s a skill you can develop like anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/13.png&quot; alt=&quot;Agile Project Development&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever talked to anyone else about the way that they work, you’ve probably realized that everyone takes on projects in different ways. Even writing. When I was writing my dissertation, I would use the “add comment” feature in Microsoft Word to leave myself tasks on the document itself. Any page would have hundreds of comments that I would sort through when I sat down to write and was looking for where to begin for the day. I would be shocked if anyone else used this weird, idiosyncratic system of mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digital work is no different - we all have different ways of going about it. But it’s helpful to get everyone working from the same book if not exactly on the same page. In a corporate context, it can save time, money, and energy if your team has a shared philosophy towards your workflow and project management. This can be true of humanities and DH work as well. In the Scholars’ Lab, we use an approach to project management called Agile Development. The basics of it are before you in this diagram. The general idea is that you work in two-week sprints (at least in the way that I implement it with our students). At the end of each sprint you reflect on where you’re at, what you need help with, and what you need for next steps. A scrum is a term taken from rugby, and it is a set of tools and methodologies for conducting these of check-ins, whether they happen daily or at the end of your sprints. In our staff scrums, for example, we go around the room and ask for two-minute updates (max) describing what you are currently working on, what is next for you, and what you are not working on. But for your purposes here today, you can just think of it as a two-week sprint followed by a meeting to touch base. And then you repeat. We do this with our fellows, who have biweekly scrums with their R&amp;amp;D points of contact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That explains the center of the diagram. The left side of it refers, I believe, to the idea that you should break your larger project down into smaller tasks that you can accomplish in two-week sprints. That way you have a good sense of progress. In a student project situation, this might be as simple as “I’m going to work through this chapter from this programming book and come to you with the progress I’ve made and the questions I have.” And if a task can’t be accomplished in two weeks it’s probably actually several smaller tasks lumped into one. Break your tasks down until you find something you can do in that window of time. One last thing here – notice the emphasis on circular shapes and the word “potentially.” One of the core concepts of agile development is the idea that iteration is good. It actually saves you time, energy, and, in the corporate world, money to produce something early that might be half baked and get feedback on it. This allows you to learn from your mistakes and iterate on your materials. It requires a certain amount of humility to work like this, and it’s radically different from what we’re used to in academia. Produce something for other eyes? &lt;em&gt;Before it’s perfect?&lt;/em&gt; Perish the thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/14.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cult of Done Manifesto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But truly – I’m here to tell you that perfectionism, while often encouraged in academia, can be a significant barrier to getting things done (and hint – also a cause of imposter syndrome). The &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@bre/the-cult-of-done-manifesto-724ca1c2ff13&quot;&gt;Cult of Done Manifesto&lt;/a&gt; is a document I adore that gets at this point. “Accept that everything is a draft,” it reads. Your project is a draft. You’re a draft! It helps to think about ourselves as works in progress. The Cult of Done Manifesto isn’t a text that necessarily comes from the agile community per se, but they have overlapping concerns. Iteration is a part of our practice. It’s how we learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s worth considering that not everyone is equally able to iterate or develop in public – women, people of color, and other marginalized communities have different experiences of the world and of digital life. And the internet, the public audience for much digital work, is toxic. But it’s worth at least thinking about how you can push yourself to rethink the practices with which you’re comfortable in spaces that allow you to do so. I’m not really talking about a binary, where, on the one hand, things are kept fully private until they are absolutely perfect and, on the other, you’re publishing every piece of half-finished work for all to see. Find what makes sense to you. Consider how you can take small steps that work for you in the direction of being more comfortable with your work in progress as something worth sharing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/15.png&quot; alt=&quot;Principles of Agile Development&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last note on agile. The agile community released a &lt;a href=&quot;https://agilemanifesto.org&quot;&gt;series of principles&lt;/a&gt; that are worth pausing over. I’ll read them. Individuals and interactions over processes and tools. Working software over comprehensive documentation. Customer collaboration over contract negotiation. Responding to change over following a plan. Keep in mind that these come from the software world. Let’s take a moment to think about them. What do you notice about them? How might these apply to your own work as a humanities student? As a DH student? What are they missing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Sidebar: At this point I paused for discussion and questions. My goal was to get the students to think about questions of communication, self-reflection, and iteration as they might pertain to their own work. The students had great thoughts and questions about how to apply agile thinking to digital projects and dissertations. One that stuck out to me - how could you apply these sorts of ideas to a project where you were, really, the sole person working on the project? I suggested in response that, first, you could project manage yourself in the same way you would a team and that, second, projects were almost always the product of many hands, even if they might appear to be the work of a solo individual. Think deeply about the help you might be overlooking and how you can better structure those relationships.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/16.png&quot; alt=&quot;Four principles for project planning&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lists of principles like this are often helpful, so here is my own spin on the conversation. If I had to offer four principles for DH project planning, I might offer these. Give yourself permission to keep it small. Work iteratively. Credit generously. Connect it to you. There could be many others, and I might give you a different list depending on the day of the week. But they’re a start. We’ll talk more about what some of these points mean shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/17.png&quot; alt=&quot;What will you do?&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything we’ve talked about so far could be filed under the question of how you’ll do your work. But, at this early stage, you’re probably also thinking about - obsessing about - the what. What exactly do I want to do with this project? One project management tip: this can be a dangerous question. For humanities students and faculty, it’s all too common to want your idea to go deeper, further, more complex. You’re trained to deconstruct and push ideas. This is great when writing a book or teaching a class. But in a digital project each of these potential ideas represents time and energy on your part. Digital projects aren’t developed at the speed of an idea or the speed of writing. They take time to implement. And each new idea takes more time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I want to suggest you think about a related question as enlivening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/18.png&quot; alt=&quot;What don't you want to do?&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of asking, “what do I want to do?” you might ask, “what don’t I want to do?” It’s a powerful question. But it is very, very hard to ask it of yourself. And it’s a question whose value only becomes clear with experience. You learn the value of it the hard way. Put another way - check out this image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/19.png&quot; alt=&quot;Feature creep&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feature creep refers to a tendency for projects to creep along, growing in size, way beyond their original intention. And at a certain point, like this tool here, a project becomes unwieldy and useless. You can’t even pick it up without stabbing yourself. We’ve all worked with tools or interfaces like this – so many options that you can’t do anything at all. When you continue to layer more and more ideas, more and more features, onto a project, things can quickly spin out of control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an especially difficult problem for students of digital humanities because they’re often coming to these questions for the first time. So you don’t know if an idea is a reasonable one or totally impossible. Spoiler alert - this a problem even among professionals. We’re all dealing with this all the time. So I wanted to give you a few ways to think about scoping out features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/20.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pepper reaction shot to feature creep. &quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Sidebar: I believe I made a joke here about Pepper’s reaction to feature creep.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/21.png&quot; alt=&quot;Two pi rule pt 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to share two quotes from a conversation we had about project scoping during my time as a student in the Scholars’ Lab. Apologies if I don’t get the exact wording right - this was a decade ago after all. Here is Wayne Graham, former Head of R&amp;amp;D in the Scholars’ Lab, discussing how he plans out work on a project. He takes any estimate his staff gives him and multiplies by pi, because things always take longer than anticipated, even for professionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, here is a quote from Bethany Nowviskie, former Head of the Scholars’ Lab and Wayne’s boss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/22.png&quot; alt=&quot;Two pi rule pt 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I take whatever estimate Wayne gives me and double it.” It was a conversation that really stuck with me. Multiply any estimate for how long a project or task will take by two pi. That’s a lot longer than expected!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How, then, can you decide what’s worth doing? In the face of these kinds of difficulties, it’s helpful to have some sort of a system in place for determining the value of what you’re thinking about doing. This is especially helpful in humanities work, where sometimes the features we’re talking about directly build upon our own ideas about things we care about. It can all feel very personal. It can be helpful to try to make things objective. Here’s one way to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/23.png&quot; alt=&quot;Scoping checklist&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a checklist for you as you go about your work. Is this feature hard? And is it important? These questions are difficult to answer when starting out, so it can be good to ask for help as you think through them. But it’s also a skill that you can develop with experience. So take the time to try to break your large project into as many components as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s practice together. Take the idea of a digital archive. That’s a big thing. But you could poke at a lot of pieces of it. Say…you were going to make an archive of American protest. What are some decisions you would have to make about it? What would some features be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/24.png&quot; alt=&quot;Design an archive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Sidebar: had we more time, at this point I would have paused to actually run the speculative exercise for designing a digital archive, something I’ve done in courses before. I was watching the clock, though, and felt I needed to just give a few conceptual takeaways before moving on. I asked the students to consider a range of different questions that would impact the features and scale of such an archive. Will the archive be private or public? Will it index everything about the topic from all countries in all years? Maybe just one year? Maybe just one country? All types of media? Maybe just text? Will people be able to add to it? If they can add to it, will you have to moderate their contributions? The answers to all of these questions will affect the scale of a project and the time it will take to implement.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You quickly begin to see that there are many different ways you can slice up a big idea. And any one of these decisions could potentially blow your project up and make it unwieldy. Start small, and, remember – a project that is all things for all people is probably nothing for no one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/25.png&quot; alt=&quot;Design an archive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That checklist I gave you before is actually a pretty common one, and this visualization probably seems like common sense. But I still think it’s powerful to see laid out like this. Take a moment to look at it. [Sidebar: pause for a moment] Where do you think you want to live? [Sidebar: the answer is top left] Where do you want to avoid? [Sidebar: the answer is bottom right.] And of course you will probably spend most of your time in the top right. Not too difficult to tell that because this visualization gives you helpful names for each category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sort of task-oriented thinking isn’t something we’re used to doing. But it’s helpful to think about your work this way. Even something as abstract as writing can benefit from this! In my own situation – I’m a full-time, 12-month, 40-hour staff person, but I still try to write, publish, and (as you can see) give talks. Trying to finish writing projects when you have the regular standing commitments of a job is difficult. I only have so many hours in the workweek. Methods like these help me to figure out how long I have to write, what I can accomplish, and what I can’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Sidebar: I want to give huge credit to Ronda Grizzle here for everything she does for the Lab related to project management. Everything I know about it I learned from her. Anandi also had wonderful thoughts on project management during this portion of the workshop, and she shared them with the students.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/26.png&quot; alt=&quot;Quote from Antoine de Saint-Exupery&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last quote on this that I want to leave you with. “Perfection is achieved not when there is nothing more to add, but when there is nothing left to take away.” Saying no is a super power. Truly. I’ve said in the Scholars’ Lab before that the best projects – the best features – are the ones you don’t implement. Because saying no to something in the short-term means that, in the long-term, you can say yes to something you really want to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/27.png&quot; alt=&quot;What support do you have?&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Sidebar: I set aside time here, again, for any questions or discussion that might come up.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next question is a big one for students. What kind of support do you have? It’s one thing to talk about the difficulties of project development in theory, but it’s another to come up against the actual realities of project development. You all have lives. You have programs you’re trying to do. This is hard. But the good news is that you’re not alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/28.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pepper being supported by my arm&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Sidebar: Pepper being supported, cats, etc. etc. It was also about this time that Sarah and I agreed we would not get to the follow-up activities I had planned. Instead, the new plan was to finish out the talk portion, discuss with the students, and describe the kinds of activities we would have done with more time so that they could follow up with them on their own later. This revised plan meant that I didn’t feel the need to rush through the material - I could instead allow the students space for discussion as they wished.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/29.png&quot; alt=&quot;MLA Committee on Information Technology&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one, I wanted to point you a &lt;a href=&quot;https://infotech.mla.hcommons.org/2018/digital-humanities-dissertation-starter-kit/&quot;&gt;blog post put out by the MLA Committee on Information Technology&lt;/a&gt; on how to begin thinking about putting together a digital dissertation. There are a number of good resources linked here that I would encourage you to check out. Guidelines for evaluating digital work. Models of work that has already been done. Any difficulties you might face from the standpoints of project development, of getting buy-in from your committee, or of dealing with the university have probably been faced by others before you. It is highly unlikely you are the first ones to have these issues. So look for evidence, help, support, and resources from the larger community. I’m happy to help you find things as well. Feel free to reach out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/30.png&quot; alt=&quot;Collaborators Bill of Rights&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also certain there are people locally – students, staff, librarians, and faculty – who are in your corner. Sarah has already told me about some of them, and you already mentioned others in your introductions. Accept their help - you don’t have to do this alone. But be careful you don’t take exploit their goodwill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I would encourage you to think of this work as an opportunity to start to develop a space more like what you would want the academy to be. This is an image of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.mith.umd.edu/offthetracks/recommendations/index.html&quot;&gt;Collaborators Bill of Rights&lt;/a&gt;. Digital work takes many hands. Consider that labor. Share generously. Credit liberally. Make sure that everyone all the way down is acknowledged in your project, in as many places as you can. Consider how you can make these people your true collaborators if they are up for it – ask them how they want to be cited. If their voice and work are important to you and your project, ask them if they want to co-present or co-author with you. These things might seem weird, trained as we are in the humanities to think of authorship as something done by sole individuals, but that doesn’t have to be the norm. And I can assure you that these conversations mean the world to people in libraries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This conversation is not just about projects. It’s about people. And you can use this space to begin to help shape a more expansive, generous, and humane way of doing digital work. In the Scholars’ Lab, for example, we push for real collaborations. We do work with – not for – as much as we can. So begin to think about how your project, in some small way, can begin to flatten the hierarchies at work in the academy. If you were interested in a related document about rights you should expect of collaborations as a student, I’d also point you to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://humtech.ucla.edu/news/a-student-collaborators-bill-of-rights/&quot;&gt;Student Collaborators Bill of Rights&lt;/a&gt; from UCLA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Sidebar: I paused again for questions.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/31.png&quot; alt=&quot;Praxis charters&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One tool we use in the Scholars’ Lab to help structure relationships in positive, ethical ways is called a charter. The charter is the last concept that I wanted to introduce to you all. It’s a pretty simple idea – a charter is a document that reflects your shared values and principles. What you expect of each other, how you’re going to work together. What you hope to get out of the thing. Think of it like a personal and collective mission statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A charter is something that a group can return to later when questions come up. Articulating values like this can be really useful because when the rubber hits the road you can ask of any new feature, project, or idea - does this connect with the things I care about? Is it advancing our mission, or at least our mission as we want to see it? In front of you is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/charter/charter-2011-2012/&quot;&gt;charter for our first Praxis cohort&lt;/a&gt;. We’ve had students on this collaborative fellowship put a charter together every year, and we have several for the lab as well – &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/charter/&quot;&gt;one for the lab in general&lt;/a&gt; and another for how we approach &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/student-programs-charter/&quot;&gt;student programs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason I end with the charter is that it connects to what I might offer as a last principle for project planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/32.png&quot; alt=&quot;Five principles for project planning - last line has to be filled in by you. &quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A project is only as good as it connects to you. But you have to decide what that connection looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We encourage our students to think about charters as an opportunity to articulate their project goals and &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; their goals for their own portion of the project. Their goals for themselves. What do they hope to gain? How do they hope to grow? What do they acknowledge as their own limitations? A project should, in some way, help you in your life. It’s going to get you to a place you want to be, be that professionally, spiritually, intellectually, or ethically. I thought of my dissertation as a story that I wanted to sit with and a story I wanted to tell for a few years. This is similar to how my colleague Jeremy Boggs describes digital archives and digital projects more generally. To him, projects tell stories. Put another way, how is your project going to help you tell yours? Or more specifically – what kind of person do you want to be? How can the telling of your project’s story help you to bring that person into reality? One answer might be as simple as “this content is important to me.” Another could be “I want to become closely connected with the librarians I work with and learn about their lives.” It could mean that you’re aware of the climate of the academic job market, and you’re using this as an opportunity to develop skills and expertise that can help you in a wide variety of careers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A project is more than just the stuff - the disciplinary material - in it. It’s a statement about how you view your work and the world and how you think each should be. That’s why there’s a blank line at the end here. You have to decide what that last line is for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/33.png&quot; alt=&quot;Quote by Paulo Freire&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To tip my own hand a little bit, I wanted to speak just for a moment about how I see my pedagogical work and the project underlying it. I had this quote by Paulo Freire in mind as I was writing this talk. “As beings programmed for learning and who need tomorrow as fish need water, men and women become robbed beings if they are denied their conditions of participants in the production of tomorrow.” Sean Michael Morris shared this quote with us at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digitalpedagogylab.com/&quot;&gt;Digital Pedagogy Lab&lt;/a&gt; a few weeks ago, and it’s been on my mind ever since.  There is a lot there, but Freire is getting at a few things. For Freire, education should always be a radical act of revolution. Students should always be thoroughly engaged in the process of shaping their own learning experiences, and it is the job of the progressive educator to help them overturn traditional modes of education and allow them to act as teachers themselves. The quote is about what does or does not help students produce their own tomorrows, but it’s also about producing the tomorrows of education and society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I try to approach all the projects I work on – and really the students are the projects – with a sense of this animating philosophy in mind. I always want to ask, “how is what I’m doing here empowering students to reshape the structures that are holding them back?” There can and should be a reason for everything that I do, and I’m constantly thinking about what that reason is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s where I’m coming from. That’s how I fill in that empty line. And I want you to think about that why question for yourselves. It’s not just a why for the content. But also about the why behind all the steps of project planning. How can your work help engineer the tomorrow you want to see?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I want to end today by helping each of you engage in some soul searching. With the time we have remaining, we’re going to run a series of exercises and discussions about the kinds of goals and assumptions you’re bringing to this. And we’ll talk things out – I’m happy to spend more time addressing specific questions as well. We can go anywhere you want. Let’s get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Sidebar: as I mentioned above, we didn’t actually have time to run the workshop proper, and we instead used the remaining moments for more discussion. I shared the slides with the folks who invited me, because they thought they might make for useful follow-up activities throughout the year. So even though we didn’t get to them, I thought I’d share the materials below with a few quick notes on what I had in mind. I’ll quit with the brackets, as the talk proper has ended. What follows is all just framing for the extra material I had prepared.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;workshop-activities-to-get-you-there&quot;&gt;Workshop Activities to Get You There&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The preceding talk and discussion aimed to get the students thinking about their projects from a number of different angles - practical, logistical, collaborative, and theoretical. But I ended with values because, to me, they’re the most important. They can also be the most difficult to think about. It takes practice to learn how to articulate your values and goals in relation to a project, a measure of self-reflection that we aren’t necessarily taught how to do in graduate school. The following activities are meant to build on each other and guide participants towards a firmer sense of themselves in relation to their projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want to explicitly note the importance of the work of two people to the shape of these activities. &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/people/ronda-grizzle/&quot;&gt;Ronda Grizzle&lt;/a&gt; is the expert in the Lab on project management, charters, and life design, and I adapted the mind mapping activity, in particular, from work she has had us do internally. Secondly, I attended &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalpedagogylab.com/&quot;&gt;Digital Pedagogy Lab&lt;/a&gt; over the summer, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.seanmichaelmorris.com/&quot;&gt;Sean Michael Morris&lt;/a&gt;’s breakout session on writing about teaching was instrumental in changing how I thought about in-class writing activities. I learned the four rules for writing from him in that session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three activities I had planned. Given the title of the talk, I suppose I might call them “three activities to get you there”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Charter discussion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mind mapping&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Timed writing on values&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll contextualize each activity briefly and share the slides that I had prepped. Hopefully that will give a sense of how I’d run them if others are interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;charter-discussion&quot;&gt;Charter Discussion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charters can be somewhat difficult to wrap your head around without models. So I planned to begin by offering the students some examples drawn from past years of the Praxis program. I shared the link for &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/charter&quot;&gt;praxis.scholarslab.org/charter&lt;/a&gt; with the students, and from there I planned on doing a pretty typical think-pair-share activity. None of the charters are especially long, and it’s not necessary to read through one in its entirety to get the flavor of the piece. I anticipated having each student pick a charter to spend five minutes reading and thinking about. After the initial thinking time, they would spend five minutes discussing with their neighbor before we came back for a general discussion for ten minutes or so. The goal was to give the students models and to show them the kinds of categories that might go into such a document. Hopefully from there they would start thinking about personal, professional, and technical values they might have alongside their goals for the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relevant slide:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/34.png&quot; alt=&quot;Charter discussion slide&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mind-mapping&quot;&gt;Mind Mapping&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After looking at charters from other groups, the students are ready to start thinking more deeply about their own views on things. For that, I turn to mind mapping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mind mapping is an activity that asks people to free associate words related to a particular topic in in the service of opening up a free, non-judgmental space for brainstorming. The first challenge with mind mapping, I find, is that people don’t necessarily know what it is. So several of the following slides focus on setting up the concept for participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/35.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mind mapping as a concept&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/36.png&quot; alt=&quot;What mind mapping looks like in practice&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The definition and example mind map I offer here come from a book Ronda Grizzle shared with me called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://designingyour.life/the-book/&quot;&gt;Designing Your Life&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; by Bill Burnett and Dave Evans. After offering a definition, I describe the general process, which involves a starting word, mapping out associations to that word, and then mapping out further secondary associations from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/37.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example of a mind map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Images help to explain this better, I think, so I offer a picture of an example mind map from &lt;em&gt;Designing Your Life&lt;/em&gt;, where someone is trying to brainstorm a potential career from things that interest them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/38.png&quot; alt=&quot;Why mind map your project&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I suggest some reasons for mind mapping. By getting all of your ideas on the table, the process allows you to reflect more fully about which pieces are important to you. At the end of the mapping process, circling four or five of the words most important for you will help clarify which elements could be the basis for a good charter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/39.png&quot; alt=&quot;How to generate the core words of your project&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The starting word in the center of the map is important, as it generates the other associations for you. So I planned on reiterating the questions that we discussed in the course of discussion to help the students get started and to help generate other associations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/41.png&quot; alt=&quot;The mind mapping prompt&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there, the mind mapping activity involves the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Placing your starting word.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mapping outwards for five minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reflecting on the resultant map for five minutes and circling important concepts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Discussing with their neighbor for five minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve done a version of this activity for helping people develop a sense of their DH pedagogy, and I’ve found that mind mapping is great for helping participants engage in deeper forms of self-reflection about their everyday practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;timed-writing-on-values&quot;&gt;Timed Writing on Values&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that the students have seen some examples and discussed them, it’s time for them to write. They’ll be in a decent place to do so, hopefully, because the mind mapping activity already asked them to think about large topics that were meaningful to them. As writing about values can sometimes feel frightening, I drew in Sean Michael Morris’s great rules for timed writing prompts here to help encourage the participants. I chose eight minutes, but you could give a longer amount of time - anything would be useful. After writing, I could imagine having a productive conversation about the results. The students need not feel pressured to share their exact wording, but a general discussion of the process, the issues, and things that they gravitated towards would be useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post-media/getting-from-here-to-there/42.png&quot; alt=&quot;Timed writing on values&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it for the workshop and accompanying materials! Happy to talk with anyone who might be interested in working with them. The trip to Emory was very invigorating and provocative, and I was endlessly impressed, especially, by the students at ECDS. They’re a great crew. Keep an eye out for them - they’re already doing important work, and you’ll be hearing from them soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Five Verbs for Open Pedagogy</title>
   <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/five-verbs-for-open-pedagogy/"/>
   <updated>2019-08-07T12:37:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/five-verbs-for-open-pedagogy</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Crossposted to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/five-verbs-for-open-pedagogy&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week I’m at Digital Pedagogy Lab 2019, where I’m taking a course on Critical Open Pedagogy from Rajiv Jhangiani. For one of our prompts today, he asked us to respond to a post of his on &lt;a href=&quot;http://thatpsychprof.com/5rs-for-open-pedagogy/&quot;&gt;5 Rs for Open Pedagogy&lt;/a&gt;. The goal was to get us to reflect a bit on the values that bring us to the open space as well as the kinds of values that we bring with us. I think the aim was to come up with a concise, listicle style, but I didn’t quite follow that format. If I had to extract five verbs to describe what I write below about open pedagogy, they might be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Care&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Value&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Share&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Empower&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Critique&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prompt and Rajiv’s post make me think of Erin Rose Glass’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.gc.cuny.edu/papers/45249/&quot;&gt;incredible notion&lt;/a&gt; that if you stacked up all the papers written in all the courses in the world each semester they could reach the moon. Along with the image, she offers the provocative notion that those notes will all be thrown away at the end of the term. It’s an image to which I often return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that paper. All those ideas. All those people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things that brings me to open pedagogy is the idea that our students have something to contribute to the world. They are capable of good, complex thought, even about material that they are approaching for the first time. This is a belief about their ideas, but it’s also a comment on their value as people. In short, a degree is not necessary to prove your worth or your ability to think. A student’s thoughts are just as worthwhile as those of their teacher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open pedagogy is a practice that encourages us to think of student work as work, of student ideas as ideas.   Students can change the world if we don’t get in the way. Instead of throwing their ideas away, we should approach them with care and attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world is a terribly risky and dangerous thing, a risk disproportionately shared by different groups of students based on identity and background. We cannot ask students to work in the open without pause. The task of the teacher is to help guide students in this space and to give them agency over their presence in it. To care and to steward, to collect and to distribute. But also to concede and to critique. To grant the right to be forgotten, as &lt;a href=&quot;http://tararobertson.ca/2016/oob/&quot;&gt;Tara Robertson&lt;/a&gt; reminds us. To allow for opting in as well as out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open is not universally good or universally available. A critical open pedagogy recognizes the limits and risks of open and educates students about this space so that they can be productive citizens of it if they so choose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, then, open pedagogy is not just about distributing those pages rather than tossing them. It’s about taking them down from the stack and helping their author to think before throwing them away, even if they wind up deciding it’s necessary to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it’s not just about the paper - it’s about the one who did the writing.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
