<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Brandon Walsh]]></title>
  <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-04T10:26:44-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://bmw9t.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brandon Walsh]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Teaching with Twitter - Part One]]></title>
    <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/11/02/twitter-1/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-02T12:54:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/11/02/twitter-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post begins a series reflecting on my experiments using Twitter in the classroom. Be sure to read the second and third posts that continue the discussion.</em></p>

<p>I was only recently introduced to Twitter as a part of the <a href="http://praxis.scholarslab.org/">Praxis Program</a>, which encourages its fellows to engage with the social media platform as part of their education in how to engage with the digital humanities. I have become fascinated with Twitter’s ability to generate discussion, facilitate connections, and expand my own sense of the conversation in the field. I wanted to bring all of these elements into my classroom and share them with my students, so this past semester I integrated class Twitter responses into the participation element of my syllabus. Students tweeted several times over the course of the semester rather than post email responses to a private course site. In this post, I offer suggestions for the logistics of setting up such a course requirement and recount my own, while later posts theorize the pedagogical implications of the move and offer suggestions for tweaking student participation.</p>

<p>The Twitter requirement was not particularly onerous: I required students to tweet at a course hashtag (#ENRN_F or #ENRN_R) seven times over the course of the semester. Students would only be required to respond roughly every other week, so collectively these tweets would barely equal the length of a more typical paragraph response. I asked students to follow the tweets as they came in throughout the week, and I occasionally used the content of student tweets as quiz questions to encourage active engagement. Response tweets could take any form – a link to an image, a film clip from an adaption, a short quote, a thought on a particular character, a theme, etc. – anything that could advance the conversation.</p>

<p>About half of the students in my courses had used Twitter before, so interested instructors should be prepared to explain the format and offer support for those who are unfamiliar with it. I encouraged students to use <a href="http://tweetdeck.com/">TweetDeck</a> as a free and easy option for following the course hashtag, and we previewed the experience at the first course meeting by putting the app on the class overhead projector. A student tweeted to the hashtag in class at my request, allowing students to see just how instantaneous the class’s twitter engagement could be. I encouraged students to come by office hours during the first week if they wanted help setting up an account, but very few needed the assistance. The activity generated more anxiety up front than actual difficulty in practice.</p>

<p>I taught two course sections of the same course when I implemented Twitter, so I considered using a shared hashtag for both classes. A single hashtag would allow cross-discussion conversation in ways that would not otherwise be possible. The increased activity that would come from two classes tweeting to the same place could provide a lively sense of community, even if some of those participants remain relative strangers in the context of the course. Separate hashtags make the actual logistics of teaching a bit more manageable: it is easier to lesson plan for the students that will actually be in the room and able to account for thoughts they have expressed online. I eventually opted for separate hashtags, but I encouraged students to follow and tweet at their sister section.</p>

<p>Some students who already possessed Twitter accounts protected their tweets, but such gestures towards privacy would complicate the course setup: protected tweets would not show up on the course hashtag unless the student allowed every member of the class to follow them. Similarly, while I encouraged students to be excited about the opportunity to engage with a wider community through Twitter, some felt uncomfortable with their ideas exposed to the world. I gave these students the option of creating a new, dummy Twitter account specifically for the purposes of the course. Their name did not have to be associated with the account at all, so long as the rest of the class knew to whom the account belonged. I circulated a list of students’ twitter handles early on so that we could match names to e-identities. Twitter required students to meditate on the public nature of their own intellectual lives and the reach of their own voices, and dummy accounts respected the privacy of concerned students.</p>

<p>In all, teaching with Twitter requires a relatively small amount of effort to implement, as the barrier to entry for students is quite low. But a little planning about your setup ahead of time goes a long way. For more helpful tips on the logistics of using Twitter in the classroom, check out Mark Sample’s ProfHacker post on &#8221;<a href="http://chronicle.com/blogs/profhacker/practical-advice-for-teaching-with-twitter/26416">Practical Advice for Teaching with Twitter</a>.&#8221;</p>

<p><em>Stay tuned for part two in my series on Teaching with Twitter, where I further discuss pedagogical benefits and justifications for class Twitter accounts, and part three, where I examine ways to curate and cultivate different types of engagement with the class Twitter.</em> </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Tri-Wizard Paper Outline Challenge]]></title>
    <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/10/21/wizard/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-21T10:19:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/10/21/wizard</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This teaching exercise grew directly out of a comment made by <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/wilkinsteachingportfolio/">Kirk Wilkins</a> in a recent <a href="http://fycchat.blogspot.com/">#FYCchat</a> on how he uses Harry Potter to facilitate group work. I instantly fell in love with the idea, but the semester was a bit too far along to integrate a whole Harry Potter house system into the course. Instead, I developed a one-off group activity in the same spirit: The Tri-Wizard Paper Outline Challenge. Group work with a twist - I sorted the students into the houses from Harry Potter, as they competed for our own <a href="http://harrypotter.wikia.com/wiki/Triwizard_Cup">Tri-Wizard Cup</a>, a literary mug filled with candy. &#8220;Let the magic of literature sweep you away to far-off lands!&#8221;</p>

<p><img src="http://bmw9t.github.com/images/mug.jpg" width="40%" class="right"></p>

<p>Enough Harry Potter. On to the activity, which works perfectly fine without the magical theme.</p>

<p>When teaching a discussion section of a large literature survey that only meets once a week, talking about writing presents a constant challenge. Students are evaluated on their ability to execute writing assignments, but there is little class time in which to develop these skills <em>and</em> adequately address the literature. I have been working hard this semester to tie literary analysis consistently back to writing practices, and the Tri-Wizard Paper Outline Challenge attempts to do so by asking students to move from analysis to paper structuring in a very short timeframe. The exercise asks students to work in groups towards a possible paper outline in the course of a single class.</p>

<p>Time Breakdown:<br/>
5-10 minutes to explain the activity and read the passages aloud.<br/>
30 minutes to work in groups<br/>
10 minutes to share, declare a winner, and discuss.</p>

<p>Split the class into four equal groups, each of which has the same small set of passages and the same paper prompt. In the time allowed, each group must develop a paper outline: a thesis statement and three supporting points that will draw upon close readings of the passages. At the end of 30 minutes, students nominate one student from their group to read their thesis and describe the structure of their group&#8217;s proposed paper outline. The instructor then gives very quick feedback on each group&#8217;s work and selects a &#8220;winner&#8221; - the outline most likely to lead a successfully executive argument.</p>

<p>The exercise works best if things are kept as constrained as possible: common passages and a common paper prompt. The activity encourages aggressive time management, and too many options will likely detract from the students&#8217; ability to complete the exercise. I am currently teaching a course on <a href="http://bmw9t.github.com/teaching/#ENRN3210">Shakespeare&#8217;s Histories and Comedies</a>, so my passages all drew from a very small portion of Act I Scene I of <em>Merchant of Venice</em><img src="http://bmw9t.github.com/images/MOV.jpg" width="60%" class="left">. For a prompt I asked that students develop a paper broadly related to friendship, sexuality, marriage, or desire in some way. I chose passages that offer up opportunities for analysis and clear readings: the selections I chose had a strong homoerotic subtext, and several of the student groups picked up on this.</p>

<p>The whole activity is quite frantic in 50 minutes, but it can still work well, so long as you help the students keep a close watch on the time. Ideally, it would be a 75-minute activity, allowing more time for reflection at the end and discussion. I chose to err on the side of not giving enough for follow up discussion of the event: I generally give a short email follow up to each class meeting, so I used this e-space to share more thoughts on why we did the activity and what to take away from it. I would recommend doing the same, even if this is not your usual practice.</p>

<p>The exercise works especially well when conducted after students have already received feedback on written work and in dialogue with those paper comments. Written feedback from the instructor is essential to a student&#8217;s growth, but the ultimate aim is for students to internalize the critical attention so that they can revise their writing on their own. To facilitate this while framing the activity, speak in terms they recognize from your feedback on their papers when discussing how you will judge the final products. I required the theses to be written out because we had stressed the importance of a well-articulated thesis statement with specific language in earlier discussions. I encouraged students to consider alternative paper structures, to consider whether their work was an observation or an argument, and to ask whether their argument was fundamentally interesting or based on plot summary. Many of the group discussions took on aspects of these questions as they shaped their papers.</p>

<p>Teaching detachment from one&#8217;s own writing can be very difficult. Some things just need to be cut, but we often feel personally invested in the words we put on the page. The Tri-Wizard Paper Outline Challenge also allows students to shape a paper outline in which they have little investment. The activity has no grade repercussions beyond participation, allowing students to shape ideas in a collaborative space that models the benefits for developing such detachment. Students have nothing to lose but candy, but what they stand to gain from hearing their peers and themselves speak in the language of good, critical writing - magical.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing Out Loud: Google Docs for Live Writing, Revision, and Discussion]]></title>
    <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/09/25/writing-out-loud/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-25T09:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/09/25/writing-out-loud</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have been using Google Docs as a part of my teaching for almost two years now. The idea first came about in an advanced course on Academic and Professional Writing. We talked a lot about editing in the class, and many of the conversations about style took this shape:</p>

<p>Student A: &#8220;Something about this word feels strange, but I don&#8217;t know what it is.&#8221; <br/>
Student B: &#8220;What if we moved the phrase to the beginning of the sentence?&#8221;<br/>
Student C: &#8220;We could get rid of that word and use this phrase instead.”</p>

<p>Hard to wrap your head around, right? Just imagine if those conversations were spoken. <em>Talking</em> about writing can only get you so far: writing is graphic, after all. As I write and edit, I try out different options on the page. I model possibilities, but I do so <em>in</em> writing. Discussing the editing process without visual representations of suggested changes can make things too abstract to be meaningful for students. I developed an exercise that I call “Writing Out Loud” that more closely mirrors my actual editing process. Using a Google Doc as a collaborative writing space, students are able to model alternate revisions visually and in real time for discussion.</p>

<p><img src="http://bmw9t.github.com/images/WOL_settings.jpg" width="60%" class="right"></p>

<p>The setup requires a projector-equipped classroom and that students bring their laptops to class. Circulate the link to the Google Doc ahead of time, taking care that anyone with the link can edit the document.</p>

<p>The template of the Google Doc consists of a blank space at the top for displaying the sentence under question and a series of workspaces for each student consisting of their name and a few blank lines. Separate workspaces prevent overlapping revisions, and they also minimize the disorienting effects of having multiple people writing on the same document.</p>

<p><img src="http://bmw9t.github.com/images/WOL_template.jpg" width="60%" class="left"></p>

<p>We usually turn to the exercise when a student feels a particular sentence is not working but cannot articulate why. When this happens, put the Writing Out Loud template on the projector with the original version of the sentence at the top. Using their own laptops, students sign onto the Doc and type out alternative versions of the sentence, and the multiple possible revisions show up on the overhead for everyone to see and discuss. After each student rewrites the sentence to be something that they feel works better, ask for volunteers to explain how the changes affect meaning. The whole process only takes a few minutes, and it allows you to abstract writing principles from the actual process of revision rather that the other way around. How does the structure of a sentence matter? How can word choice change everything? What pieces of a sentence are repetitive?</p>

<p><img src="http://bmw9t.github.com/images/WOL_filled.jpg" width="60%" class="right"></p>

<p>Obviously Writing Out Loud works better on micro-edits, revisions at the level of the sentence. The standard process of the exercise—write, collate, and discuss—would take far too long with anything longer than a few lines. The exercise can be particularly useful for those sentences that carry a lot of importance for entire arguments: thesis statements, topic sentences, the first sentences of the document, etc.</p>

<p>I find that students often think of editing as an intense, sweeping process that involves wholesale transformation from the ground up. Modeling multiple, slightly different versions of the same sentence can allow for a more concrete discussion of the sweeping rhetorical changes that even the smallest edits can make.</p>

<p>You can find a copy of the template <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1Dk2GpCqvm6o3K-dbfUazekHbiSlqwJeIoE2OZ-OjL00/edit?usp=sharing">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rails Girls Digital Humanities]]></title>
    <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/09/08/railsgirls/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/09/08/railsgirls</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This past weekend I coached at <a href="http://railsgirls.com/digitalhumanities_fairfax">Rails Girls Digital Humanities</a> at the <a href="http://chnm.gmu.edu/">Roy Rosenzweig Center for History and New Media</a>. The event was amazing, the women were inspiring, and the tacos were delicious. It was just wonderful to take a first attempt at teaching Ruby on Rails in a community that was so supportive and welcoming! I learned a lot about teaching from the day. Here are a few thoughts on the experience and on how I would be a better coach in the future.</p>

<p><strong>Deep Technical Problems</strong><br/>
At my table we ran into a couple problems where Rails refused to play nicely with the version of Windows a student was running. After working on the problem for a while, it became clear that I wasn&#8217;t going to be able to solve the issue in the time allotted. I eventually lent the student my laptop so that she could keep learning and building during the course of the afternoon. Of course, this is only a temporary fix, as the Rails issues would come up again when the student got home and tried to continue working. Is the tradeoff worth it? Or did I just delay the frustration until she was home? In the future it might help to have a designated Rails installation expert hanging around that wasn&#8217;t coaching to help troubleshoot tech problems like these that show up later, after the installation party is over.</p>

<p><strong>Syntax</strong><br/>
Syntax errors often posed the biggest teaching challenge for me. What do you do when you see that the problem is in the syntax before the student does? Suggesting to a student that the issue is with the syntax gave me the feeling that I was withholding information from her, which I can only imagine felt irritating. But I don&#8217;t think jumping in to point out mistakes is any good for long-term skill building either. Fellow coach <a href="http://anglophileinacademia.blogspot.com/">Annie Swafford</a> suggested that I use moments like these to teach the process by which I would find a syntax error, and I could definitely do a better job of this in the future. In the context of following a tutorial like the Rails Girls guides, this would mean a few steps. First, I double-check each line meticulously with one finger on my code and another on the tutorial. Second, I read the offending code backwards bit by bit to get my mind away from thinking about the lines semantically, which often tricks you into overlooking things. As a last resort, I copy and paste the tutorial code over top of my own. If nothing changes, I know there is no syntax error and that I need to look elsewhere. Finally, I search online for answers.</p>

<p><strong>Frustration</strong><br/>
It&#8217;s important to learn that we <em>all</em> break things. Constantly. I tried to stress again and again that I spend far more time breaking and fixing than I do actually building things that function properly. In the future I might even bring copies of some of my own commit messages (<a href="https://github.com/scholarslab/prism/commit/8fba94b904219d42b5d270660d04a4bef69ed034">1</a>, <a href="https://github.com/scholarslab/prism/commit/bfae5eca226dfc8cbbee86f6acbfe63ec0c8c07f">2</a>, <a href="https://github.com/scholarslab/prism/commit/1fbba70b3577d093430426f7b4ee34752aa5c64c">3</a>, <a href="https://github.com/scholarslab/prism/commit/be0a319c44d6d2b3f894168cc26044ff42642c2e">4</a>, <a href="https://github.com/scholarslab/prism/commit/0af47e4d214f1c994714223f93c11801975f09d0">5</a>) to illustrate the point and get some laughs. This feeling of helplessness, obviously, can be incredibly frustrating. Rails Girls DH made me wonder: how much frustration is pedagogically useful? How can we teach frustration in such a way that it doesn&#8217;t cause students to shut down? One of the hardest parts of coaching was learning to balance my instinct to help with the need to allow people to struggle. The women did an <em>amazing</em> job working through and learning from issues that popped up, but I wonder if I was doing the best job possible to facilitate their learning. As a coach, do you jump in the moment someone&#8217;s face expresses annoyance? Or, do you wait for them to reach out to you? I think at times I was too willing to read facial expressions and jump in to help, possibly out of a feeling that I wasn&#8217;t doing enough. Students should learn to feel confident and independent in their tech abilities, and they will only develop these traits by dealing with and pushing through their own frustrations. They should feel that they can ask for help, but they should also learn when they can handle something on their own. In general, I think the women I worked with were better at knowing when to ask for help than I was at knowing when to offer it.</p>

<p>So, if I were coaching again, I would do the following differently:<br/>
1. Bring an extra laptop.<br/>
2. Learn more about the Rails installation process and known issues with different operating systems ahead of time so that I am better equipped to troubleshoot such things.<br/>
3. Talk more about processes: of troubleshooting, of asking for and finding help, and even of conceptualizing new projects.<br/>
4. Strike a more satisfying balance between jumping in and letting students explore independently.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m already looking forward to the next Rails Girls DH event!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bash-it Plugins]]></title>
    <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/08/11/bash-it-plugins-and-symlink-troubles/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-11T16:41:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/08/11/bash-it-plugins-and-symlink-troubles</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes things go wrong. When this happens, I often find a temporary solution that works fine in the moment, but implementing the fix repeatedly can get annoying over time. Here is something that I had been ignoring for a while and only recently took the time to fix.</p>

<p>I use <a href="https://github.com/revans/bash-it">bash-it</a>, which has lots of neat tricks and functions. Since installing it, however, I had been getting a message every time I open up a terminal window:</p>

<p><code>sorry, the z plugin is incompatible with the fasd plugin. you may use either, but not both.</code></p>

<p>The message doesn&#8217;t stop you from going about your business, so I never really read it very closely: bash-it tells you everything you need to know. When installing, bash-it prompts you to make a variety of decisions about how many plugins you will use on a regular basis. I told bash-it to enable everything by default, but this decision caused a conflict between two plugins.</p>

<p>To see which plugins you have enabled, open a terminal window and type:</p>

<p><code>$ bash-it show plugins</code></p>

<p>In the output, you should see some flavor of the following diagnosing the problem:</p>

<p><code>z [x]     maintains a jump-list of the directories you actually use  
z is DEPRECATED, use fasd instead</code></p>

<p>Plugin z causes an error when activated with a newer plugin with the same functionality. Bash-it gives you the fix:</p>

<p><code>$ bash-it disable plugin z</code></p>

<p>After that, your terminal should run free of the message.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TextMate and Git]]></title>
    <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/08/03/textmate/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-03T10:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/08/03/textmate</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This one is for my own files as much as anything else. For some time now, I&#8217;ve been getting a persistent error in Git when I try to go through the steps of committing a file online. This particular error came about when trying to pull before pushing up to GitHub:</p>

<p><code>/usr/bin/mate -w: /usr/bin/mate: No such file or directory
error: There was a problem with the editor '/usr/bin/mate -w'.
Not committing merge; use 'git commit' to complete the merge.</code></p>

<p>From what I understand, this comes about because Git can&#8217;t find the symbolic link to TextMate, even though it has existed in the past. For whatever reason, this issue seems to come up from time to time on my machine. I&#8217;ve tried a number of different solutions online, but none seemed to take.
<a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/9610884/cant-create-a-symbolic-link-with-textmate-in-terminal-mate-command-not-found">This</a> solution finally did it for me. First, of course, make sure that you have TextMate installed and updated (my first mistake). The solution:</p>

<p><code>ln -s /Applications/TextMate.app/Contents/SharedSupport/Support/bin/mate /usr/local/bin/mate</code></p>

<p>This very post was made free of the error.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SelfControl for Working on the Web]]></title>
    <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/07/28/working-web/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-28T20:53:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/07/28/working-web</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The web enables virtually all of my work as a graduate student, but it can all too easily become a powerful distraction. Sometimes it helps to have a few practical aids in the war against procrastination. Of the several tools that I’ve tried - <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-us/firefox/addon/foxfilter/">Fox Filter</a>, <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/stayfocusd/laankejkbhbdhmipfmgcngdelahlfoji?hl=en">StayFocused</a>, and <a href="http://macfreedom.com/">Freedom</a> - <a href="http://selfcontrolapp.com/">SelfControl</a> remains my favorite. SelfControl provides relentless self-regulating freedom from procrastination. Best of all, it is free.</p>

<p><img src="http://bmw9t.github.com/images/Self_Control_1.jpg" width="60%" class="left"></p>

<p>SelfControl is an app for Mac OS X that, unlike FoxFilter or StayFocused, works across browsers. When enabled, SelfControl asks you to specify how long you want to block a list of domains, up to 24 hours. The app also sports a “Whitelist” function that works in reverse, disabling everything except for a handful of specified domains.</p>

<p>Once activated, the blocks remain live until a particularly menacing timer runs down, and only some minor computer hacking will allow you to disable the app’s functionality. This relentlessness is SelfControl’s best and worst feature. The timed function is particularly good for short bursts of productivity, ie. an hour or shorter, but disabling the web for any longer feels too risky: it is easy to imagine time-sensitive emails going unanswered because you have blocked access to the internet for the next five hours.</p>

<p><img src="http://bmw9t.github.com/images/Self_Control_2.jpg" class="right"></p>

<p>At its best, SelfControl allows me to temper the impulse to spend a lot of time hovering around my inbox; I tend to use SelfControl in hour long chunks to allow sessions of distraction-free work in between e-mail checks. How do you stay productive during long hours on the computer?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Praxis Posts]]></title>
    <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/07/23/praxis/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-23T21:19:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/07/23/praxis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>All last year I was a <a href="http://praxis.scholarslab.org/">Praxis Fellow</a> in the <a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/">Scholars&#8217; Lab</a>, where they gave us a &#8220;soup to nuts&#8221; crash course in all things digital humanities. As a part of the program, the fellows were asked to reflect periodically on their experiences on the Scholars&#8217; Lab blog.</p>

<p>I did not do a good job of continually cross-posting those blog posts to this site, so I wanted to make sure that they were properly linked here. I posted with the program on a variety of topics from my work as a developer, to reflections on collaborative programming, to our own plan for the year. Many of the posts relate to <a href="http://www.prism.scholarslab.org">Prism</a>, the tool we built over the course of the year. The Scholars&#8217; Lab has <a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/people/brandon-walsh/">a list of all my posts to date</a>. Below I included the posts with a short gloss.</p>

<ol>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/hello-world/">Hello World</a>: I reflect on how our team would interact with the previous year&#8217;s Praxis team.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/failure/">Failure</a>: On the importance of failing in public and my first stab at creating a personal website.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/marking-and-explanation-in-prism-2/">Marking and Explanation in Prism</a>: Thoughts on the marking interface in Prism and its implications for the interpretive process.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/the-direction-of-prism/">The Direction of Prism</a>: Attempts to reflect broadly on how particular types of changes to the project might affect its direction.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/prism-proposal-against-anonymity/">Prism Proposal: Against Anonymity</a>: An argument for the redesign of Prism to track individual users in relation to the total dataset.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/poster-abstract-and-code-camp/">Poster Abstract and Code Camp</a>: Discusses our DH2013 poster abstract and first reflections on learning code.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/your-digital-life-in-140-characters/">Your Digital Life in 140 Characters</a>: I discuss my first foray into Twitter.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/fizzing-buzzing/">Fizzing, Buzzing</a>: Links my solution to the Fizz Buzz programming homework.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/grading-in-ruby/">Grading in Ruby</a>: I develop a very basic program that will compute your end of semester grading for you.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/ruby-grading-2-0/">Ruby Grading 2.0</a>: I attempt to redesign the same grading program to have cleaner, more elegant code.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/looking-forward/">Looking Forward</a>: Possible directions for the project.  </li>
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/on-learning-code/">On Learning Code</a>: Discusses the online tools that I found most helpful for learning coding.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/omniauth/">Omniauth</a>: On implementing Omniauth for Prism.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/out-on-a-small-limb/">Out on a (Small) Limb</a>: Discusses the importance of small feature branches when working collaboratively.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/on-tasks-large-and-small/">On Tasks Large and Small</a>: On realistic expectations and identifying problems.</li>  
<li><a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/experimental-humanities/arduino-rainbow-hack/">Arduino Rainbow Hack</a>: Reflects on an Arduino hackday held in the Scholars&#8217; Lab.</li>
</ul>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Search Bar]]></title>
    <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/07/10/search-bar/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-10T19:41:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/07/10/search-bar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After some tweaking, I managed to get the search bar to play nicely. I unrounded the corners and lightened the borders to match the framing lines elsewhere in the navigation bar. Here is the CSS for it. You&#8217;ll want to give it an id selector of your own, a la #searchform.</p>

<p><a href="https://gist.github.com/bmw9t/5968989">Here</a> is the CSS for the changes to the search bar.</p>

<p>In trying to embed the above gist, I noticed that octopress breaks the styling: <img src="http://bmw9t.github.com/Broken_Gist.jpg"></p>

<p>Now I have something else to work on.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Design Refresh]]></title>
    <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/07/08/design/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-08T00:39:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/07/08/design</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At long last, I am ready to unveil the project that I have been working on over the summer - a design refresh for site. The main drive behind this aesthetic: I noticed the sheer abundance of information that the basic octopress theme gives you. This setup leads to a lot of duplicate information that ultimately makes things feel cluttered. I tried to keep things very minimal in this design, eliminating as much overlapping information and noise as possible.</p>

<p>I used a few different models for the design of the site. The main inspirations came from the sites of <a href="http://aijazansari.com/">Aijaz Ansari</a>, <a href="http://clioweb.org/">Jeremy Boggs</a>, and <a href="http://daniel.inletters.com/">Daniel Carter</a>. Ansari&#8217;s <a href="http://aijazansari.com/2012/08/27/how-to-customize-octopress-theme/">blog post</a> on customizing Octopress, especially, proved essential as I worked through my own setup. There are still a few things that I could stand to change for this current design, but it felt as thought it was time to let the current iteration see the light of day.</p>

<p>A couple issues I ran into:</p>

<p>How minimal is too minimal in an aesthetic like this? I am not crazy about the search bar in the navigation setup, but it does feel necessary to have one. The function there outweighed the desire to keep the aesthetic. In a future refresh, I will probably try to make the search bar a bit more subtle. In addition, at one point I had my links only turn blue when hovered. This looks great, but it presents obvious problems: you never know what is a link. Again, I had to make some sacrifices for the site to function properly.</p>

<p>How to deal with images in a minimal aesthetic? I initially wanted to have some sort of a banner image at the top where my name serves as a heading. I might explore this in the future, but images offer whole new complications. What kind of image texture would keep the aesthetic alive? Content? Color? I punted the issue for now by opting for my name as the banner, but I will be returning to this in the future.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Looking Forward]]></title>
    <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/02/01/looking-forward/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-01T18:25:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/02/01/looking-forward</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cross posted on the <a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/praxis-program/looking-forward/">Scholars&#8217; Lab blog.</a></p>

<p>As we move into the second half of our tenure on the <a href="http://praxis.scholarslab.org/">Praxis squad</a>, we are feeling the pressure to start actually making something. To that end, the <a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/">SLab</a> crew asked us to make a list of our priorities for <a href="http://prism.scholarslab.org/">Prism</a>. Hopefully this will help us make a to do list in the coming weeks. The following was the list that seemed to come out of yesterday’s meeting, though it’s possible that other people could have gotten different impressions from the conversation.</p>

<p>These seem to be our priorities, in no particular order except roughly that in which they were brought up:</p>

<p><strong>Types of texts</strong> – we’re interested in opening up the Prism framework to deal with pictures, music, etc.</p>

<p><strong>Getting a crowd</strong> – we want to get a large group of people working with Prism, however that might be arranged.</p>

<p><strong>Visualizations</strong> – we’re interested in expanding Prism’s visualizations to allow you to see the individual set of markings in relation to the crowd and to let you see one marking category’s visualization beside another.</p>

<p><strong>User uploads</strong> – we want to make it possible for users/instructors to upload a text for marking themselves, which we see as essential for classroom use.</p>

<p><strong>Complicating the sense of how we highlight</strong> – there has been discussion of complicating how the marking system works, allowing for a limit to the number of markings or a type of marking economy that is distributed across your selections to encourage different types of engagement with the data.</p>

<p><strong>Design makeover</strong> – we want to remake the design of the site with an eye to usability.</p>

<p>I think my own priorities lie in making it possible for users to upload their own texts for marking and in possibly adding more visualizations. If forced to choose between the two, I would spend the time on making the tool capable of handling user uploads. As quickly became clear, any one of these goals spins off into dozens of other questions. What do we mean by “upload a text”? Will those texts be public? Private? How will we navigate copyright and fair use? In the coming days we’re aiming to get a sense of our collective ordering of the list.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Teaching]]></title>
    <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/01/25/teaching/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-25T17:26:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2013/01/25/teaching</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After some Git problems were sorted out and explained to me by the staff of the <a href="http://www.scholarslab.org/">Scholars&#8217; Lab</a>, I can make updates to the site again. I have added some content to the <a href="http://bmw9t.github.com/teaching/index.html">Teaching</a> page: the syllabus for my current writing course among other goodies. Enjoy!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[We're Live!]]></title>
    <link href="http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2012/12/21/were-live/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-21T02:58:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bmw9t.github.com/blog/2012/12/21/were-live</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The site is officially reborn and is now running on Octopress. In the coming days I will continue tinkering with the design and adding some content here and there, but the basic framework for the site is in place.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
