<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: digital humanities | Brandon Walsh]]></title>
  <link href="http://walshbr.com/categories/digital-humanities/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://walshbr.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-10-19T19:12:13+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://walshbr.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[{"name"=>"Brandon Walsh", "url"=>"https://twitter.com/mdo", "email"=>"walsh@virginia.edu"}]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Teaching with Big Ears]]></title>
    <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/teaching-with-big-ears/"/>
    <updated>2020-08-10T16:36:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/teaching-with-big-ears</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Crossposted to the <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/teaching-with-big-ears">Scholars’ Lab blog</a></em></p>

<p>When I studied music in school, we were all given a listening placement test. First, the graduate student in charge would play a series of melodies and harmonies for us, and we were asked to notate them. The second test exercised the inverse skills: given a sheet of music we were asked to sing what we saw in front of us. In each case, we were graded on how accurately we were able to convert sound to written notation and back again. All incoming music majors were slotted into one of six sections based on the results of our ear training test, and I placed into the bottom one. Even the most basic skill–pitch matching, or the ability to hear a note and sing that same note back–was a challenge for me. Twice a week for the rest of the semester, the students in my section filed into a basement classroom and made noise around a piano in what must have been an excruciating experience for the trained music doctoral student who taught us.</p>

<p>Over the course of the year, that teacher worked with us to develop “big ears.” This term refers to a number of overlapping concepts from the music industry that, together, represent an exceptionally strong attention to the nuances of musicmaking and the collaborations required for performance. Ashley Capps, organizer of the <a href="https://bigearsfestival.org/">Big Ears Festival</a> in Knoxville, Tennessee, described it in this way: “The term ‘big ears’ is also slang in the music industry that describes being an especially acute and perceptive listener […] So, a great sound engineer, a DJ who has an affinity for picking hit songs or simply someone who listens broadly and deeply—they’re all said to have big ears.” I’ve heard the term a few times over the years. Most recently, on <a href="https://cubidesartists.com/podcast">The Musician’s Guide to Being Healthy, Wealthy &amp; Wise</a>, a podcast about the music industry, it was used to describe a performer who was especially strong at perceiving what others were playing. In that context, it was specifically used to refer to someone with strong <em>aural skills</em>, a term that refers to the ability to hear pitch, harmony, intervals, melodies, and similar characteristics of music and identify them based solely or primarily on hearing.</p>

<p>Listening in this way—with big ears—is challenging, but it is a skill that can be learned. Each semester as a music student, I had to take a version of that same ear training placement test. Each time I got a lot wrong, but the care and attention of the instructors helped me, over time, to get a little more right. By my sixth semester I made it into the fifth section—not quite the top group of students but close! My last undergraduate semester involved singing a lot of Bach chorales twice a week each morning. I am still far from the best, but I continue to improve to this day. I don’t have a musicianship class anymore, but I do have an <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/ear-trainer/id358733250">app for my phone</a> that helps me to keep practicing. You can always get better at listening.</p>

<p>This is one of my favorite stories about learning because it takes something that appears magical and wholly out of reach and shows that, with time and practice, it is a skill that can be developed by anyone. It’s also a story, I think, about teaching. How easy would it have been for my instructor to belittle me as I struggled to get started with singing? Instead, my teacher listened—however hard that might have been for them. The story feels especially relevant for the present moment, because it’s fundamentally about how those in power do or do not listen to those in their care.</p>

<p>It feels impossible to work right now, let alone teach, when so many people are barely holding families, institutions, and themselves together. How can we work with students under these conditions, when it feels, so often, as though the important voices of those doing the work go unheard? The students and staff that inhabit our educational spaces, that maintain them, and that labor in them are struggling through catastrophe. We are bodies, dealing with the physical and emotional strain of a public health emergency. Now, more than ever, the work of the classroom requires careful attention and, I think, a pedagogy of radical empathy. A renewed focus on intentional and purposeful listening, even—and especially—as it is devalued around us.</p>

<p>When we moved online this spring, I, like many instructors, struggled to transition my work to an entirely virtual format. But I also knew it was entirely necessary. My students in the <a href="http://praxis.scholarslab.org/">Praxis Program</a> were in the thick of shaping what their developing project would look like and how to implement it. When the students and I were able to touch base in our first online Zoom meeting, I made one thing clear: their well-being came first. Even if the students produced no final project as originally planned, that was perfectly acceptable. They were already successes to us. Then, I asked them to take some time to think together about what they wanted to do as a team. These were not empty promises: I was prepared to fully back up whatever choice the students made.</p>

<p>In a number ways, our ability to focus heavily on students’ well-being was enabled by privilege. Because the Scholars’ Lab operates a fellowship program from the library, I don’t have to give grades and the outcomes can be quite flexible. There are, however, a range of thinkers in critical digital pedagogy, including <a href="https://www.jessestommel.com/how-to-ungrade/">Jesse Stommel</a> and <a href="https://www.seanmichaelmorris.com/late-work/">Sean Michael Morris</a>, who have written eloquently on how such choices are good, ethical pedagogy that can and should be explored by all teachers such as they are able. Other critics, too, have talked about the importance of empathetic attention to students’ needs during the present moment. Pedagogy and American Literary Studies has suggested that <a href="https://twitter.com/PedagogyAmLitSt/status/1287817872794882055">you might not need that absence policy right now</a>. Michelle Pacansky-Brock has offered a <a href="https://brocansky.com/humanizing/student-info">model survey</a> for checking on your students’ needs during this difficult time. <a href="http://www.syllabusjournal.org/syllabus/article/view/301">Matthew Cheney</a> and <a href="https://hybridpedagogy.org/pedagogy-of-kindness/">Catherine Denial</a> have each argued for modifying our syllabi and our pedagogies to be founded on kindness rather than abuse. There are many more ideas in circulation, and the ones that most resonate with me are those that accommodate the urgent and pressing needs of others, of those students and collaborators who are caring for children, lack access to broadband internet, or are worried for loved ones.</p>

<p>When we resumed meetings, it was clear that the students wanted to forge ahead and complete their project, but we also recognized that the nature of the community had changed. I think by offering the possibility of an extreme (though, in my view, ethical) response to the pandemic, they, an already cohesive and close group, became even more caring for one another. For the rest of the semester, we had regular check-ins, individually and collectively on personal well-being. We cared for each other as people even as the work carried forward. The project resulted in <a href="http://landandlegacy.scholarslab.org/">Land and Legacy</a>, an incisive look at the University of Virginia’s and the University of Virginia Foundation’s land expansion in Charlottesville and Albemarle County since the 1980s.</p>

<p>For me, these ideas are part of a broad pedagogy of deep listening—that is, of hearing students’ needs as both thinkers <em>and</em> people and structuring a learning environment to accommodate them. Listening in this way is not passive. Instead, it borrows from musicians, for whom listening is always a process of attention and response. In their collection entitled, appropriately enough, <em><a href="https://read.dukeupress.edu/books/book/1150/Big-EarsListening-for-Gender-in-Jazz-Studies">Big Ears: Listening for Gender in Jazz Studies</a></em> Nichole T. Rustin and Sherrie Tucker quote Ingrid Monson on listening: “[jazz musicians] mean it in a very active sense: they must listen closely because they are continually called upon to respond to and participate in an ongoing flow of musical action that can change or surprise them at any moment” (1). Listening—real listening—is about careful attention to the whole, your part in the collective, and how you can grow together. Sometimes that means staying silent. Sometimes that means making noise. It always means paying attention to what the group needs.</p>

<p>Listening, in these terms, is the action by which the collective forms itself. Whether teaching in-person, hybrid, or online this fall, whether talking about the classroom, the administrative planning meeting, or the ballot box in November: voices are likely to be silenced. Committing to listening does not mean inaction in the face of these oppressive systems. Sean Michael Morris gets at a similar point in “<a href="https://criticaldigitalpedagogy.pressbooks.com/chapter/not-enough-voices/">Not Enough Voices</a>,” when he discusses his own anxiety over speaking too much: “The answer doesn’t lie in turn-taking, but in changing what it means to speak. Make speaking a collaborative event. Join your voice with the voice of students. Join your voice with the voice of other teachers.” In these terms, a pedagogy of listening is one that attends to voices, one that helps make space for equitable terms of engagement. This sense of listening, one that is born of and that leads to collective action, is something we need now more than ever. Right now, we need teachers and administrators who are ready to listen, to make space, and to speak up. To hear, echo, and amplify the voices of their students.</p>

<p>There is much more to say about pedagogies of listening. For now I will end with one last quote, this one from Igor Stravinsky: “To listen is an effort, and just to hear is no merit. A duck hears also.” Don’t be a duck. People aren’t born good at listening. Teaching with big ears is a skill you can practice, and there’s no better time than the present.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Your Budget Is a Question of Pedagogy and Equity]]></title>
    <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/your-budget-is-a-question-of-pedagogy-and-equity/"/>
    <updated>2020-04-15T11:29:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/your-budget-is-a-question-of-pedagogy-and-equity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Crossposted to the <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/your-budget-is-a-question-of-pedagogy-and-equity">Scholars’ Lab blog</a></em></p>

<p>I finished drafting this post back before the extent of the coronavirus pandemic was becoming known. And now, of course, the impact of the virus around the globe—and on higher education in particular—continues to evolve. So I had been sitting on this post for some time; I wasn’t sure how a rapidly changing landscape of higher education, replete with hiring freezes and bleak budgetary outlooks, might impact these conversations. I’m still uncertain. But I’m publishing this now in the expectation that ethical conversations about budgets as they pertain to students and teaching are likely to become more important now than ever. I’m grateful to <a href="https://mackenziekbrooks.info/">Mackenzie Brooks</a>, <a href="http://literaturegeek.com/">Amanda Visconti</a>, and Elizabeth Fox for reading the post over.</p>

<p>Caveats aside—this post is part of a larger project I’m working on over the course of the year about the intersections of digital humanities pedagogy as it can reflect and enact infrastructural change in higher education. While each post is meant to stand on its own, they do participate in a longer conversation. It might be helpful to explore the <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/year-of-book-blogging-digital-humanities-pedagogy-in-kind/">framing post for the series</a> for context.</p>

<p>I will talk elsewhere about opportunities for pedagogical interventions in the context of credit-bearing courses. For now, I wanted to speak primarily from my own institutional perspective. As the Head of Student Programs for a library-based center for digital research, the teaching that I do tends not to happen in for-credit courses. Instead, my teaching takes place in a range of activities: year-long student fellowships that carry a stipend that I design and administer in collaboration with the rest of the Scholars’ Lab, one-on-one consultations, one-off workshops, and more. Roughly half of my working life is spent on the actual work of theorizing and carrying out teaching. The other half is spent on developing the administrative infrastructure to allow such work to happen, for myself and others. With that in mind, I wanted to pause over the kinds of pedagogical interventions that can be made by people in these kinds of positions—whether we describe them as alt-academic, para-academic, academic, or otherwise. For that reason, the following does not apply so much to teaching in credit bearing courses, though it might offer useful food for thought as it applies to a range of pedagogical situations.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.seanmichaelmorris.com/the-habitus-of-critical-imagination/">Sean Michael Morris</a> refers to a pedagogical habitus, “embodied practice, often uninspected or subterranean to a person’s own thinking about themselves,” that forms the “genetic makeup” of an instructor’s teaching. In this line of thought, pedagogy is not just a practice–it is more properly thought of as your general attitude towards the work of teaching that you do. Put simply, your pedagogy is reflected in every action you take that could potentially affect students and your attitudes towards all such actions. It’s not too much of an exaggeration, I think, to say that with this frame of thinking every action can be considered a pedagogical one. No administrative decision is too small to affect students in some way.</p>

<p>I often point to budgets as the clearest example of how mundane administrative details, seemingly disconnected from the work of the classroom, have profound ramifications for teachers and learners. To put the finest point on it: your budget is a pedagogical issue. It’s also a question of equity. The economic circumstances your program creates or participates in directly affect the kinds of people able to participate in your programs and the work they can do.</p>

<p>Higher education is a time of enormous financial uncertainty for many students. Sara Goldrick-Rab’s work with <a href="https://realcollege.org/">#realcollege</a>, for example, has brought attention to the number of college students that struggle with food and housing insecurity. The situation is often no better for graduate students who, even if their programs offer tuition remission and stipends, are frequently forced to live in poverty. B. Mano’s <a href="https://thetech.com/2019/10/31/mit-grad-students-poverty">piece on their particular circumstances</a> at MIT sheds light, in particular, on how specific institutional policies can intersect with national labor and immigration law to produce especially dire situations for students. In these circumstances, any decision that we make as administrators can have dire consequences for the lives of the students around us.</p>

<p>Of course, every situation is different and subject to different pressures. Many institutions doing digital work simply don’t have any budget or funding at all. If you’re in a position like this, it might feel difficult to imagine how you could structure financial circumstances for your students in a more equitable manner when you’re still trying to find any kind of firm structure at all. In what follows I don’t mean to propose the perfect as the enemy of the good. Instead, I’d suggest taking the following as opportunities to examine where you’re at in the hopes of finding a way towards better outcomes—whatever “better” means for you and your circumstances. At the very least, I hope that the following discussion can supply resources and questions to use as we all try to advocate for better labor conditions for students.</p>

<p>Four pedagogical questions that you might ask of the student side of your budget are:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Does it exist?</li>
  <li>Is it stable?</li>
  <li>Is it transparent?</li>
  <li>Is it what my students need?</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="does-it-exist">Does it exist?</h2>

<p>Are students a part of your budget? If not, why? In Elissa Frankle’s ignite talk entitled “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0niIskfLpdE&amp;list=PLl7V7chP13lBSnSyYpEp6g6lpu7pZftrC">Pay Your F-ing Interns</a>,” she describes how unpaid internships reinforce whiteness and homogenous, privileged communities in museum workers. Frankle goes on: “We may say that we value diversity, that of course we want to treat our workers well, but do our core documents and budgets reflect that fact?” Our decisions about infrastructure, at their best, should reflect what our organizations believe in. A first useful question you can ask of your budget, then, is, whether and to what degree your work with students rises to the level of budget lines and conversations during allocations.</p>

<p>What you can pay is, of course, a local issue. But it is worth questioning whether your current payment practices are the result of habit or limitations. At UVA, we are subject to a <a href="https://provost.virginia.edu/wage-authorization-academic-areas">range of policies</a> that impact what we can offer students. It’s important to know what these are at your institution so that you can answer statements like “we can only pay X” with “actually, the policy states we can pay X+Y.” I often find state and local policies as a useful first tool when advocating for students, and they can also provide common language for working with financial administrators elsewhere in your institution who might be more removed from the day-to-day lives of your students.</p>

<p>Even if you’re not instituting something as formal as an internship or an hourly position, it’s worth considering how much unpaid time you’re asking of your students. Asking students to drive visiting speakers to events, for example, might appear negligible for the amount of effort it requires. But this small ask still takes a student’s time, time that they could be applying to their own work, to another paid position, or to personal needs.</p>

<p>In short, recognize the economic impact you are likely already having on students and decide whether you can do better. Recognize what you ask of them, first, and second ask what you can pay them.</p>

<h2 id="is-it-stable">Is it stable?</h2>

<p>Students need to be able to plan their finances. If they cannot, only students from affluent backgrounds will be able to make decisions about their educations in the face of such uncertainty. If we want to design programs for students that will be as inclusive as possible, we need to strive for better stability in what we can offer. I am well aware that stable budgets are a luxury in most institutions, including my own. This is especially true in digital humanities, where people and organizations have successfully lobbied IMLS, CLIR, the Mellon Foundation, and the NEH ODH for substantial grants to support their work.</p>

<p>Grant funding can provide valuable experience for students and resources for paying them for their labor. And at some institutions these avenues might be the only ones available for funding the work of you and your students. Grants come with the disadvantage, of course, that they will eventually run their course. Soft money can provide useful supplemental resources for employing students, but the associated instability can cause long-term issues for students and staff. For example, a term-limited grant-funded student position might be listed as one year with year extension contingent on successful performance. In such a situation, the student or postdoctoral worker will spend a significant portion of their time planning and searching for what comes next when the grant-funded position ends. Extensions to a contracted position might, of course, be more dependent on successful lobbying for continued funding than on faith in an already carefully vetted candidate. But it’s still worth considering the real-life ramifications these positions can have for candidates.</p>

<p>It is worth noting the benefits of stable student programs founded on hard money. Through a combination of advocacy and strategic planning, the Lab has been fortunate enough to offer two stable fellowships for several years now. Praxis is completing its ninth year, and our Graduate Fellowship in Digital Humanities is in its thirteenth year. This means that students can plan on these programs as possibilities for them as they plot out not just their research agenda during their time with us, but also their plans for applying for supplemental funding. It is truly unfortunate that we cannot accept everyone who applies, but we work hard to try to bring as many people as we can into our community. It takes time for research agendas to develop, and students need time to decide if such things are right for them. The Scholars’ Lab has application cycles that run virtually all year long for its various programs, and students discuss their intention to apply well in advance of when they are eligible to do so.</p>

<p>Stable programs lead to better support for students as well. Supporting students requires time and energy from staff, no matter how experienced and skilled they might be. Thoughtful and considerate planning that includes student support as part of the regular workload for staff ensures that teaching and pedagogy will not become afterthoughts. Even if suddenly presented with the financial option to take on new students, one should ask if they can be supported.</p>

<p>Good teaching follows from well-supported and energized staff who are empowered to decide if they have the bandwidth to take on new students. Good learning follows from students who can make informed decisions about their lives and have the time and space to commit to learning.</p>

<h2 id="is-it-transparent">Is it transparent?</h2>

<p>I often find that students have received no real information about the systems by which their finances get processed. On the one hand, this is understandable—university budgeting processes are byzantine, and information about payment processing might seem like a means to an end and less crucial to students’ day-to-day lives. But providing knowledge about these systems can help students plan their own lives more capably. I have found it helpful to make sure students are aware of a range of different components related to how their payments are processed:</p>

<ul>
  <li>University payroll calendars</li>
  <li>The length of time it takes for a payment to process</li>
  <li>Whether a payment will be taxed up front or not</li>
  <li>Whether a certain amount of payment during the year triggers automatic taxation</li>
  <li>When payments are likely to come through, how often, and in what amount</li>
</ul>

<p>Each of these elements can help students plan their time and finances. In addition, I’ve found that it can be difficult for us to track when something goes wrong in a payment that we’ve issued. We know when we issue it, and we find out if a student gets their funds. But there are many steps along the way. With many, many links in the administrative chain before the money actually gets dispersed to students, there are many places where things could go wrong. So I have regular appointments on my calendar when I ask students to make sure that they’ve been paid as expected. I often find students are really patient and willing to wait even if it appears that something might be amiss. But, as payments take time to process, I would rather we be in constant communication and transparent about where things stand so that we can reduce the burden on students already living in states of financial precarity. A transparent budgeting and dispersal process is a more ethical one.</p>

<h2 id="is-it-what-they-need">Is it what they need?</h2>

<p>Lastly, any administrative process can be enhanced by student input. As is often the case with teaching, I find the best way to grow is to ask students for their insights. Put simply, unless you were a student <em>very</em> recently, you probably do not know what sorts of pressures your students are subject to. Unless you recently lived paycheck to paycheck, it might be easy to forget the sort of financial precarity that a number of our students live under. And it is impossible for any one person to have personal experience that tracks with every possible student experience in the world. In short, be wary of invoking Students with a capital ‘s’, as one broad monolithic community. In order to take a broad, intersectional approach to your teaching and administration, you must talk with students themselves. They are experts on their own situations, and talking with your students about their needs can help to inform your decisions. They’ll learn more about how the university works, and the teaching and pedagogy you can offer will be enhanced as it more closely matches the real-world experiences of your community.</p>

<p>We address this same point in the <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/student-programs-charter/">Scholars’ Lab Student Programs Charter</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We teach in public, meaning that we talk openly about our pedagogical process. When possible, we write about it as well. If something is not working, we will change it and adapt based on the needs of the students and our colleagues. Accordingly, we expect our students to talk and write about their work and the learning process for them, to engage in the experience, and help us shape a pedagogical experience that works for them.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>To engage your students directly in conversations like those above is to treat them as peers, as collaborators in the learning process in all of its messiness. Details like these might seem removed from teaching or overly specific. But they have material effects on the day-to-live lives of your student collaborators. A conversation with a student about how the uncertainties around a particular fellowship payment, for example, helped us to understand that a different distribution calendar would offer students more cushion if payments were delayed. We wouldn’t have gotten the idea had we not talked with the student directly about their needs.</p>

<p>As mentioned above, it can be difficult to balance these conversations against the realities of trying to do this work. We don’t live in a perfect world, and we’re all working with limited resources. Talking with students directly can be a way of sussing out whether your budgetary situation is operating for them and their lives and how it might work better for them. Students can help us all find our way to more equitable pedagogies and budgets that reflect them. You cannot do everything, but you might be able to adjust a few things. In the current climate of higher education, when many are faced with hiring freezes, across-the-board budget cuts, the prospect of layoffs, and withdrawn job offers, such conversations might seem small. But small decisions can matter in big ways for your students. And they can help us care for our vulnerable community members during chaotic times.</p>

<p>Resources for further reading on the topic:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://humtech.ucla.edu/news/a-student-collaborators-bill-of-rights/">UCLA Student Collaborators Bill of Rights</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1bKpiqX9LPGJsKJsLopFW5vvEgwS3koXZJQU3nv-iuWw/edit">Postdoctoral Bill of Rights</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.dhwogem.org/">Women and Gender Minorities in Digital Humanities group</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Year Of Book Blogging: Digital Humanities Pedagogy in Kind]]></title>
    <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/year-of-book-blogging-digital-humanities-pedagogy-in-kind/"/>
    <updated>2020-01-28T09:41:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/year-of-book-blogging:-digital-humanities-pedagogy-in-kind</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Crossposted to the <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/year-of-book-blogging-digital-humanities-pedagogy-in-kind">Scholars’ Lab blog</a></em></p>

<p>Amanda, Ammon, and I have been discussing our plans for the upcoming year of blogging. While last year’s blogging push was invigorating and exciting, we wanted things to be slightly different in the coming year. In particular, we’ve been talking about wanting more continuity in the things we publish. Speaking for myself, it often felt like I was blogging just in time and on deadline. Some good things came out of that work, but I liked the idea of putting just a little more thinking into the project ahead of time so that I could blog around a central topic for the year. Amanda and Ammon have been incredibly helpful in talking about all this with me.</p>

<p>Truthfully, I’ve been feeling the lack of a large writing project lately. After my <a href="http://doi.org/10.18130/V3R27G">dissertation</a>, I worked on a <a href="http://walshbr.com/textanalysiscoursebook">text analysis coursebook</a> with Sarah Horowitz, a faculty colleague at W&amp;L. I adore blogging, but I feel the lure of a large project I can chip away at over the next year and that can draw together my energy. Am I talking about writing a book? Maybe? We’ll see. I’m certainly not the first person to write a book in public, but the idea of revealing what I was aiming for made me feel a little uneasy. What if my ideas didn’t cohere (I tend to write in multiple sections of a project at once)? What if I didn’t actually produce anything or finish? What if the project turned out to be empty (easier to dismiss a single blog post)? Does what I’m interested in working on even need to be a book? What do I mean by book - is it a published thing with a press or just something big that lives online?</p>

<p>I had initially planned on just quietly blogging around a cluster of ideas over the next year and then potentially revealing at the end that they were part of a coherent project in progress. But as I started to write the first post on imposter syndrome (seriously)- and in the midst of talking with my students about the very topic - I thought I should put my money where my mouth is from the outset. So here you go! Here are my notes on the large, ongoing, multifaceted writing project that I’ll be trying to cohere together over the course of the next year. If it winds up being something I try to actually turn into a book so be it. If it just winds up being a series of blog posts, then I’ll at least be happy to have written about topics I felt were urgent.</p>

<p>One last note on process: in my PhD program we did an activity where we repeatedly drafted a fantasy table of contents for our dissertation. No abstracts necessary at that stage - just a title for the project and titles for the chapters. I found it enormously useful as a means for thinking through the different shapes a large writing project could take. That’s essentially what I do below. I try on a provisional title for the large project and take a spin at some rough chapter ideas. Since this is a blogging endeavor to begin with, within each chapter title I offer some titles, topics, or questions for blog posts that might intersect with it. I flag a few thinkers and discourses that I see this all drawing upon and engaging with. I also offer a few beginning thoughts towards a topic (nothing surprising, if you’ve read other posts by me on here). My arguments always tend to emerge in the process of writing, though, so it will be interesting to see how this develops over the course of a year. So take this for what it is - a sketch of a sketch of things I find urgent and will be trying to attend to over the coming months. Stay tuned for a look into my messy process.</p>

<p>I thought I might start by close reading this provisional, draft-y title as a way of getting at the ideas I want to explore. For now, at least, I’m thinking about it as called <em>Digital Humanities Pedagogy in Kind</em>.</p>

<h2 id="digital-humanities-pedagogy-in-kind">Digital Humanities Pedagogy in Kind</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Our pedagogies model and reflect the kind of academic community we want to see in the  world. Academia is toxic in numerous ways. Teaching and the ways we theorize and practice it can be interventions in the culture around us. The project hopes to connect classroom practice broadly construed with the kinds of infrastructural changes they reflect and enact.</li>
  <li>Kindness is at the core of the project. I’m trying to formulate a theory of DH pedagogy that is, at its core, one about developing a less toxic and more affirmative space for students in higher education. It’s about developing empathy and kindness as teachers and how DH can (or cannot?) offer us the space to do so within and against the infrastructures of academia.</li>
  <li>Finally, at least in this title, I wanted to get at the idea of paying a debt in goods and services rather than in cash. For starters, I like this formulation because it draws in a range of topics. What do we owe our students? It raises the specter of student debt. And it draws in Paulo Freire and questions of neoliberal, zero-sum teaching. Is digital humanities fundamentally bound up in neoliberal politics of the university? Yes. How can we develop an ethical, just, and progressive pedagogy anyway and in the face of this?</li>
</ol>

<p>A starting list of thinkers I imagine the project in dialogue with: <a href="https://www.cathydavidson.com/books/the-new-education/">Cathy Davidson</a>, <a href="https://www.dukeupress.edu/putting-the-humanities-phd-to-work">Katina Rogers</a>, <a href="https://jhupbooks.press.jhu.edu/title/generous-thinking">Kathleen Fitzpatrick</a>, <a href="https://mith.umd.edu/advocacy-design-moving-theory-practice-part-1/">Jeremy Boggs and Purdom Lindblad</a>, <a href="https://www.halperta.com/">Hannah Alpert-Abrams</a>, <a href="http://akhenrichs.com/blog/">Amanda Henrichs</a>, <a href="https://www.roopikarisam.com/">Roopika Risam</a>, <a href="http://saragoldrickrab.com/">Sara Goldrick-Rab</a>; <a href="https://urgencyofteachers.com/">Jesse Stommel and Sean Michael Morris</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/finiteeyes/status/1217175390491295744">Matthew Cheney</a>, <a href="https://hybridpedagogy.org/author/catherine/">Catherine Denial</a>, bell hooks, Paulo Freire; <a href="https://thedigitalpress.org/failing-gloriously/">Shawn Graham</a>; <a href="https://digitalpedagogy.mla.hcommons.org/">Rebecca Frost Davis, Matthew K. Gold, Katherine D. Harris, and Jentery Sayers</a>; <a href="https://briancroxall.net/">Brian Croxall</a>; <a href="https://artepublicopress.com/carolina-villarroel/">Carolina Villarroel</a>, <a href="https://www.uh.edu/class/spanish/faculty/baeza-ventura_g/">Gabriela Baeza Ventura</a>, <a href="https://mith.umd.edu/people/person/trevor-munoz/">Trevor Muñoz</a> (and more). Significant projects that I’d examine and reflect on would include the <a href="https://humtech.ucla.edu/news/a-student-collaborators-bill-of-rights/">UCLA Student Collaborators’ Bill of Rights</a>, the <a href="https://archive.mith.umd.edu/offthetracks/recommendations/index.html">Collaborators Bill of Rights</a>, <a href="https://futuresinitiative.org/">The Futures Initiative</a>, <a href="https://www.hastac.org/">HASTAC</a>, <a href="https://digitalpedagogy.mla.hcommons.org/">Digital Pedagogy in the Humanities</a>,  <a href="https://iliads.org/">ILiADS</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/generousthinking?src=hash">#generousthinking</a>, <a href="https://hcommons.org/deposits/item/hc:26741/">The Postdoctoral Laborers Bill of Rights</a>, the <a href="https://hcommons.org/groups/academic-job-market-support-network/">Academic Job Market Support Network</a>, <a href="https://aadhum.umd.edu/">AADHum</a>, and <a href="http://usldhrecovery.uh.edu/">USLDH</a>, among others. In my mind I want to tie together questions of higher education reform, critical digital pedagogy, and DH pedagogy. I’m certain I’m leaving people and projects out in this short and initial list - such is the nature of blogging about a work in progress. I’ll be working on a Zotero bibliography that collects these resources for myself and others as I continue reading around about the important work already being done in these areas.</p>

<p>I imagine the project offering a theory and praxis of DH teaching and pedagogy - very broadly construed, as it tries to develop a theory of pedagogy far beyond the classroom -  as an intervention in academic culture. DH pedagogy offers a number of great interventions to begin with – meditations on failure, teaching as activism, rethinking the professional futures of humanities students – and I’d like to join those conversations with others from critical digital pedagogy that emphasize radically student-centered teaching. With these frameworks, I’ll focus the work on the conditions of being a DH student – the material labor and working circumstances, the conditions of professional development and career prospects, the intersections of administrative decisions and the economic conditions of student life. I think doing so will help to give a better sense of the lives at the core of DH pedagogy as they intersect with the administrative infrastructures of DH. And perhaps ultimately the project aims to argue for a pedagogy that teaches with and alongside students and with kindness that happens together (a lot of echoes of Kathleen Fitzpatrick’s <em>Generous Thinking</em> here).</p>

<p>That’s where I’m at right now at least. Lots of loose threads and jumbled thoughts but at least a place to get started. One unresolved question for me is what makes this an argument about DH and not just pedagogy in general? Is it DH just because I am a DH person? Or does DH specifically have something to say about this? Is the DH audience, in particular, a good one for this? Or not? Things I’ll want to think further about in the future for certain. Without further ado, though, I’ll close with the draft table of contents and associated blog topics / questions. The arc of the project as I’m thinking it at the moment moves from micro to macro, from the classroom to larger questions of professional climate.</p>

<h2 id="draft-table-of-contents-and-ideas">Draft Table of Contents and Ideas</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Introduction
    <ol>
      <li>Where does DH teaching happen?</li>
      <li>Where does infrastructural change happen?</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>Classroom experience
    <ol>
      <li>Kindness and generosity as skills that require training</li>
      <li>Pedagogies of listening</li>
      <li>How do we make the classroom a space where students can be sheltered from the academy and also create the conditions to transform it a la <a href="https://jwernimont.com/">Jacqueline Wernimont</a>?</li>
      <li>What are the spaces of teaching, for DH in particular?</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>Labor
    <ol>
      <li>DH students as DH teachers</li>
      <li>Neoliberal DH pedagogies</li>
      <li>Expanding on the UCLA Student Collaborators’ Bill of Rights</li>
      <li>Precarious labor and the labor of teaching</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>Infrastructure
    <ol>
      <li>As it impacts pedagogy and student life and teaching in particular; how do the small decisions we make at the level of administration reflect out pedagogies?</li>
      <li>How can pedagogy be enacted beyond the classroom? How can we take teacherly actions as administrators?</li>
      <li>How can those teacherly administrative actions address issues of precarity among the student population?</li>
      <li>Your budget is a question of pedagogy and justice</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>Profession
    <ol>
      <li>Imposter syndrome. Where does imposter syndrome start for students? How can we address it?</li>
      <li>Professional Development / Career Paths</li>
      <li>Professional Imposters</li>
      <li>Small changes / big changes</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>Conclusion – on inclusivity
    <ol>
      <li>How do we invite students into the profession and into higher education in a way that makes their voices heard and valued?</li>
      <li>How can we ensure students are valued in online spaces? Or welcomed in spaces of open peer review?</li>
      <li>Where to go from here?</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Seems like plenty to go on for now. Now to get blogging!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Digital Humanities Job Talks: Some Case Studies]]></title>
    <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/digital-humanities-job-talks-some-case-studies/"/>
    <updated>2019-12-16T11:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/digital-humanities-job-talks:-some-case-studies</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Co-authored with <a href="http://amandavisconti.com/">Amanda Visconti</a>. Crossposted to the <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/digital-humanities-job-talks/">Scholars’ Lab blog</a> and <a href="http://literaturegeek.com/2019/12/16/digital-humanities-job-talks">Amanda’s personal blog</a>.</em></p>

<p>To follow up on sharing and annotating <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/dh-cover-letters/">our past cover letters</a> for DHy academic jobs, in this post we share how we’ve thought through past job talk prompts and the experience of giving the resulting presentations. (To learn more about Brandon’s practical workflow to drafting and memorizing talks, check out his <a href="http://walshbr.com/blog/dh-public-speaking/">post on DH public speaking</a>! To learn about Amanda’s workflow, prod her to finally publish a now-too-long post about DH and public speaking anxiety before 2020 ends…)</p>

<p>Before you dive in, though, you may wish to read our October 2019 blog post <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/dh-cover-letters/">“How We Talk and Write about DH Jobs”</a> if you haven’t already. Well intentioned academic job advice can be and often is harmful—so in that post’s “Slightly Better Job Advice, Take Two” section, we discuss how we’re trying to share what we know about job searches in a way that affirms any readers as valued peers and scholars, just as they are. We hope sharing our experiences here can be useful and not overly prescriptive. Our perspectives are shaped by our own particular contexts, and we trust that readers will know their own circumstances - and what will work for them - better than we do. With this in mind, we share the following in the hopes that resources and transparency about our own thinking on the process of preparing for job presentations can help others getting started.</p>

<h2 id="brandon">Brandon:</h2>

<p>I should note outright that my experience pertains to giving job talks for what might be called alternative academic positions in DH working in libraries. And, while I have seen a number of presentations by job candidates for a range of library positions, I have always wondered how my own background and experiences affect how I evaluate candidate presentations. For example, I do not have a library degree: I did my graduate work in literature before coming to work in libraries, and this different orientation undoubtedly shapes how I view job presentations and prepare for them. When applying for any position, it’s a good idea to talk with someone who is familiar with that discipline or field so that they can give you a sense of the generic expectations that your audience will bring to your presentation. I would not take any of my thoughts on job talks as prescriptive in the least. Your mileage will vary. But I remember my own experiences as a student felt largely as though I was trying to approach a job presentation without any context or sense of how to think about them. Hopefully seeing how I do so can help someone in the same position formulate their own approach.</p>

<p>We’re often raised to think of writing and, by association, presentations, as having a clear and direct point. But, to me, the difficulty with alt-ac job talks is that they often seem to address a number of different issues at once. When I prepare one, I try to think of the presentation as working to convey a few things:</p>

<ul>
  <li>my response to a prompt</li>
  <li>my experience</li>
  <li>my understanding of the job</li>
  <li>my vision for the position</li>
</ul>

<p>You can find the <a href="https://walshbr.com/blog/in-out-across-with/">job talk</a> for my current position as Head of Student Programs in the Scholars’ Lab on my website. As I discuss elements of that job talk below, readers might find that full text helpful for context.</p>

<h3 id="prompts">Prompts</h3>

<p>Many positions that ask you to give a presentation will also give you some kind of prompt for the job talk. To a greater or lesser degree depending on the audience, they will expect you to respond to it. For my position as Head of Student Programs in the Scholars’ Lab, I was given a prompt that broadly addressed education in digital humanities:</p>
<div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>What does a student (from undergraduate to doctoral levels) need to learn or experience in order to add “DH” to his or her skill set? Is that an end or a means of graduate education? Can short-term digital assignments in discipline-specific courses go beyond “teaching with technology”? Why not refer everyone to online tutorials? Are there risks for doctoral students or the untenured in undertaking digital projects? Drawing on your own experience, and offering examples or demonstrations of digital research projects, pedagogical approaches, or initiatives or organizations that you admire, make a case for a vision of collaborative education in advanced digital scholarship in the arts and humanities.
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>I had a lot of feelings about this prompt, as you can imagine. As Amanda mentions below, prompts are often abstract and vague because they are not written with any particular candidate in mind. By trying to offer something for everyone, they sometimes seem intentionally amorphous so that anyone can find a way to latch onto the material. But this means that a prompt can go anywhere, really, and trying to devise a response to it can feel very difficult. So my first point of advice is simply that the difficulty with the prompt is not you! It’s a strange genre, and recognizing this can hopefully help begin to mitigate feelings of imposter syndrome.</p>

<p>In my case, I remember feeling pretty convinced that every question on my prompt could be its own talk. There was just so much to work with, so many topics to address! In the face of this issue, I explicitly framed my own talk as only responding to the first question listed - “What does a student (from undergraduate to doctoral levels) need to learn or experience in order to add “DH” to his or her skill set?” I thought responding to all pieces of the prompt was an impossible task, and I leaned into a talk that did more with less. For what it’s worth, I remember one person approaching me after the presentation and softly noting that I had not responded to all of the questions in the prompt (but they still appreciated the talk). Fair enough, but I did what made the most sense to me. Noting the parts of the prompt you will or won’t address can be a useful way of articulating the intentionality of your response for the audience, and it can also be useful for people in the audience who might not be as familiar with the text of the prompt. After all, in an open job talk you are likely to have some members of the search committee in attendance as well as those who might be more removed from the search process.</p>

<p>Like Amanda describes, I framed my response to the prompt as a critique of it. In essence, I argued that framing DH education as about acquiring a set of skills would undercut the prospect for DH pedagogy to make real, transformative change in the lives of students and institutions. There were a few reasons I took such a perpendicular approach to the question. I had worked in the Scholars’ Lab as a student, so I had some sense of the philosophy of the institution at which I was interviewing. I knew at least a portion of the room would be open to the kind of critique I wanted to offer. For better or worse, I also wanted the talk to show the kind of hire I would be. In other words, I didn’t want to present myself as having one set of views at the interview stage only to be hired and reveal myself to have a set of opinions and beliefs that wouldn’t fit with the institution. If the search committee was looking for someone who really thought of DH education in terms of skills acquisition, I was not that person. They would not be happy with me in this position, and I would not be happy trying to act in it. Better, I thought, to get it all out there. Like Amanda says below, it’s worth noting that not all candidates have the comfort and privilege of being able to make a decision like this as part of the interview process. The approach worked for me, but it might not work for others in different situations. You best know your own circumstances. I do think it’s worth trying to use the hiring process to suss out in small ways the kind of environment in which you would be employed and whether you can be happy there, but you don’t necessarily need to use your job talk to do it.</p>

<h3 id="experiences">Experiences</h3>

<p>The audience for a job talk is going to show up to learn about you and your qualifications in relation to the job for which they’ve brought you in. This can be tricky, as in a public talk the audience will contain a diverse range of people. The search committee can be expected to have spent time with your CV and cover letter, but, while those documents are typically circulated in advance, you cannot assume that everyone at a public talk will have given the same attention to those documents. So, while you don’t want to wholly reiterate your background, you do need to share some of your qualifications. I think of this as an opportunity to contextualize some of your experiences in a richer way so that your work can play for the whole audience regardless of how familiar they are with your work.</p>

<p>By richer context, I mean that a job talk is a good place to take the things listed on a CV, select two or three, and deploy them in service of a larger vision for the position (more on that below). What did you learn from working with X? How does Y connect to the kinds of work you will be doing at institution Z? I often find it useful to pick a few things from my background and ask “so what?” of them repeatedly until I feel that they stand on their own as a self-reflective moment in the talk. You can use an otherwise boring and rote listing of experiences to show an audience <strong>how</strong> you will work in a position by reflecting on the work you have already done. In the Scholars’ Lab talk, I talked about my work at <a href="https://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/">WLUDH</a>, a coursebook I was co-writing with a faculty collaborator, and my experiences with curriculum design. But examples like these wouldn’t stand on their own - I thought of them as evidence in the larger argument I was making about how I think about DH teaching. Another way to think about all this: in an essay, you are likely to cite other authors or texts as you make your argument. In job talks I think of the evidence as potentially drawing from either your own experiences or other example projects/texts in DH. By weaving these together, your job talk can show both your personal qualifications and your sense of how your work connects to the broader field.</p>

<h3 id="understanding">Understanding</h3>

<p>To some degree, the audience will expect you to signal that you know what the job will entail. It’s always difficult to know exactly what the day to day life at a place will be like, and most of the time a candidate won’t actually make it to the job talk stage if their understanding of the position is in question. But conveying your understanding of the position can help nonetheless. I often tell students to think of it as a roleplaying challenge. You have imperfect knowledge of what the position will be like, but you have evidence from websites, projects, descriptions, and postings. Search committees are always trying to imagine each candidate into the position. Why not meet them halfway and start to imagine yourself into the position in your job talk? There are, of course, ways to do this poorly - I would not go into a talk saying “I will entirely transform everything in my first week. Only I have the solutions to your problems.” You will never have all the answers. Furthermore, positions always have pressures and needs that are difficult to perceive from the outside, and it can be useful to acknowledge that. I like to offer this formulation: “Given that I know you are working on X, I would take my experiences with Y to work towards Z with you all.” Syntactically it’s not actually a formula I would recommend, but as an exercise in thinking it can get you in the direction of good thinking about yourself in relation to a job. In that way, you’re making transparent the kind of thought process that you will bring to the position. And you’re helping the search committee by shaping the imaginative exercise of hiring for them.</p>

<p>To do this well, you’ll need to do research on the position but also the institution. If the position has existed before, what kind of work did they previously do? What kind of projects did they take on? Does the job description appear to be different in some way from that previous body of work? The institution can also offer clues: libraries, small liberal arts colleges, and cultural heritage institutions (to name a few) each carry with them certain assumptions about the work that they do, and these categories can offer evidence for you as you start to determine what kind of work the place values. You might also look at projects undertaken, grants and new initiatives that might be in process, recent hires, and the like. Some institutions might even offer explicit statements of values that you can explore. The Scholars’ Lab, for example, has published a series of <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/charter/">charters</a> describing how we think about our work. I had the benefit for my presentation of having worked with the Scholars’ Lab as a student. So I knew something of how they thought of themselves, and I similarly tried to frame my interest in working with DH students towards progressive, transformative reform in higher education. But I only knew the Scholars’ Lab from the student’s perspective - I had to make a lot of educated guesses about how they thought of their work and their students.</p>

<p>One further thought: applying for jobs can be especially scary as a student. It’s all too easy to think, “I am a PhD student in literature! What do I know about institutional collaboration for DH education?” But you probably know more than you think! You’ve likely experienced a number of these issues from the student side, so you actually have valuable experiences with them. Many administrators are desperate to get student voices on a range of issues, and your direct experience can provide a useful perspective when combined with research about the other sorts of stakes, pressures, and questions that the position might engage with. It’s just a matter of imagining yourself from the other side.</p>

<h3 id="vision">Vision</h3>

<p>This point is not one that I’m sure is required by the generic conventions of general DH staff jobs. Lots of people leave it off. But it is an element that I often think about, and I know that, of the job presentations that I’ve attended, all of the ones I considered the best included some sense of a vision for the work they will do. I was trained that a piece - be it an essay or a talk - should have an argument to it. So it’s difficult for me to imagine preparing a job talk that doesn’t also offer an argument, a philosophy, a vision for the work. In the context of the Scholars’ Lab talk, I explicitly framed the position I was applying for as someone who thinks past and beyond the prompt I was given. This was my closing sentence:</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Foremost, then, I see the Head of Graduate Programs as someone who takes the lists, documents, and curricula that I have discussed and connects them to the people that serve them and that they are meant to speak to. This person is one who builds relationships, who navigates the prepositions of my title.
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>I presented a vision of the position as one that fundamentally cared about the people and their development more than the skills associated with digital humanities. For me at least, it’s important that a talk say something, even in a genre as strange as a job presentation. “Vision” can be a big baggy term with little meaning to it. But you might approach it by asking a series of questions of yourself - why is this position important? what do I see as the fundamental role of this position? What are the top three verbs I would associate with this position? How can I frame this position as being vital to the mission of the institution? A job description answers the “what” of a position - what about the “why”? In trying to work in a sense of your philosophy for the work, you’re helping a search committee to further imagine what kind of a colleague you would be. I think it will also make for a more engaging job talk. And that job talk is also likely to be easier to write if you’re engaged with the topic of it!</p>

<p>One last note on DH / alt-ac public speaking. In some disciplines it is common to read your talk. Job presentations often seem to be done from notes instead. I try to operate somewhere in the middle. For my longer presentations I write my talk, memorize as much as I can, and then give some version of it more or less off the cuff but with the talk in front of me for reference. The result is something that is bloggable, has a shape to it, is more engaging than reading from a paper, but more polished than a presentation fully off the cuff. I’ve written about this elsewhere if you want more detail about <a href="https://walshbr.com/blog/dh-public-speaking/">my process</a> for preparing for talks. It feels a bit idiosyncratic, but it could work for you as well.</p>

<h2 id="amanda">Amanda:</h2>

<p>My job talk thoughts are biased toward the roles I’ve given a candidate’s talk for—tenure-track faculty roles (interdisciplinary lab; library with digital humanities focus) and the SLab co-director role (library staff). You might also wish to check out talks from others who’ve applied to related DHy and library roles for more approaches—<a href="https://readywriting.org/faculty-development/faculty-development-for-the-21st-century-and-beyond/">Lee Skallerup Bessette</a>, <a href="http://celestesharpe.com/onward/">Celeste Tuong Vy Sharpe</a>, and <a href="https://chrisbourg.wordpress.com/2015/07/12/infrastructure-and-culture-a-job-talk/">Chris Bourg</a>—or visit the <a href="https://hcommons.org/groups/academic-job-market-support-network/documents/">Academic Job Market Support Network</a> on Humanities Commons, a forum created by Hannah Alpert-Abrams where folks have uploaded a variety of humanities-related job materials.</p>

<h3 id="responding-to-job-talk-prompts-in-general">Responding to job talk prompts, in general</h3>

<p>You’ll likely be given a prompt to reply to via your talk. In both of the talks shared below, I took a mild risk in explaining why I was responding a bit differently than probably expected to each prompt. I’ll talk about the privileges that allowed me to take these small risks below; if you do not have those privileges, you’ll probably want to respond more directly to prompts than I did, yet still with some changes from how you might answer the prompt if, for example, someone asked you the same thing during Q&amp;A or a panel interview. That is: a job talk prompt is intended to be something that each candidate should be able to answer, and is thus often fairly abstracted and open to interpretation. Sometimes, creating a question that will work for all candidates results in a franken-prompt containing multiple questions.</p>

<p>This might just be a question of how you frame your response to yourself, but my recommendation is to not treat this as you would an essay question on a test: no one is scoring you for explicitly mentioning or responding to the letter of each question in a prompt. An explicit answer to all portions of a prompt can be fine, but it can also make for a poorly structured, hard to listen to talk. I’ve found it more useful to use the prompt as a prompt, rather than as a question—that is, a suggestion of topics your audience might want to know your thoughts on. (In combination with the HR-approved job ad, it might offer more specific clues to local contexts or challenges you could ask about…) I try to give a talk that shares both the philosophies guiding my professional practice and very specific examples from my past work as illustrations. What your audience may remember is whether your talk presented you as 1) someone up to the job’s tasks, and 2) someone who would be a good and healthy addition to the local community. I’m guessing most people won’t even notice, much less care, if your talk isn’t an explicit response to the prompt.</p>

<p>Below, I’ll discuss how I worked through a response to the prompts for two of my past successful job talks, and then comment on the structure and contents of each talk.</p>

<h3 id="scholars-lab-managing-director-talk">Scholars’ Lab Managing Director Talk</h3>
<p>You can read the full text and slides of this talk <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/disrupt-the-humanities-managing-director-job-talk/">here</a>.</p>

<p>The talk prompt was:</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>The digital has the potential to be a disruptive force in humanities scholarship, giving scholars the means to critique, reimagine, and transform ideas, theories, material artifacts, and even interpersonal relationships. Using examples from your own collaborations with faculty, graduate students, and staff, please discuss how this disruption can be successfully embodied in scholarly inquiry, as well as in the cultivation of people and organizations.
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>I was recruited to apply to this job while working in a comfortable role (tenure-track library faculty) with some stellar colleagues and local resources, so it was safe for me to take some risks in my interview. Because paying my rent did not depend on receiving a job offer, I was able to pay more attention to whether the role would be good for me, to be more open about my values and what I wanted in a workplace. So when something in the prompt made me uncomfortable, I decided I wanted to speak to that from the very start of my talk. This turned out well, but could have gone badly, had I failed to convince the audience of the worth of my perspective, or offended the folks who wrote the prompt (assumedly, these were the folks on my search committee and/or folks I’d be reporting through).</p>

<p>The prompt wasn’t explicitly positioning “disruption” as a positive force, but that assumption felt at least implicit enough (disruption allowing reform, wanting that to be “successful”) that I was uncomfortable not speaking specifically to the problems with that. (Part of my reaction was from past experience giving a job talk at a “demo or die” pro-language-of-disruption institution, and my discomfort about how that place’s mixture of amazing colleagues but also very shiny resources temporarily pushed me more toward more disregard for the harms of disruption.) I’ve learned that most terms invoke both positive and negative possibilities:</p>

<p>Valuing openness does harm to cultural practices intended for limited access (see e.g. <a href="https://localcontexts.org/tk-labels/">Traditional Knowledge labels’</a> approach to this issue)
Speaking at a highly abstracted level about “diversity” or “social justice” can disadvantage acting on specific harms including racism and classism.
In Data Feminism, Catherine D’Ignazio and Lauren Klein discuss a number of terms that connote “imagined objectivity” and alternative terms that better “strengthen real objectivity”, e.g. “ethics” =&gt; “justice”, “bias” =&gt; “oppression”, “fairness” =&gt; “equity” (I learned this from Neil Selwyn’s <a href="https://data-smart-schools.net/2019/02/03/data-feminism-introductory-thoughts/">review of their book</a>)</p>

<p>I want to avoid the harm often done in the name of “disruption” treated as a context-less good. And I knew that Scholars’ Lab had a history of publicly valuing many of the same things I valued, e.g. from reading the <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/charter/">staff charter</a>, and appreciating staff’s tweets and conference talks. So my approach wasn’t actually a huge risk, but enough had recently changed in terms of the lab and library’s staff and work that if those values had shifted unbeknownst to me, I would probably be able to choose not to work there without harm to my livelihood. And I was applying to co-direct the lab, so there was more space to safely share thinking that might be a change to the institution’s current values.</p>

<p>This is all to say, the first sentence of my SLab job talk was: “My digital humanities is not disruptive.” I won’t repeat the rest of my talk, as the first few slides explain why I diverged from the prompt, how I thought about the positive potentials of DH. I did respond to the part of the prompt that indicated what the desired outcomes of (a positive definition of) disruption were to them, and in particular noted that people were mentioned multiple times (relationships, specifics examples of collaboration, organizations). After defining what my definition and goals for DH were against a negative read of “disruption”, I spoke to the prompt’s emphasis on people by structuring the rest of my talk around two examples of people-centric work (my <a href="https://infiniteulysses.com">Infinite Ulysses</a> participatory edition, and founding the <a href="https://tinyurl.com/DHSlack">Digital Humanities Slack</a>).</p>

<p>Attending to the people behind scholarship was a way for me to give the audience a sense of how I might be as a colleague. In my talk, I cited people who impacted how I think and work, regardless of the format (book, article, tweet, panel discussion, lunch conversation, something someone pointedly didn’t say) and regardless of if that person identifies as a scholar. If they contributed to how you think, you should cite them.</p>

<p>But I need to mention privilege again: Some people think less of you for having co-authors or other collaborators, as if that shows your effort was smaller rather than greater. If you aren’t read as male, some people may assume you didn’t do the coding or other technical work on your DH project. If you’re hurting for a job and/or already have other biases working against how people treat you, you might need to be more emphatic about your individual contributions to scholarship.</p>

<p>In this job talk, I tried to speak to people who value or assume different things than me, e.g. folks who would appreciate an explicit discussion of how something functions as scholarship, rather than assuming that people recognize the work behind <a href="http://InfiniteUlysses.com">Infinite Ulysses</a> or the <a href="https://tinyurl.com/DHSlack">DH Slack</a> as scholarship. And given I’ve had some experiences that are likely to be construed as academic success, like my dissertation project being cited in The New York Times, I think it’s reasonable to make sure your interviewers know about that—even if you’re kind of uncomfortable with that being seen as a metric toward whether you should be hired. But I also spoke to things I was proud of that others might not value or see as relevant to scholarship, like receiving emails from a variety of non-faculty strangers happy about discovering my DH project. Interviewing necessitates anxiety, and it’s a privilege to be safe and comfortable sharing some pieces of yourself during a job visit—but I’ve found myself happiest after interviews, including an interview where I did not get offered the job, when I felt I brought and shared more of my full self during the process.</p>

<p>(I was basically going to rewrite Brandon and my post about how to share our job-market knowledge without prescriptively reinforcing classist, sexist, etc. notions of individual value and what counts as scholarship, so instead I’ll just link to <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/dh-cover-letters/">that post</a> again—I learned a lot from the discussions we had before deciding to continue blogging our past job search experiences and advice, and we tried to capture those ideas about a more just and affirming way of supporting jobseekers in that post.)</p>

<h3 id="purdue-tenure-track-faculty-dh-specialist-talk">Purdue Tenure-Track Faculty DH Specialist Talk</h3>

<p>You can read the full text and slides of this talk <a href="http://literaturegeek.com/2016/02/28/DHjobtalk">here</a>.</p>

<p>The talk prompt was:</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Digital humanities and the research library: opportunities and challenges for academic libraries and librarians. Draw upon your experience and knowledge as well as citing research literature in library/archival/information science, and/or disciplinary literature relating to digital humanities. (Audience: Libraries staff and faculty)

</code></pre></div></div>

<p>As with my SLab job talk, I quibbled mildly with this prompt, and explained why at the start of the job talk:</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>There are already many recent voices defining what the digital humanities (or DH) is, what a library does, and exactly how much DH and libraries overlap as academic fields. I didn’t want to rehash those debates, so I put together an online Zotero bibliography with bunch of pertinent readings, which you can access via [tinyurl.com/dhlibraries](https://tinyurl.com/dhlibraries). You’ll also be able to find any work I cite in this talk there…Pulling together over fifty works defining DH and libraries, and strategizing this combination, wasn’t difficult."
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Instead, I wanted to focus on what DH might look like locally, given how I’d function if hired:</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> It was harder to find case studies of the specific, day-to-day tactics of successful combinations of DH and libraries. So, in wanting to discuss the specific question of DH library service today, I’ll try to give some specific examples, spoken and on screen, of the types of events, workflows, and services I’m envisioning. I’d like to focus on what both the strategy and the tactics of a user-focused service ethic look like, when combined with 1) the digital humanities commitment to collaboration, and 2) recognizing scholarship in all areas of professional practice.
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>A small thing, but I like that I included an explicit reference to caring about timekeeping while outlining my talk (“I’ll be talking for around 15 minutes, after which we’ll have a lot of time for discussion”) to help the audience pace their attention.</p>

<p>Now that I know that community, I think the audience would have appreciated more time spent on what DH is and what the arguments about DH and libraries are than I gave them. It’s hard to gauge that, or know who will be at your talk! I think I did okay by defining what DH would look like locally if I were hired, but sharing a few specific projects that show the breadth of what DH can be would have improved the talk. I’d recommend focusing on what DH is to you, and what you hope for DH to be (inspired by <a href="https://twitter.com/elikaortega/status/618097310505938944">Élika Ortega</a>).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Digital Humanities Pedagogy and Opportunities for Hope]]></title>
    <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/digital-humanities-pedagogy-and-opportunities-for-hope/"/>
    <updated>2019-10-16T09:45:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/digital-humanities-pedagogy-and-opportunities-for-hope</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Crossposted to the <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/digital-humanities-pedagogy-and-opportunities-for-hope">Scholars’ Lab blog</a></em></p>

<p>In September, I visited Emory University in conjunction with the launch of their <a href="http://digitalscholarship.emory.edu/partner/learn/ddsp.html">new graduate fellowship</a> for students aiming to incorporate digital projects in their dissertations. This is the second of two posts sharing materials from the events I took part in while there. I was asked to give <a href="http://walshbr.com/blog/getting-from-here-to-there/">a workshop on project development for graduate students</a> as well as an open talk on digital humanities pedagogy. The text of what follows pertains to the open talk I gave, where I was asked to give a broad overview of how the Scholars’ Lab works with students. I write a talk for situations like these, but I try to avoid straight-up reading the text (<a href="http://walshbr.com/blog/dh-public-speaking/">more info on how I approach public speaking in DH available here</a>). So what you will see below is more like a roadmap of the general gist of what we talked about. I did not consult the text too much in the moment. The only other relevant piece of framing that you will need is that I added the phrase “he works for the students” to the end of the bio I gave Sarah McKee (Senior Associate Director for Publishing at the Bill and Carol Fox Center for Humanistic Inquiry) to read when she introduced me. Talk begins below!</p>

<hr />

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/1.png" alt="Title slide" /></p>

<p>Hello! I’m Brandon Walsh. I am the Head of Student Programs at the Scholars’ Lab, a community lab for experimental scholarship in all fields, particularly informed by digital humanities, spatial technologies, and cultural heritage. You will hear a lot more about what we mean by that in the talk to come, one that I have titled “Digital Humanities Pedagogy and Opportunities for Hope.” Thank you so much for having me and for coming today to hear me talk. I am truly grateful for the opportunity to speak with you.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/2.png" alt="zotero collection, links, and acknowledments" /></p>

<p>I wanted to first start out by offering a couple links and thanks. If you need access to the slides or the transcript of this talk (or you’re interested in what I shared with your students in <a href="http://walshbr.com/blog/getting-from-here-to-there/">the workshop</a> earlier today), you can find those resources at <a href="http://bit.ly/Emory-Talks">this top link</a>. I have also made a <a href="http://bit.ly/DHPedagogyAndHope">Zotero collection</a> here with all the resources I mention in the talk in case you want to take a look at them later on. And finally, most importantly, I wanted to take a moment to express gratitude to everyone whose work has brought me here today. I’m very grateful to all my colleagues in the Scholars’ Lab whose work you will hear about in a moment, especially Amanda Visconti, Ronda Grizzle, Jeremy Boggs, Laura Miller, and Shane Lin. And I would also like to express my thanks to Sarah McKee, Lisa Flowers, Anandi Silva Knuppel, and all the ECDS students for making this trip possible and invigorating.</p>

<p>Sarah asked me to give a high-level overview of the Scholars’ Lab and how we work with students. I will do that today, but my standard disclaimer about the Scholars’ Lab is that we are a complex entity with many different folks doing many kinds of jobs. And you will get a different path through our work depending on who you ask. I am the Head of Student Programs, so given my work and interests you might come away from this talk thinking, “they only work with students.” This is not true! We have an R&amp;D team and spatial technologies staff that work with the entire university, students, faculty, and library staff alike on a variety of different projects related to digital scholarship, digital preservation, and digital project development. So what you will hear about today is about my own particular corner of the lab. One of my colleagues might have a different, overlapping story. My story is about our students, though I am happy to help flesh the full picture out for you if you would like during discussion.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/4.png" alt="Overview of what is to come, text to follow" /></p>

<p>At the risk of tipping my hand too early, I wanted to offer an overview of what is to come. I’ll move back and forth between example and theory, but the main takeaways, if I had to offer them are these. First, DH pedagogy does not just take place in the classroom, and it’s not just about DH. Second, digital humanities pedagogy is pedagogy. Third, DH pedagogy at every level should consider, intersect with, and reconstruct desire paths through the academy. I’ll talk more about all of these ideas in a moment. I’m not going to be offering any practical thoughts on how to carry out DH pedagogy, though I’m happy to do so in the discussion afterwards. This is more a talk about the animating philosophy for DH and pedagogy as we try to practice it in the lab, about the idea that teaching can offer spaces for hope in the university.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/5.png" alt="Chad Sansing bio page" /></p>

<p>When Sarah invited me here today, as is usually the case for things like this, she asked me to send her a bio. I always dread this part of giving talks. When I was a student, I always felt like I hadn’t done enough, and I hated hearing people read my short list back to me. Now that I have been working in the field for a bit longer, I still find it embarrassing for different reasons. So I decided to take a cue from Chad Sansing of the Mozilla Foundation and do something with this moment of discomfort. In his <a href="https://medium.com/@chadsansing">bio on Medium</a> he mentions, a bit tongue in cheek, “I teach for the users.”</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/6.png" alt="Tron movie poster" /></p>

<p>I don’t want to spend my entire time here reiterating the plot of the 1982 movie Tron, but, in my reading at least, Sansing’s bio is a riff on a line from that movie: “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8kcgosLwPDE">he fights for the users</a>.” The line describes the titular character of the movie, a security program who fights other fascist computer programs on behalf of the users who have been locked out of the computing world. It’s a lot. But I like Sansing’s adoption of it here, and I wanted to try it out for myself. I like the way that his bio ties up his identity into a kind of mission statement. “Who am I” becomes “why am I here?” He is here to teach, and he’s here to teach the users how to take back control of the web.</p>

<p>The bio I gave Sarah ended with the phrase “he works for the students.” That phrase is a mission statement and also the subject of this talk, which will deal with how we work in the Scholars’ Lab to have care and consideration towards our student collaborators suffuse everything we do. I’ll talk against the ideas that teaching only takes place in the classroom and that administrative work has nothing to do with teaching.  I’ll start with what we do in the lab “for the students” and why. Second, I’ll contextualize this briefly as happening against the backdrop of a larger crisis in higher education. Third, I’ll offer thoughts about how we can shape a DH pedagogy that responds to such emergencies.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/7.png" alt="Image of a desire path - a paved path to the left with barriers on it to prevent speeding cyclists. To right, a trodden path made by pedestrians and cyclists avoiding the barriers and paved section entirely." /></p>

<p>To begin. In the Scholars’ Lab, we try to start by approaching the whole student. We try to think about how our decisions affect lives and need to be informed by lives. Because administrative choices matter in big ways for people. When an application date gets set, who is eligible for a fellowship, or what kinds of work we allow as permissible in a particular context - choices like these affect the journeys our students are on.</p>

<p>So I would like to start by talking about paths. This image by an English Councillor circulated on the <a href="https://digitalpedagogylab.com">Digital Pedagogy Lab</a> hashtag last month, and it illustrates a phenomenon called a “desire path” or a “desire line” – I would wager we have all seen them before. Desire lines are the paths made, over time, by people stepping on the same, unplanned path. They typically represent the organic actions of pedestrians as opposed to what was planned by the city designer. In this case, based on the Twitter conversation, the path you’re looking at appears to have been made over time by cyclists in response to the constructions you see on the left, obstacles deliberately put in place to discourage cyclists speeding along on this paved path. It is not difficult to imagine the accessibility issues caused by this same construction choice.</p>

<p>I’m taken with this image as a metaphor for the life of a graduate student in academia (caveat here that most of my comments will be about graduate students given who I tend to work with, but I think they are relevant for students generally as well). The image certainly resonates with me, coming as I do to work in the library without a library professional degree but instead with a PhD in English. In short, our students might get into this space for one reason, and we might imagine paths through it on their behalf. But everyone finds their own way through their own education and often through different means and to different ends than we anticipate. I certainly got pulled sideways at a certain point and wound up in a place I could not have envisioned at the beginning of my time at UVA.</p>

<p>I often wonder in related ways about my own activities in the administration of the Scholars’ Lab and in higher education more generally. In my role, I’m often making or offering small choices that are likely to affect the course of someone’s journey through their time as a student. These individual, local interventions in a person’s path - how do they fit into the larger journey for them? Am I helping people to form their own desire paths? Or am I the one throwing up barriers? How can I take those barriers down or help pave a new path to help the route be a little easier? Who am I to be making such decisions for other people? How can I take the responsibility of these choices as seriously as possible?</p>

<p>Given this logic of the desire path, for student programs to service your community in a perfect world you will be offering a diverse slate of opportunities. Because your student population does not just have broad and diverse disciplinary research questions – they also come from a range of different backgrounds and life situations. An MA student, at UVA at least, has a different course load and does not typically teach. This puts them in a fundamentally different category financially, with different pressures and needs, from a PhD student. And what works for one will not work for the other. That is to say, any conversation about DH pedagogy, for me, starts and ends with a discussion of the lived circumstances of the students. Our student activities in the lab are foremost informed by a consideration for the diverse contexts and backgrounds that our students represent.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/8.png" alt="For students page of the slab site" /></p>

<p>We try to make our programs fit those many needs, and we try to offer a number of different ways in to do so. The phrase “for the students” that I mentioned earlier is also pretty close to a page on our website where I try to collect everything that a student might be interested in knowing about us. This is the “For Students” page of the Scholars’ Lab website if you would like to check it out at <a href="http://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/for-students">http://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/for-students</a>. I will talk about a few of these pieces in detail first from a nuts and bolts standpoint and then a theoretical one, though I am happy to talk in more depth about any one of them.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/9.png" alt="Image of our makerspace" /></p>

<p>We regularly offer two hourly wage positions for students in the lab. The first is that we employ hourly students in our makerspace as technologists assisting community members with 3D printing jobs, experimental electronics, or sewing and wearable electronics. No experience is necessary for a student to take on the role, and we typically train people up on the job. There are a number of makerspaces on campus, but ours is distinct for being committed to teaching folks how to do the printing themselves. So you don’t drop off a file and pick up a print - you learn how the technologies work. And our makerspace primarily caters to humanities students, though we do get a fair amount of traffic from science students who tend to find our space less crowded than the ones provided by the Engineering School.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/10.png" alt="Mapping of Anne Whitney abroad" /></p>

<p>Second, our GIS specialists <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/people/drew-macqueen/">Drew McQueen</a> and <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/people/chris-gist/">Chris Gist</a> service needs related to spatial technologies for the entire University, and they regularly employ a GIS student collaborator to assist them in doing so. This student and these projects can come from across the university – not just the humanities. And they also frequently collaborate with local and regional governmental organizations on a variety of different geospatial projects. Our students are there at each step along the way as collaborators.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/11.png" alt="Will Rourk's Twitter account on scanning" /></p>

<p>We also engage students in an internship for course credit through the architecture school, where our 3D Data and Content Specialist, <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/people/will-rourk/">Will Rourk</a>, collaborates with them on the scanning of artifacts and spaces that are significant for cultural heritage purposes. They often carry out site visits in the region, and Will also collaborates with local museums on scanning objects of importance to them.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/12.png" alt="3D model that resulted from scanning" /></p>

<p>Will then engages those same students in the production of 3D data based on these objects. Through the process, our student interns get a deep introduction to all different parts of a 3D data pipeline, and the work that they all do together is truly impressive. The previous tweet and this 3D model all relate to the McCormick observatory on UVA’s campus.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/13.png" alt="Summary of the two year-long fellowship programs in the Scholars' Lab" /></p>

<p>Beyond these opportunities, we also offer two yearlong fellowship programs that offer deeper dives into digital humanities. These are the programs that I most directly supervise. Our higher-level DH fellowship is for advanced PhD students at the dissertation stage who want to work on a project related to their research. They teach some, but they are largely doing a deep dive into developing a professional portfolio that will serve them on the job market. And our <a href="http://praxis.scholarslab.org">Praxis Program</a> is something of an introduction to digital humanities by way of project-based pedagogy. The six students in this fellowship each year form a cohort and work collaboratively on a self-designed project over the course of two semesters. The students drive the program: the fall feels more like a seminar or workshop with us at the front of the room, but the spring is owned by them. We flick them in a direction, but they take the project and develop it in a way that feels authentically theirs both in spirit, scope, and shape.</p>

<p>So that’s a piece of what we do in the lab, and you might have noticed just how much we do for students. I am well aware that the Scholars’ Lab is in a privileged position as far as resources go, both for centers for digital research and even within our own library. Over 2/3 of our budget goes directly to students, and we work directly with about 50 students each year. That’s a <em>lot</em>. As anyone who works with budgets knows, our own budget is the result of longstanding and ongoing campaigns for more resources. I am grateful for allies in the library who recognize the value of supporting students and especially to those who fought for years before I was involved to get those numbers to where they are. These numbers are not settled, and we have to work to keep them every year. But I bring these points up to ask - what can an institution without this level of support do? What can an individual without the support of an institution do? What are small actions we can take in our pedagogy - particularly our DH pedagogy - to help the desire paths our students are trying to make for themselves, even when we’re limited by resource scarcity?</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/15.png" alt="&quot;I don't teach - quote from a colleague&quot;" /></p>

<p>For me, one way of approaching these questions is to think more deeply about what we mean when we think of pedagogy. I remember one conversation I had about teaching, when a colleague offhandedly said, “Oh well I don’t teach.” And a nearby colleague agreed as well. I remember doing a double take. These were people who, to my mind, were constantly engaged in the work of teaching.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/16.png" alt="&quot;I don't teach - you who teach all the time.&quot;" /></p>

<p>Even besides the workshops they regularly give, these were people who mentored students, helped with their projects, and pair programmed beside them to help them learn. Furthermore, they’re fantastic teachers. The general culture in the Scholars’ Lab is one in which we constantly engage in peer mentoring. Digital Humanities is hard - there are so many fields. No one knows all of it, and we try to offer a spirit of generous assistance to each other every day as we find our way through this field. How, then, did I have an entirely different view of these colleagues than they did of their own work?</p>

<p>I think my colleagues were equating teaching with teaching classes as instructors of record. And, to be fair, sometimes I’m asked whether I am teaching or not in the upcoming semester, and I don’t quite know how to respond either. While I sometimes teach semester-long courses, my primary work is not in such traditional modes of instruction. While it’s not really the question they’re asking, my gut response is usually to think, “when am I not teaching?”</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/17.png" alt="Pedagogy as habitus" /></p>

<p>This is to say that pedagogy is not something that only happens in the classroom. I especially like the way that Sean Michael Morris describes this notion in <a href="https://www.insidehighered.com/digital-learning/article/2018/10/10/digital-learning-experts-reflect-evolving-field-new-book">an interview</a> with Jesse Stommel. They’re two prominent scholar-practitioners of critical digital pedagogy, and they’re the chief instigators behind Digital Pedagogy Lab. In an interview about their new collection An <a href="https://urgencyofteachers.com/">Urgency of Teachers</a>, Morris describes pedagogy as not something we just enact in the classroom. Instead, it’s a system of beliefs that we carry with us. A way of orienting ourselves in the world. Or at least it should be. If we think about teaching and pedagogy as things that only take place when we’re in front of a classroom or with our names in an LMS, then I would argue that we’re not thinking of teaching in the fullest possible sense. The spaces for teaching are vast, and our students many. To be “for the students,” we need to think of education as a way of life. As something that runs deeper than sharing material with students. This about how we view them and their work. We’re always teaching, whether or not we’re in front of students for a whole semester.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/18.png" alt="Image of charters" /></p>

<p>It’s one thing to believe having values like these are important. But in the Lab we also believe it’s important to share them, and now we’re getting into the philosophy behind what we do. We believe it is important to write our work philosophies down and to explicitly say them in public. In the Scholars’ Lab, we believe in explicit statements of values called charters, documents that spell out your beliefs, goals, and ambitions. We have had our cohorts of Praxis students put charters together describing their shared ambitions and values each year for the last nine years. <a href="http://praxis.scholarslab.org/charter/charter-2011-2012/">Here</a> you have one of the Praxis charters from one of the early cohorts. They cite free and generous credit, transparency, and an awareness of each other’s diverse backgrounds and disciplinary interests as important markers for them. The hope is that by encouraging our students to examine their shared group identity we will draw out a richer sense of themselves and each other.</p>

<p>Last year in conversation with <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/people/jeremy-boggs/">Jeremy Boggs</a> we realized that, even though we have our students write a charter every year, we hadn’t actually done one of our own, as a staff, for our student programs. We possessed a general charter for the lab, but we thought our student programs needed to explicitly share their own pedagogical philosophy and promises. It was time to make things clear and explicit. So we wrote one together. For the students.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/19.png" alt="Image of student programs charter in particular" /></p>

<p>You can find the whole charter on our website at <a href="http://scholarslab.org/student-programs-charter">http://scholarslab.org/student-programs-charter</a>, and I’d encourage you to read it. It’s a document that is not perfect, but it’s one that I’m glad is out in the world. Here are a few excerpts from it that describe our approach to teaching.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/20.png" alt="Excerpts from the student programs charter" /></p>

<p>We’re here, and we care. We trust in students. We teach the whole person. We’re committed to advancing pedagogical practices that are equitable, just, and ethical. It’s important that our students know where we stand, and one of the first things I have our students do is read this document along with the more <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/charter/">general charter for the Scholars’ Lab</a>. Our pedagogies, the ways we think about our work with students, should be shared with them. In the Lab we believe they should be part of the conversation.</p>

<p>Lest you think this is an artifact of the quotes I chose to emphasize, the charter doesn’t actually talk an awful lot about technology. It does occasionally, but only in oblique ways. We want our students to own their projects as well as their domains. We want them to fail in public in a way that pushes their comfort zone but not their safety. We all feel like imposters - many of us everyday. Some of you probably feel like imposters right now. I know I do. These points imply a certain interdisciplinary approach to technology, even though they are not specific to digital humanities.</p>

<p>And it’s also not lost on me that I’ve spent most of this talk on digital humanities pedagogy not talking all that much about <em>digital humanities</em> pedagogy. And that’s part of the point.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/21.png" alt="DH pedagogy is pedagogy" /></p>

<p>Digital humanities pedagogy is pedagogy. I’ll say that again. Digital humanities pedagogy is pedagogy. Similarly, to go back to Digital Pedagogy Lab, I’ve heard Sean Michael Morris say that the “digital” part of DPL is just an excuse to get people in the room to talk about pedagogy. The definition of digital humanities I usually give to students is one I draw from <a href="https://isearch.asu.edu/profile/3146756">Elizabeth Grumbach</a>: DH is asking humanities questions <em>of</em> technology and asking humanities questions <em>with</em> technology. DH pedagogy is certainly teaching that engages with those topics, materials, and methods, but leaving it there is akin to saying that you only teach if you’re an instructor of record.</p>

<p>Because I feel a tad guilty staying wholly theoretical I want to pause for a moment to say that there are great resources for digital humanities pedagogy from a practical perspective: I highly recommend <a href="https://www.bloomsbury.com/uk/using-digital-humanities-in-the-classroom-9781350029750/">Using Digital Humanities in the Classroom</a>, co-authored by Claire Battershill and Shawna Ross, and <a href="https://digitalpedagogy.mla.hcommons.org/">Digital Pedagogy in the Humanities</a>, edited by Rebecca Frost Davis, Matthew K. Gold, Katherine D. Harris, and Jentery Sayers. These resources are exemplary for those seeking practical advice and examples on how to teach digital humanities.</p>

<p>But what I mean by “DH pedagogy is pedagogy” is that, for us in the Scholars’ Lab, a digital humanities pedagogy is one that thinks deeply and critically about the teaching itself and the interpersonal, societal, and institutional changes it purports to make. It’s not just about the classroom. That is to say, we certainly teach DH methods, tools, and thinking, but we’re more directly trying to think about how and why we do this work and what larger implications it might have. Digital humanities might be an especially good opportunity to make these sorts of interventions, and that brings me to the quote that the title of this talk is riffing on.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/22.png" alt="Henry Giroux quoting Freire, text to follow." /></p>

<p>“Opportunities for Hope” is a play on Henry Giroux quoting the work of Paulo Freire. In full it reads: “Hope demanded an anchoring in transformative practices, and one of the tasks of the progressive educator was to ‘unveil opportunities for hope, no matter what the obstacles may be.’” For Freire, education in its best shape was always about social reform, and he called for new forms of teaching that empowered students and upended traditional modes of instruction like the banking model for education that assumes students are empty vessels who need to have the knowledge of the instructor given to them only to regurgitate it back. And it’s this same spirit of transformation that we bring to the students who work with us in the Scholars’ Lab. How can our pedagogical practices as digital humanists open up space for new ideas for students, but more importantly, for imagining new lives? How can we unveil opportunities for hope, no matter the difficulties? Beyond simply giving them tools and methods, how can we go further and make the teaching we do be a political intervention?</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/23.png" alt="But it's all on fire" /></p>

<p>More specifically, how do we unveil opportunities for hope in a climate like the one in which we all live, where it often feels higher education is on fire? Tenure track positions are vanishing, adjunctification is on the rise, and an enormous number of students and staff are in precarious positions. A so-called “free speech” crisis threatens actual free expression and freethinking in our classrooms. I could go on and on. I spoke about the privileged position the Scholars’ Lab is in, in terms of funding. But, no matter how much funding we’re able to direct to students, it’s never enough. There are always more students applying for fellowships than we have spots to give. Since I’ve been teaching, students have spoken with me about homelessness, food insecurity, precarious finances, uncertain job futures, mental health crises, chronic health conditions, and more. And I know the student populations I’ve worked with are not unique in higher education. How do we find hope for ourselves and for our students in the face of these situations? And what can pedagogy do here? I’ll offer three provisional responses to this question. In the face of a crisis in higher education, we should think of the work we do as creating spaces of shelter and intervention, as empowering student voices, and as changing culture more broadly.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/24.png" alt="Feminist lab symposium" /></p>

<p>My first response is that we can think of the teaching work that we do in digital humanities spaces as work that seeks to shelter and also to intervene. “<a href="https://whatisafeministlab.online/">What is a feminist lab?</a>” was a symposium that took place at University of Colorado Boulder earlier this year. I got permission from <a href="https://jwernimont.com/">Jacqueline Wernimont</a> to cite her remarks, quoted here: “A lab can be a technology to survive the institutions we work in while we seek to transform them.” Our students in the Scholars’ Lab frequently refer to it as an oasis in the larger academy, by which I take them to mean that we value their futures, their concerns, and anxieties in ways that are not as well supported elsewhere. As they develop charters and have conversations about the values they want to develop and promote during their time with us, I often encourage them to think of it as an opportunity to shape the sort of kind, generous, and transformative space they want to see in the academy.</p>

<p>That is to say, we also engage students in a wide variety of support that is not particular to wage employment or research. Some of these are programmatic. We offer mock interviews if students wind up applying for library or digital humanities related jobs. We read materials. We circulate job postings relevant to this kind of work. But more generally we have frank conversations with students about our lives and theirs and try to make space for them in ways that might otherwise be difficult in other parts of the university. Our fellowships don’t carry grades, we allow deferment of our fellowships, and we generally try to make lives a little easier. For us, this is the work of pedagogy, and the fact that we are operating in a library-based digital humanities space helps facilitate this. Your own mileage may vary, as your circumstances are likely to be different. Given your own limitations, how can you use your position as teachers to inject more kindness into the academy?</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/25.png" alt="UCLA Student Collaborators Bill of Rights" /></p>

<p>Second – we can respond by asking, “where are the students?”</p>

<p>It’s important that we keep student interests and needs in mind. They are an important audience for our work, but sometimes they can disappear from the conversation when we discuss long-term strategy. So simply asking how students fit in is a place to start, and even small actions like making sure the word “student” appears on mission statements can be important interventions. But we can go further.  Student voices need to be included in discussions about their own education. Digital humanities pedagogy is often quite amenable to this, as project-based pedagogy of the sort that is common in DH can often invite students to have an active role in shaping their experiences. The <a href="https://humtech.ucla.edu/news/a-student-collaborators-bill-of-rights/">UCLA Student Collaborator Bill of Rights</a> has other good advice for how to engage student voices and to make sure that you’re doing so in an ethical way. It’s a touchstone for us in the Lab.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/26.png" alt="ILIADS splash page" /></p>

<p>The Small Liberal Arts Community (as exemplified by <a href="http://iliads.org">ILiADS</a>) offers fantastic models for how you can engage students as true partners in research projects and disrupt the labor distinctions that all too often exist in our work. I’d encourage you to explore the ILiADS site for examples of projects that might offer models as you think through how to work with students. For my money, the SLAC community is offering some of the most exciting digital pedagogy work. This kind of flattened distinction between student and teacher, as much as possible, is something we try to aim for in the Scholars’ Lab. It’s expressed in a concise way, I think, in this Instagram story by Nicholas Payton, a prominent jazz trumpet player and composer.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/27.png" alt="Quote by Nicholas Payton, text to follow" /></p>

<p>In a recent “ask me anything” session on Instagram, Payton was asked, “Who are the best trumpet teachers alive right now?” He responded, “There are no great teachers, only great students who give tools to other students.” That is the world I want to live in. A world in which the Scholars’ Lab students see themselves as experts, and in which their staff and faculty see themselves as equal partners in the pursuit of knowledge.</p>

<p>We’re all students at the end of the day.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/28.png" alt="Praxis program splash page" /></p>

<p>This can sometimes feel difficult to square with digital humanities, though, where often we quite literally have things we need to share with students that they are encountering for the first time. One thing we try to do in the Lab, beyond adapting our curriculum to the needs of the students, is talk to our students about the work of teaching and learning in which we are all engaged. We talk to them about why we are doing what we are doing, what difficulties we’re having, and what thoughts they might have for making a better experience.</p>

<p>For example, I mentioned the Praxis Program, our yearlong fellowship where our students go from soup-to-nuts with digital humanities, from knowing little to launching their own collaborative digital project by the end. For years, the interdisciplinary makeup of the team has been a recipe for real interpersonal conflict. Usually in March. Every year, right when the rubber hits the road and they’re trying to launch their project. Finally this past year we decided to talk to the team about it.</p>

<p>During the second session of Praxis this year, Amanda Visconti and I ran a discussion for our new cohort of Praxis students on good collaboration and community. And we laid this pedagogical problem out – we talked about issues we had in the program in the past not as interpersonal issues between specific people but as expressions of larger difficulties in collaborative work. We discussed what seemed to help and what did not. What’s more, we also talked about what good collaboration looked like for each other and how the students could make sure they treated each other with respect and kindness first. The students took the conversation very seriously. Last year was the best year yet as far as collaboration is concerned, and Amanda and I just ran the conversation for a new cohort last week. In short, there’s no need to treat pedagogy like something that has to be hidden from your students. Particularly in DH, as it asks so much of students professionally, interpersonally, and emotionally, we need to involve student voices in the development of good teaching practices. They deserve it, and everyone’s experience will be enriched.</p>

<p>Third, and I think it’s apparent from this talk, we have to think about the work that we do, even at the level of the individual assignment, as engaged in a larger project of shifting the culture of the university. When I spoke to the graduate students earlier today, we ended our workshop by talking about values. The workshop was called “getting from here to there” with a digital project, but the point was that there is always going to be another project. Another semester. Another student. It’s more important to think about why you’re doing this work: what are the animating philosophies behind what you’re doing? I’ve tried to give you a glimpse today of the “why” for the Scholars’ Lab.</p>

<p>I encouraged the students earlier to think about their work as opportunities to open up small spaces for more generous, kind, and productive spaces in the academy, to imagine the future they want to see into the world. In the Lab we see our work as part of a larger attempt to shift the culture of the university, both in terms of what graduate training in the humanities can look like but also in terms of what kinds of conversations are acceptable.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/30.png" alt="PHD Plus Splash Page" /></p>

<p>At UVA, we’re plugged into a larger network of like-minded programs working to train graduate students for a broad range of lives and future careers. This program, called <a href="https://phdplus.virginia.edu/index">PHD+</a>, has been instrumental for us in helping to see that the work we’re doing as being part of a larger movement to rethink what graduate education can look like. Thinkers like <a href="https://katinarogers.com">Katina Rogers</a> and <a href="https://www.cathydavidson.com/">Cathy Davidson</a>, both at CUNY, and <a href="https://www.seanmichaelmorris.com/">Sean Michael Morris</a> and <a href="https://www.jessestommel.com/">Jesse Stommel</a>, co-founders of the <a href="https://www.digitalpedagogylab.com/">Digital Pedagogy Lab</a>, have been instrumental for me in seeing the work of the classroom as intimately connected to the work outside it. And, to go back to my point about student voices, we talk about these issues explicitly with our students. We have a session on diverse career options for them, on labor precarity and employment in digital humanities. We’re not solely interested in getting them jobs; we want to make sure that they can find their ways to happy futures no matter the outcome.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-media/dh-pedagogy-and-hope/31.png" alt="Desire path image again." /></p>

<p>So to bring it back to an earlier image and earlier questions - when working on DH pedagogy decisions I’d encourage you to think about this image. I know I will. How are our decisions helping people navigate their own desire paths through the university? Throwing up new barriers for them? Paving new roads? How can we make even small assignments part of larger culture shifts? How might digital humanities pedagogy, in libraries and out of them, make space for these conversations?</p>

<p>That’s my talk. Thanks for listening. I’m happy to talk more about Tron, the Scholars’ Lab, nuts and bolts of digital humanities pedagogy, other opportunities for hope, and anything else you’d like.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
