<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: alt-ac | Brandon Walsh]]></title>
  <link href="http://walshbr.com/categories/alt-ac/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://walshbr.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-10-19T19:12:13+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://walshbr.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[{"name"=>"Brandon Walsh", "url"=>"https://twitter.com/mdo", "email"=>"walsh@virginia.edu"}]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Your Budget Is a Question of Pedagogy and Equity]]></title>
    <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/your-budget-is-a-question-of-pedagogy-and-equity/"/>
    <updated>2020-04-15T11:29:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/your-budget-is-a-question-of-pedagogy-and-equity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Crossposted to the <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/your-budget-is-a-question-of-pedagogy-and-equity">Scholars’ Lab blog</a></em></p>

<p>I finished drafting this post back before the extent of the coronavirus pandemic was becoming known. And now, of course, the impact of the virus around the globe—and on higher education in particular—continues to evolve. So I had been sitting on this post for some time; I wasn’t sure how a rapidly changing landscape of higher education, replete with hiring freezes and bleak budgetary outlooks, might impact these conversations. I’m still uncertain. But I’m publishing this now in the expectation that ethical conversations about budgets as they pertain to students and teaching are likely to become more important now than ever. I’m grateful to <a href="https://mackenziekbrooks.info/">Mackenzie Brooks</a>, <a href="http://literaturegeek.com/">Amanda Visconti</a>, and Elizabeth Fox for reading the post over.</p>

<p>Caveats aside—this post is part of a larger project I’m working on over the course of the year about the intersections of digital humanities pedagogy as it can reflect and enact infrastructural change in higher education. While each post is meant to stand on its own, they do participate in a longer conversation. It might be helpful to explore the <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/year-of-book-blogging-digital-humanities-pedagogy-in-kind/">framing post for the series</a> for context.</p>

<p>I will talk elsewhere about opportunities for pedagogical interventions in the context of credit-bearing courses. For now, I wanted to speak primarily from my own institutional perspective. As the Head of Student Programs for a library-based center for digital research, the teaching that I do tends not to happen in for-credit courses. Instead, my teaching takes place in a range of activities: year-long student fellowships that carry a stipend that I design and administer in collaboration with the rest of the Scholars’ Lab, one-on-one consultations, one-off workshops, and more. Roughly half of my working life is spent on the actual work of theorizing and carrying out teaching. The other half is spent on developing the administrative infrastructure to allow such work to happen, for myself and others. With that in mind, I wanted to pause over the kinds of pedagogical interventions that can be made by people in these kinds of positions—whether we describe them as alt-academic, para-academic, academic, or otherwise. For that reason, the following does not apply so much to teaching in credit bearing courses, though it might offer useful food for thought as it applies to a range of pedagogical situations.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.seanmichaelmorris.com/the-habitus-of-critical-imagination/">Sean Michael Morris</a> refers to a pedagogical habitus, “embodied practice, often uninspected or subterranean to a person’s own thinking about themselves,” that forms the “genetic makeup” of an instructor’s teaching. In this line of thought, pedagogy is not just a practice–it is more properly thought of as your general attitude towards the work of teaching that you do. Put simply, your pedagogy is reflected in every action you take that could potentially affect students and your attitudes towards all such actions. It’s not too much of an exaggeration, I think, to say that with this frame of thinking every action can be considered a pedagogical one. No administrative decision is too small to affect students in some way.</p>

<p>I often point to budgets as the clearest example of how mundane administrative details, seemingly disconnected from the work of the classroom, have profound ramifications for teachers and learners. To put the finest point on it: your budget is a pedagogical issue. It’s also a question of equity. The economic circumstances your program creates or participates in directly affect the kinds of people able to participate in your programs and the work they can do.</p>

<p>Higher education is a time of enormous financial uncertainty for many students. Sara Goldrick-Rab’s work with <a href="https://realcollege.org/">#realcollege</a>, for example, has brought attention to the number of college students that struggle with food and housing insecurity. The situation is often no better for graduate students who, even if their programs offer tuition remission and stipends, are frequently forced to live in poverty. B. Mano’s <a href="https://thetech.com/2019/10/31/mit-grad-students-poverty">piece on their particular circumstances</a> at MIT sheds light, in particular, on how specific institutional policies can intersect with national labor and immigration law to produce especially dire situations for students. In these circumstances, any decision that we make as administrators can have dire consequences for the lives of the students around us.</p>

<p>Of course, every situation is different and subject to different pressures. Many institutions doing digital work simply don’t have any budget or funding at all. If you’re in a position like this, it might feel difficult to imagine how you could structure financial circumstances for your students in a more equitable manner when you’re still trying to find any kind of firm structure at all. In what follows I don’t mean to propose the perfect as the enemy of the good. Instead, I’d suggest taking the following as opportunities to examine where you’re at in the hopes of finding a way towards better outcomes—whatever “better” means for you and your circumstances. At the very least, I hope that the following discussion can supply resources and questions to use as we all try to advocate for better labor conditions for students.</p>

<p>Four pedagogical questions that you might ask of the student side of your budget are:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Does it exist?</li>
  <li>Is it stable?</li>
  <li>Is it transparent?</li>
  <li>Is it what my students need?</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="does-it-exist">Does it exist?</h2>

<p>Are students a part of your budget? If not, why? In Elissa Frankle’s ignite talk entitled “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0niIskfLpdE&amp;list=PLl7V7chP13lBSnSyYpEp6g6lpu7pZftrC">Pay Your F-ing Interns</a>,” she describes how unpaid internships reinforce whiteness and homogenous, privileged communities in museum workers. Frankle goes on: “We may say that we value diversity, that of course we want to treat our workers well, but do our core documents and budgets reflect that fact?” Our decisions about infrastructure, at their best, should reflect what our organizations believe in. A first useful question you can ask of your budget, then, is, whether and to what degree your work with students rises to the level of budget lines and conversations during allocations.</p>

<p>What you can pay is, of course, a local issue. But it is worth questioning whether your current payment practices are the result of habit or limitations. At UVA, we are subject to a <a href="https://provost.virginia.edu/wage-authorization-academic-areas">range of policies</a> that impact what we can offer students. It’s important to know what these are at your institution so that you can answer statements like “we can only pay X” with “actually, the policy states we can pay X+Y.” I often find state and local policies as a useful first tool when advocating for students, and they can also provide common language for working with financial administrators elsewhere in your institution who might be more removed from the day-to-day lives of your students.</p>

<p>Even if you’re not instituting something as formal as an internship or an hourly position, it’s worth considering how much unpaid time you’re asking of your students. Asking students to drive visiting speakers to events, for example, might appear negligible for the amount of effort it requires. But this small ask still takes a student’s time, time that they could be applying to their own work, to another paid position, or to personal needs.</p>

<p>In short, recognize the economic impact you are likely already having on students and decide whether you can do better. Recognize what you ask of them, first, and second ask what you can pay them.</p>

<h2 id="is-it-stable">Is it stable?</h2>

<p>Students need to be able to plan their finances. If they cannot, only students from affluent backgrounds will be able to make decisions about their educations in the face of such uncertainty. If we want to design programs for students that will be as inclusive as possible, we need to strive for better stability in what we can offer. I am well aware that stable budgets are a luxury in most institutions, including my own. This is especially true in digital humanities, where people and organizations have successfully lobbied IMLS, CLIR, the Mellon Foundation, and the NEH ODH for substantial grants to support their work.</p>

<p>Grant funding can provide valuable experience for students and resources for paying them for their labor. And at some institutions these avenues might be the only ones available for funding the work of you and your students. Grants come with the disadvantage, of course, that they will eventually run their course. Soft money can provide useful supplemental resources for employing students, but the associated instability can cause long-term issues for students and staff. For example, a term-limited grant-funded student position might be listed as one year with year extension contingent on successful performance. In such a situation, the student or postdoctoral worker will spend a significant portion of their time planning and searching for what comes next when the grant-funded position ends. Extensions to a contracted position might, of course, be more dependent on successful lobbying for continued funding than on faith in an already carefully vetted candidate. But it’s still worth considering the real-life ramifications these positions can have for candidates.</p>

<p>It is worth noting the benefits of stable student programs founded on hard money. Through a combination of advocacy and strategic planning, the Lab has been fortunate enough to offer two stable fellowships for several years now. Praxis is completing its ninth year, and our Graduate Fellowship in Digital Humanities is in its thirteenth year. This means that students can plan on these programs as possibilities for them as they plot out not just their research agenda during their time with us, but also their plans for applying for supplemental funding. It is truly unfortunate that we cannot accept everyone who applies, but we work hard to try to bring as many people as we can into our community. It takes time for research agendas to develop, and students need time to decide if such things are right for them. The Scholars’ Lab has application cycles that run virtually all year long for its various programs, and students discuss their intention to apply well in advance of when they are eligible to do so.</p>

<p>Stable programs lead to better support for students as well. Supporting students requires time and energy from staff, no matter how experienced and skilled they might be. Thoughtful and considerate planning that includes student support as part of the regular workload for staff ensures that teaching and pedagogy will not become afterthoughts. Even if suddenly presented with the financial option to take on new students, one should ask if they can be supported.</p>

<p>Good teaching follows from well-supported and energized staff who are empowered to decide if they have the bandwidth to take on new students. Good learning follows from students who can make informed decisions about their lives and have the time and space to commit to learning.</p>

<h2 id="is-it-transparent">Is it transparent?</h2>

<p>I often find that students have received no real information about the systems by which their finances get processed. On the one hand, this is understandable—university budgeting processes are byzantine, and information about payment processing might seem like a means to an end and less crucial to students’ day-to-day lives. But providing knowledge about these systems can help students plan their own lives more capably. I have found it helpful to make sure students are aware of a range of different components related to how their payments are processed:</p>

<ul>
  <li>University payroll calendars</li>
  <li>The length of time it takes for a payment to process</li>
  <li>Whether a payment will be taxed up front or not</li>
  <li>Whether a certain amount of payment during the year triggers automatic taxation</li>
  <li>When payments are likely to come through, how often, and in what amount</li>
</ul>

<p>Each of these elements can help students plan their time and finances. In addition, I’ve found that it can be difficult for us to track when something goes wrong in a payment that we’ve issued. We know when we issue it, and we find out if a student gets their funds. But there are many steps along the way. With many, many links in the administrative chain before the money actually gets dispersed to students, there are many places where things could go wrong. So I have regular appointments on my calendar when I ask students to make sure that they’ve been paid as expected. I often find students are really patient and willing to wait even if it appears that something might be amiss. But, as payments take time to process, I would rather we be in constant communication and transparent about where things stand so that we can reduce the burden on students already living in states of financial precarity. A transparent budgeting and dispersal process is a more ethical one.</p>

<h2 id="is-it-what-they-need">Is it what they need?</h2>

<p>Lastly, any administrative process can be enhanced by student input. As is often the case with teaching, I find the best way to grow is to ask students for their insights. Put simply, unless you were a student <em>very</em> recently, you probably do not know what sorts of pressures your students are subject to. Unless you recently lived paycheck to paycheck, it might be easy to forget the sort of financial precarity that a number of our students live under. And it is impossible for any one person to have personal experience that tracks with every possible student experience in the world. In short, be wary of invoking Students with a capital ‘s’, as one broad monolithic community. In order to take a broad, intersectional approach to your teaching and administration, you must talk with students themselves. They are experts on their own situations, and talking with your students about their needs can help to inform your decisions. They’ll learn more about how the university works, and the teaching and pedagogy you can offer will be enhanced as it more closely matches the real-world experiences of your community.</p>

<p>We address this same point in the <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/student-programs-charter/">Scholars’ Lab Student Programs Charter</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We teach in public, meaning that we talk openly about our pedagogical process. When possible, we write about it as well. If something is not working, we will change it and adapt based on the needs of the students and our colleagues. Accordingly, we expect our students to talk and write about their work and the learning process for them, to engage in the experience, and help us shape a pedagogical experience that works for them.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>To engage your students directly in conversations like those above is to treat them as peers, as collaborators in the learning process in all of its messiness. Details like these might seem removed from teaching or overly specific. But they have material effects on the day-to-live lives of your student collaborators. A conversation with a student about how the uncertainties around a particular fellowship payment, for example, helped us to understand that a different distribution calendar would offer students more cushion if payments were delayed. We wouldn’t have gotten the idea had we not talked with the student directly about their needs.</p>

<p>As mentioned above, it can be difficult to balance these conversations against the realities of trying to do this work. We don’t live in a perfect world, and we’re all working with limited resources. Talking with students directly can be a way of sussing out whether your budgetary situation is operating for them and their lives and how it might work better for them. Students can help us all find our way to more equitable pedagogies and budgets that reflect them. You cannot do everything, but you might be able to adjust a few things. In the current climate of higher education, when many are faced with hiring freezes, across-the-board budget cuts, the prospect of layoffs, and withdrawn job offers, such conversations might seem small. But small decisions can matter in big ways for your students. And they can help us care for our vulnerable community members during chaotic times.</p>

<p>Resources for further reading on the topic:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://humtech.ucla.edu/news/a-student-collaborators-bill-of-rights/">UCLA Student Collaborators Bill of Rights</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1bKpiqX9LPGJsKJsLopFW5vvEgwS3koXZJQU3nv-iuWw/edit">Postdoctoral Bill of Rights</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.dhwogem.org/">Women and Gender Minorities in Digital Humanities group</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Year Of Book Blogging: Digital Humanities Pedagogy in Kind]]></title>
    <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/year-of-book-blogging-digital-humanities-pedagogy-in-kind/"/>
    <updated>2020-01-28T09:41:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/year-of-book-blogging:-digital-humanities-pedagogy-in-kind</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Crossposted to the <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/year-of-book-blogging-digital-humanities-pedagogy-in-kind">Scholars’ Lab blog</a></em></p>

<p>Amanda, Ammon, and I have been discussing our plans for the upcoming year of blogging. While last year’s blogging push was invigorating and exciting, we wanted things to be slightly different in the coming year. In particular, we’ve been talking about wanting more continuity in the things we publish. Speaking for myself, it often felt like I was blogging just in time and on deadline. Some good things came out of that work, but I liked the idea of putting just a little more thinking into the project ahead of time so that I could blog around a central topic for the year. Amanda and Ammon have been incredibly helpful in talking about all this with me.</p>

<p>Truthfully, I’ve been feeling the lack of a large writing project lately. After my <a href="http://doi.org/10.18130/V3R27G">dissertation</a>, I worked on a <a href="http://walshbr.com/textanalysiscoursebook">text analysis coursebook</a> with Sarah Horowitz, a faculty colleague at W&amp;L. I adore blogging, but I feel the lure of a large project I can chip away at over the next year and that can draw together my energy. Am I talking about writing a book? Maybe? We’ll see. I’m certainly not the first person to write a book in public, but the idea of revealing what I was aiming for made me feel a little uneasy. What if my ideas didn’t cohere (I tend to write in multiple sections of a project at once)? What if I didn’t actually produce anything or finish? What if the project turned out to be empty (easier to dismiss a single blog post)? Does what I’m interested in working on even need to be a book? What do I mean by book - is it a published thing with a press or just something big that lives online?</p>

<p>I had initially planned on just quietly blogging around a cluster of ideas over the next year and then potentially revealing at the end that they were part of a coherent project in progress. But as I started to write the first post on imposter syndrome (seriously)- and in the midst of talking with my students about the very topic - I thought I should put my money where my mouth is from the outset. So here you go! Here are my notes on the large, ongoing, multifaceted writing project that I’ll be trying to cohere together over the course of the next year. If it winds up being something I try to actually turn into a book so be it. If it just winds up being a series of blog posts, then I’ll at least be happy to have written about topics I felt were urgent.</p>

<p>One last note on process: in my PhD program we did an activity where we repeatedly drafted a fantasy table of contents for our dissertation. No abstracts necessary at that stage - just a title for the project and titles for the chapters. I found it enormously useful as a means for thinking through the different shapes a large writing project could take. That’s essentially what I do below. I try on a provisional title for the large project and take a spin at some rough chapter ideas. Since this is a blogging endeavor to begin with, within each chapter title I offer some titles, topics, or questions for blog posts that might intersect with it. I flag a few thinkers and discourses that I see this all drawing upon and engaging with. I also offer a few beginning thoughts towards a topic (nothing surprising, if you’ve read other posts by me on here). My arguments always tend to emerge in the process of writing, though, so it will be interesting to see how this develops over the course of a year. So take this for what it is - a sketch of a sketch of things I find urgent and will be trying to attend to over the coming months. Stay tuned for a look into my messy process.</p>

<p>I thought I might start by close reading this provisional, draft-y title as a way of getting at the ideas I want to explore. For now, at least, I’m thinking about it as called <em>Digital Humanities Pedagogy in Kind</em>.</p>

<h2 id="digital-humanities-pedagogy-in-kind">Digital Humanities Pedagogy in Kind</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Our pedagogies model and reflect the kind of academic community we want to see in the  world. Academia is toxic in numerous ways. Teaching and the ways we theorize and practice it can be interventions in the culture around us. The project hopes to connect classroom practice broadly construed with the kinds of infrastructural changes they reflect and enact.</li>
  <li>Kindness is at the core of the project. I’m trying to formulate a theory of DH pedagogy that is, at its core, one about developing a less toxic and more affirmative space for students in higher education. It’s about developing empathy and kindness as teachers and how DH can (or cannot?) offer us the space to do so within and against the infrastructures of academia.</li>
  <li>Finally, at least in this title, I wanted to get at the idea of paying a debt in goods and services rather than in cash. For starters, I like this formulation because it draws in a range of topics. What do we owe our students? It raises the specter of student debt. And it draws in Paulo Freire and questions of neoliberal, zero-sum teaching. Is digital humanities fundamentally bound up in neoliberal politics of the university? Yes. How can we develop an ethical, just, and progressive pedagogy anyway and in the face of this?</li>
</ol>

<p>A starting list of thinkers I imagine the project in dialogue with: <a href="https://www.cathydavidson.com/books/the-new-education/">Cathy Davidson</a>, <a href="https://www.dukeupress.edu/putting-the-humanities-phd-to-work">Katina Rogers</a>, <a href="https://jhupbooks.press.jhu.edu/title/generous-thinking">Kathleen Fitzpatrick</a>, <a href="https://mith.umd.edu/advocacy-design-moving-theory-practice-part-1/">Jeremy Boggs and Purdom Lindblad</a>, <a href="https://www.halperta.com/">Hannah Alpert-Abrams</a>, <a href="http://akhenrichs.com/blog/">Amanda Henrichs</a>, <a href="https://www.roopikarisam.com/">Roopika Risam</a>, <a href="http://saragoldrickrab.com/">Sara Goldrick-Rab</a>; <a href="https://urgencyofteachers.com/">Jesse Stommel and Sean Michael Morris</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/finiteeyes/status/1217175390491295744">Matthew Cheney</a>, <a href="https://hybridpedagogy.org/author/catherine/">Catherine Denial</a>, bell hooks, Paulo Freire; <a href="https://thedigitalpress.org/failing-gloriously/">Shawn Graham</a>; <a href="https://digitalpedagogy.mla.hcommons.org/">Rebecca Frost Davis, Matthew K. Gold, Katherine D. Harris, and Jentery Sayers</a>; <a href="https://briancroxall.net/">Brian Croxall</a>; <a href="https://artepublicopress.com/carolina-villarroel/">Carolina Villarroel</a>, <a href="https://www.uh.edu/class/spanish/faculty/baeza-ventura_g/">Gabriela Baeza Ventura</a>, <a href="https://mith.umd.edu/people/person/trevor-munoz/">Trevor Muñoz</a> (and more). Significant projects that I’d examine and reflect on would include the <a href="https://humtech.ucla.edu/news/a-student-collaborators-bill-of-rights/">UCLA Student Collaborators’ Bill of Rights</a>, the <a href="https://archive.mith.umd.edu/offthetracks/recommendations/index.html">Collaborators Bill of Rights</a>, <a href="https://futuresinitiative.org/">The Futures Initiative</a>, <a href="https://www.hastac.org/">HASTAC</a>, <a href="https://digitalpedagogy.mla.hcommons.org/">Digital Pedagogy in the Humanities</a>,  <a href="https://iliads.org/">ILiADS</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/generousthinking?src=hash">#generousthinking</a>, <a href="https://hcommons.org/deposits/item/hc:26741/">The Postdoctoral Laborers Bill of Rights</a>, the <a href="https://hcommons.org/groups/academic-job-market-support-network/">Academic Job Market Support Network</a>, <a href="https://aadhum.umd.edu/">AADHum</a>, and <a href="http://usldhrecovery.uh.edu/">USLDH</a>, among others. In my mind I want to tie together questions of higher education reform, critical digital pedagogy, and DH pedagogy. I’m certain I’m leaving people and projects out in this short and initial list - such is the nature of blogging about a work in progress. I’ll be working on a Zotero bibliography that collects these resources for myself and others as I continue reading around about the important work already being done in these areas.</p>

<p>I imagine the project offering a theory and praxis of DH teaching and pedagogy - very broadly construed, as it tries to develop a theory of pedagogy far beyond the classroom -  as an intervention in academic culture. DH pedagogy offers a number of great interventions to begin with – meditations on failure, teaching as activism, rethinking the professional futures of humanities students – and I’d like to join those conversations with others from critical digital pedagogy that emphasize radically student-centered teaching. With these frameworks, I’ll focus the work on the conditions of being a DH student – the material labor and working circumstances, the conditions of professional development and career prospects, the intersections of administrative decisions and the economic conditions of student life. I think doing so will help to give a better sense of the lives at the core of DH pedagogy as they intersect with the administrative infrastructures of DH. And perhaps ultimately the project aims to argue for a pedagogy that teaches with and alongside students and with kindness that happens together (a lot of echoes of Kathleen Fitzpatrick’s <em>Generous Thinking</em> here).</p>

<p>That’s where I’m at right now at least. Lots of loose threads and jumbled thoughts but at least a place to get started. One unresolved question for me is what makes this an argument about DH and not just pedagogy in general? Is it DH just because I am a DH person? Or does DH specifically have something to say about this? Is the DH audience, in particular, a good one for this? Or not? Things I’ll want to think further about in the future for certain. Without further ado, though, I’ll close with the draft table of contents and associated blog topics / questions. The arc of the project as I’m thinking it at the moment moves from micro to macro, from the classroom to larger questions of professional climate.</p>

<h2 id="draft-table-of-contents-and-ideas">Draft Table of Contents and Ideas</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Introduction
    <ol>
      <li>Where does DH teaching happen?</li>
      <li>Where does infrastructural change happen?</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>Classroom experience
    <ol>
      <li>Kindness and generosity as skills that require training</li>
      <li>Pedagogies of listening</li>
      <li>How do we make the classroom a space where students can be sheltered from the academy and also create the conditions to transform it a la <a href="https://jwernimont.com/">Jacqueline Wernimont</a>?</li>
      <li>What are the spaces of teaching, for DH in particular?</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>Labor
    <ol>
      <li>DH students as DH teachers</li>
      <li>Neoliberal DH pedagogies</li>
      <li>Expanding on the UCLA Student Collaborators’ Bill of Rights</li>
      <li>Precarious labor and the labor of teaching</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>Infrastructure
    <ol>
      <li>As it impacts pedagogy and student life and teaching in particular; how do the small decisions we make at the level of administration reflect out pedagogies?</li>
      <li>How can pedagogy be enacted beyond the classroom? How can we take teacherly actions as administrators?</li>
      <li>How can those teacherly administrative actions address issues of precarity among the student population?</li>
      <li>Your budget is a question of pedagogy and justice</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>Profession
    <ol>
      <li>Imposter syndrome. Where does imposter syndrome start for students? How can we address it?</li>
      <li>Professional Development / Career Paths</li>
      <li>Professional Imposters</li>
      <li>Small changes / big changes</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>Conclusion – on inclusivity
    <ol>
      <li>How do we invite students into the profession and into higher education in a way that makes their voices heard and valued?</li>
      <li>How can we ensure students are valued in online spaces? Or welcomed in spaces of open peer review?</li>
      <li>Where to go from here?</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Seems like plenty to go on for now. Now to get blogging!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Digital Humanities Job Talks: Some Case Studies]]></title>
    <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/digital-humanities-job-talks-some-case-studies/"/>
    <updated>2019-12-16T11:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/digital-humanities-job-talks:-some-case-studies</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Co-authored with <a href="http://amandavisconti.com/">Amanda Visconti</a>. Crossposted to the <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/digital-humanities-job-talks/">Scholars’ Lab blog</a> and <a href="http://literaturegeek.com/2019/12/16/digital-humanities-job-talks">Amanda’s personal blog</a>.</em></p>

<p>To follow up on sharing and annotating <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/dh-cover-letters/">our past cover letters</a> for DHy academic jobs, in this post we share how we’ve thought through past job talk prompts and the experience of giving the resulting presentations. (To learn more about Brandon’s practical workflow to drafting and memorizing talks, check out his <a href="http://walshbr.com/blog/dh-public-speaking/">post on DH public speaking</a>! To learn about Amanda’s workflow, prod her to finally publish a now-too-long post about DH and public speaking anxiety before 2020 ends…)</p>

<p>Before you dive in, though, you may wish to read our October 2019 blog post <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/dh-cover-letters/">“How We Talk and Write about DH Jobs”</a> if you haven’t already. Well intentioned academic job advice can be and often is harmful—so in that post’s “Slightly Better Job Advice, Take Two” section, we discuss how we’re trying to share what we know about job searches in a way that affirms any readers as valued peers and scholars, just as they are. We hope sharing our experiences here can be useful and not overly prescriptive. Our perspectives are shaped by our own particular contexts, and we trust that readers will know their own circumstances - and what will work for them - better than we do. With this in mind, we share the following in the hopes that resources and transparency about our own thinking on the process of preparing for job presentations can help others getting started.</p>

<h2 id="brandon">Brandon:</h2>

<p>I should note outright that my experience pertains to giving job talks for what might be called alternative academic positions in DH working in libraries. And, while I have seen a number of presentations by job candidates for a range of library positions, I have always wondered how my own background and experiences affect how I evaluate candidate presentations. For example, I do not have a library degree: I did my graduate work in literature before coming to work in libraries, and this different orientation undoubtedly shapes how I view job presentations and prepare for them. When applying for any position, it’s a good idea to talk with someone who is familiar with that discipline or field so that they can give you a sense of the generic expectations that your audience will bring to your presentation. I would not take any of my thoughts on job talks as prescriptive in the least. Your mileage will vary. But I remember my own experiences as a student felt largely as though I was trying to approach a job presentation without any context or sense of how to think about them. Hopefully seeing how I do so can help someone in the same position formulate their own approach.</p>

<p>We’re often raised to think of writing and, by association, presentations, as having a clear and direct point. But, to me, the difficulty with alt-ac job talks is that they often seem to address a number of different issues at once. When I prepare one, I try to think of the presentation as working to convey a few things:</p>

<ul>
  <li>my response to a prompt</li>
  <li>my experience</li>
  <li>my understanding of the job</li>
  <li>my vision for the position</li>
</ul>

<p>You can find the <a href="https://walshbr.com/blog/in-out-across-with/">job talk</a> for my current position as Head of Student Programs in the Scholars’ Lab on my website. As I discuss elements of that job talk below, readers might find that full text helpful for context.</p>

<h3 id="prompts">Prompts</h3>

<p>Many positions that ask you to give a presentation will also give you some kind of prompt for the job talk. To a greater or lesser degree depending on the audience, they will expect you to respond to it. For my position as Head of Student Programs in the Scholars’ Lab, I was given a prompt that broadly addressed education in digital humanities:</p>
<div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>What does a student (from undergraduate to doctoral levels) need to learn or experience in order to add “DH” to his or her skill set? Is that an end or a means of graduate education? Can short-term digital assignments in discipline-specific courses go beyond “teaching with technology”? Why not refer everyone to online tutorials? Are there risks for doctoral students or the untenured in undertaking digital projects? Drawing on your own experience, and offering examples or demonstrations of digital research projects, pedagogical approaches, or initiatives or organizations that you admire, make a case for a vision of collaborative education in advanced digital scholarship in the arts and humanities.
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>I had a lot of feelings about this prompt, as you can imagine. As Amanda mentions below, prompts are often abstract and vague because they are not written with any particular candidate in mind. By trying to offer something for everyone, they sometimes seem intentionally amorphous so that anyone can find a way to latch onto the material. But this means that a prompt can go anywhere, really, and trying to devise a response to it can feel very difficult. So my first point of advice is simply that the difficulty with the prompt is not you! It’s a strange genre, and recognizing this can hopefully help begin to mitigate feelings of imposter syndrome.</p>

<p>In my case, I remember feeling pretty convinced that every question on my prompt could be its own talk. There was just so much to work with, so many topics to address! In the face of this issue, I explicitly framed my own talk as only responding to the first question listed - “What does a student (from undergraduate to doctoral levels) need to learn or experience in order to add “DH” to his or her skill set?” I thought responding to all pieces of the prompt was an impossible task, and I leaned into a talk that did more with less. For what it’s worth, I remember one person approaching me after the presentation and softly noting that I had not responded to all of the questions in the prompt (but they still appreciated the talk). Fair enough, but I did what made the most sense to me. Noting the parts of the prompt you will or won’t address can be a useful way of articulating the intentionality of your response for the audience, and it can also be useful for people in the audience who might not be as familiar with the text of the prompt. After all, in an open job talk you are likely to have some members of the search committee in attendance as well as those who might be more removed from the search process.</p>

<p>Like Amanda describes, I framed my response to the prompt as a critique of it. In essence, I argued that framing DH education as about acquiring a set of skills would undercut the prospect for DH pedagogy to make real, transformative change in the lives of students and institutions. There were a few reasons I took such a perpendicular approach to the question. I had worked in the Scholars’ Lab as a student, so I had some sense of the philosophy of the institution at which I was interviewing. I knew at least a portion of the room would be open to the kind of critique I wanted to offer. For better or worse, I also wanted the talk to show the kind of hire I would be. In other words, I didn’t want to present myself as having one set of views at the interview stage only to be hired and reveal myself to have a set of opinions and beliefs that wouldn’t fit with the institution. If the search committee was looking for someone who really thought of DH education in terms of skills acquisition, I was not that person. They would not be happy with me in this position, and I would not be happy trying to act in it. Better, I thought, to get it all out there. Like Amanda says below, it’s worth noting that not all candidates have the comfort and privilege of being able to make a decision like this as part of the interview process. The approach worked for me, but it might not work for others in different situations. You best know your own circumstances. I do think it’s worth trying to use the hiring process to suss out in small ways the kind of environment in which you would be employed and whether you can be happy there, but you don’t necessarily need to use your job talk to do it.</p>

<h3 id="experiences">Experiences</h3>

<p>The audience for a job talk is going to show up to learn about you and your qualifications in relation to the job for which they’ve brought you in. This can be tricky, as in a public talk the audience will contain a diverse range of people. The search committee can be expected to have spent time with your CV and cover letter, but, while those documents are typically circulated in advance, you cannot assume that everyone at a public talk will have given the same attention to those documents. So, while you don’t want to wholly reiterate your background, you do need to share some of your qualifications. I think of this as an opportunity to contextualize some of your experiences in a richer way so that your work can play for the whole audience regardless of how familiar they are with your work.</p>

<p>By richer context, I mean that a job talk is a good place to take the things listed on a CV, select two or three, and deploy them in service of a larger vision for the position (more on that below). What did you learn from working with X? How does Y connect to the kinds of work you will be doing at institution Z? I often find it useful to pick a few things from my background and ask “so what?” of them repeatedly until I feel that they stand on their own as a self-reflective moment in the talk. You can use an otherwise boring and rote listing of experiences to show an audience <strong>how</strong> you will work in a position by reflecting on the work you have already done. In the Scholars’ Lab talk, I talked about my work at <a href="https://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/">WLUDH</a>, a coursebook I was co-writing with a faculty collaborator, and my experiences with curriculum design. But examples like these wouldn’t stand on their own - I thought of them as evidence in the larger argument I was making about how I think about DH teaching. Another way to think about all this: in an essay, you are likely to cite other authors or texts as you make your argument. In job talks I think of the evidence as potentially drawing from either your own experiences or other example projects/texts in DH. By weaving these together, your job talk can show both your personal qualifications and your sense of how your work connects to the broader field.</p>

<h3 id="understanding">Understanding</h3>

<p>To some degree, the audience will expect you to signal that you know what the job will entail. It’s always difficult to know exactly what the day to day life at a place will be like, and most of the time a candidate won’t actually make it to the job talk stage if their understanding of the position is in question. But conveying your understanding of the position can help nonetheless. I often tell students to think of it as a roleplaying challenge. You have imperfect knowledge of what the position will be like, but you have evidence from websites, projects, descriptions, and postings. Search committees are always trying to imagine each candidate into the position. Why not meet them halfway and start to imagine yourself into the position in your job talk? There are, of course, ways to do this poorly - I would not go into a talk saying “I will entirely transform everything in my first week. Only I have the solutions to your problems.” You will never have all the answers. Furthermore, positions always have pressures and needs that are difficult to perceive from the outside, and it can be useful to acknowledge that. I like to offer this formulation: “Given that I know you are working on X, I would take my experiences with Y to work towards Z with you all.” Syntactically it’s not actually a formula I would recommend, but as an exercise in thinking it can get you in the direction of good thinking about yourself in relation to a job. In that way, you’re making transparent the kind of thought process that you will bring to the position. And you’re helping the search committee by shaping the imaginative exercise of hiring for them.</p>

<p>To do this well, you’ll need to do research on the position but also the institution. If the position has existed before, what kind of work did they previously do? What kind of projects did they take on? Does the job description appear to be different in some way from that previous body of work? The institution can also offer clues: libraries, small liberal arts colleges, and cultural heritage institutions (to name a few) each carry with them certain assumptions about the work that they do, and these categories can offer evidence for you as you start to determine what kind of work the place values. You might also look at projects undertaken, grants and new initiatives that might be in process, recent hires, and the like. Some institutions might even offer explicit statements of values that you can explore. The Scholars’ Lab, for example, has published a series of <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/charter/">charters</a> describing how we think about our work. I had the benefit for my presentation of having worked with the Scholars’ Lab as a student. So I knew something of how they thought of themselves, and I similarly tried to frame my interest in working with DH students towards progressive, transformative reform in higher education. But I only knew the Scholars’ Lab from the student’s perspective - I had to make a lot of educated guesses about how they thought of their work and their students.</p>

<p>One further thought: applying for jobs can be especially scary as a student. It’s all too easy to think, “I am a PhD student in literature! What do I know about institutional collaboration for DH education?” But you probably know more than you think! You’ve likely experienced a number of these issues from the student side, so you actually have valuable experiences with them. Many administrators are desperate to get student voices on a range of issues, and your direct experience can provide a useful perspective when combined with research about the other sorts of stakes, pressures, and questions that the position might engage with. It’s just a matter of imagining yourself from the other side.</p>

<h3 id="vision">Vision</h3>

<p>This point is not one that I’m sure is required by the generic conventions of general DH staff jobs. Lots of people leave it off. But it is an element that I often think about, and I know that, of the job presentations that I’ve attended, all of the ones I considered the best included some sense of a vision for the work they will do. I was trained that a piece - be it an essay or a talk - should have an argument to it. So it’s difficult for me to imagine preparing a job talk that doesn’t also offer an argument, a philosophy, a vision for the work. In the context of the Scholars’ Lab talk, I explicitly framed the position I was applying for as someone who thinks past and beyond the prompt I was given. This was my closing sentence:</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Foremost, then, I see the Head of Graduate Programs as someone who takes the lists, documents, and curricula that I have discussed and connects them to the people that serve them and that they are meant to speak to. This person is one who builds relationships, who navigates the prepositions of my title.
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>I presented a vision of the position as one that fundamentally cared about the people and their development more than the skills associated with digital humanities. For me at least, it’s important that a talk say something, even in a genre as strange as a job presentation. “Vision” can be a big baggy term with little meaning to it. But you might approach it by asking a series of questions of yourself - why is this position important? what do I see as the fundamental role of this position? What are the top three verbs I would associate with this position? How can I frame this position as being vital to the mission of the institution? A job description answers the “what” of a position - what about the “why”? In trying to work in a sense of your philosophy for the work, you’re helping a search committee to further imagine what kind of a colleague you would be. I think it will also make for a more engaging job talk. And that job talk is also likely to be easier to write if you’re engaged with the topic of it!</p>

<p>One last note on DH / alt-ac public speaking. In some disciplines it is common to read your talk. Job presentations often seem to be done from notes instead. I try to operate somewhere in the middle. For my longer presentations I write my talk, memorize as much as I can, and then give some version of it more or less off the cuff but with the talk in front of me for reference. The result is something that is bloggable, has a shape to it, is more engaging than reading from a paper, but more polished than a presentation fully off the cuff. I’ve written about this elsewhere if you want more detail about <a href="https://walshbr.com/blog/dh-public-speaking/">my process</a> for preparing for talks. It feels a bit idiosyncratic, but it could work for you as well.</p>

<h2 id="amanda">Amanda:</h2>

<p>My job talk thoughts are biased toward the roles I’ve given a candidate’s talk for—tenure-track faculty roles (interdisciplinary lab; library with digital humanities focus) and the SLab co-director role (library staff). You might also wish to check out talks from others who’ve applied to related DHy and library roles for more approaches—<a href="https://readywriting.org/faculty-development/faculty-development-for-the-21st-century-and-beyond/">Lee Skallerup Bessette</a>, <a href="http://celestesharpe.com/onward/">Celeste Tuong Vy Sharpe</a>, and <a href="https://chrisbourg.wordpress.com/2015/07/12/infrastructure-and-culture-a-job-talk/">Chris Bourg</a>—or visit the <a href="https://hcommons.org/groups/academic-job-market-support-network/documents/">Academic Job Market Support Network</a> on Humanities Commons, a forum created by Hannah Alpert-Abrams where folks have uploaded a variety of humanities-related job materials.</p>

<h3 id="responding-to-job-talk-prompts-in-general">Responding to job talk prompts, in general</h3>

<p>You’ll likely be given a prompt to reply to via your talk. In both of the talks shared below, I took a mild risk in explaining why I was responding a bit differently than probably expected to each prompt. I’ll talk about the privileges that allowed me to take these small risks below; if you do not have those privileges, you’ll probably want to respond more directly to prompts than I did, yet still with some changes from how you might answer the prompt if, for example, someone asked you the same thing during Q&amp;A or a panel interview. That is: a job talk prompt is intended to be something that each candidate should be able to answer, and is thus often fairly abstracted and open to interpretation. Sometimes, creating a question that will work for all candidates results in a franken-prompt containing multiple questions.</p>

<p>This might just be a question of how you frame your response to yourself, but my recommendation is to not treat this as you would an essay question on a test: no one is scoring you for explicitly mentioning or responding to the letter of each question in a prompt. An explicit answer to all portions of a prompt can be fine, but it can also make for a poorly structured, hard to listen to talk. I’ve found it more useful to use the prompt as a prompt, rather than as a question—that is, a suggestion of topics your audience might want to know your thoughts on. (In combination with the HR-approved job ad, it might offer more specific clues to local contexts or challenges you could ask about…) I try to give a talk that shares both the philosophies guiding my professional practice and very specific examples from my past work as illustrations. What your audience may remember is whether your talk presented you as 1) someone up to the job’s tasks, and 2) someone who would be a good and healthy addition to the local community. I’m guessing most people won’t even notice, much less care, if your talk isn’t an explicit response to the prompt.</p>

<p>Below, I’ll discuss how I worked through a response to the prompts for two of my past successful job talks, and then comment on the structure and contents of each talk.</p>

<h3 id="scholars-lab-managing-director-talk">Scholars’ Lab Managing Director Talk</h3>
<p>You can read the full text and slides of this talk <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/disrupt-the-humanities-managing-director-job-talk/">here</a>.</p>

<p>The talk prompt was:</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>The digital has the potential to be a disruptive force in humanities scholarship, giving scholars the means to critique, reimagine, and transform ideas, theories, material artifacts, and even interpersonal relationships. Using examples from your own collaborations with faculty, graduate students, and staff, please discuss how this disruption can be successfully embodied in scholarly inquiry, as well as in the cultivation of people and organizations.
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>I was recruited to apply to this job while working in a comfortable role (tenure-track library faculty) with some stellar colleagues and local resources, so it was safe for me to take some risks in my interview. Because paying my rent did not depend on receiving a job offer, I was able to pay more attention to whether the role would be good for me, to be more open about my values and what I wanted in a workplace. So when something in the prompt made me uncomfortable, I decided I wanted to speak to that from the very start of my talk. This turned out well, but could have gone badly, had I failed to convince the audience of the worth of my perspective, or offended the folks who wrote the prompt (assumedly, these were the folks on my search committee and/or folks I’d be reporting through).</p>

<p>The prompt wasn’t explicitly positioning “disruption” as a positive force, but that assumption felt at least implicit enough (disruption allowing reform, wanting that to be “successful”) that I was uncomfortable not speaking specifically to the problems with that. (Part of my reaction was from past experience giving a job talk at a “demo or die” pro-language-of-disruption institution, and my discomfort about how that place’s mixture of amazing colleagues but also very shiny resources temporarily pushed me more toward more disregard for the harms of disruption.) I’ve learned that most terms invoke both positive and negative possibilities:</p>

<p>Valuing openness does harm to cultural practices intended for limited access (see e.g. <a href="https://localcontexts.org/tk-labels/">Traditional Knowledge labels’</a> approach to this issue)
Speaking at a highly abstracted level about “diversity” or “social justice” can disadvantage acting on specific harms including racism and classism.
In Data Feminism, Catherine D’Ignazio and Lauren Klein discuss a number of terms that connote “imagined objectivity” and alternative terms that better “strengthen real objectivity”, e.g. “ethics” =&gt; “justice”, “bias” =&gt; “oppression”, “fairness” =&gt; “equity” (I learned this from Neil Selwyn’s <a href="https://data-smart-schools.net/2019/02/03/data-feminism-introductory-thoughts/">review of their book</a>)</p>

<p>I want to avoid the harm often done in the name of “disruption” treated as a context-less good. And I knew that Scholars’ Lab had a history of publicly valuing many of the same things I valued, e.g. from reading the <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/charter/">staff charter</a>, and appreciating staff’s tweets and conference talks. So my approach wasn’t actually a huge risk, but enough had recently changed in terms of the lab and library’s staff and work that if those values had shifted unbeknownst to me, I would probably be able to choose not to work there without harm to my livelihood. And I was applying to co-direct the lab, so there was more space to safely share thinking that might be a change to the institution’s current values.</p>

<p>This is all to say, the first sentence of my SLab job talk was: “My digital humanities is not disruptive.” I won’t repeat the rest of my talk, as the first few slides explain why I diverged from the prompt, how I thought about the positive potentials of DH. I did respond to the part of the prompt that indicated what the desired outcomes of (a positive definition of) disruption were to them, and in particular noted that people were mentioned multiple times (relationships, specifics examples of collaboration, organizations). After defining what my definition and goals for DH were against a negative read of “disruption”, I spoke to the prompt’s emphasis on people by structuring the rest of my talk around two examples of people-centric work (my <a href="https://infiniteulysses.com">Infinite Ulysses</a> participatory edition, and founding the <a href="https://tinyurl.com/DHSlack">Digital Humanities Slack</a>).</p>

<p>Attending to the people behind scholarship was a way for me to give the audience a sense of how I might be as a colleague. In my talk, I cited people who impacted how I think and work, regardless of the format (book, article, tweet, panel discussion, lunch conversation, something someone pointedly didn’t say) and regardless of if that person identifies as a scholar. If they contributed to how you think, you should cite them.</p>

<p>But I need to mention privilege again: Some people think less of you for having co-authors or other collaborators, as if that shows your effort was smaller rather than greater. If you aren’t read as male, some people may assume you didn’t do the coding or other technical work on your DH project. If you’re hurting for a job and/or already have other biases working against how people treat you, you might need to be more emphatic about your individual contributions to scholarship.</p>

<p>In this job talk, I tried to speak to people who value or assume different things than me, e.g. folks who would appreciate an explicit discussion of how something functions as scholarship, rather than assuming that people recognize the work behind <a href="http://InfiniteUlysses.com">Infinite Ulysses</a> or the <a href="https://tinyurl.com/DHSlack">DH Slack</a> as scholarship. And given I’ve had some experiences that are likely to be construed as academic success, like my dissertation project being cited in The New York Times, I think it’s reasonable to make sure your interviewers know about that—even if you’re kind of uncomfortable with that being seen as a metric toward whether you should be hired. But I also spoke to things I was proud of that others might not value or see as relevant to scholarship, like receiving emails from a variety of non-faculty strangers happy about discovering my DH project. Interviewing necessitates anxiety, and it’s a privilege to be safe and comfortable sharing some pieces of yourself during a job visit—but I’ve found myself happiest after interviews, including an interview where I did not get offered the job, when I felt I brought and shared more of my full self during the process.</p>

<p>(I was basically going to rewrite Brandon and my post about how to share our job-market knowledge without prescriptively reinforcing classist, sexist, etc. notions of individual value and what counts as scholarship, so instead I’ll just link to <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/dh-cover-letters/">that post</a> again—I learned a lot from the discussions we had before deciding to continue blogging our past job search experiences and advice, and we tried to capture those ideas about a more just and affirming way of supporting jobseekers in that post.)</p>

<h3 id="purdue-tenure-track-faculty-dh-specialist-talk">Purdue Tenure-Track Faculty DH Specialist Talk</h3>

<p>You can read the full text and slides of this talk <a href="http://literaturegeek.com/2016/02/28/DHjobtalk">here</a>.</p>

<p>The talk prompt was:</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Digital humanities and the research library: opportunities and challenges for academic libraries and librarians. Draw upon your experience and knowledge as well as citing research literature in library/archival/information science, and/or disciplinary literature relating to digital humanities. (Audience: Libraries staff and faculty)

</code></pre></div></div>

<p>As with my SLab job talk, I quibbled mildly with this prompt, and explained why at the start of the job talk:</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>There are already many recent voices defining what the digital humanities (or DH) is, what a library does, and exactly how much DH and libraries overlap as academic fields. I didn’t want to rehash those debates, so I put together an online Zotero bibliography with bunch of pertinent readings, which you can access via [tinyurl.com/dhlibraries](https://tinyurl.com/dhlibraries). You’ll also be able to find any work I cite in this talk there…Pulling together over fifty works defining DH and libraries, and strategizing this combination, wasn’t difficult."
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Instead, I wanted to focus on what DH might look like locally, given how I’d function if hired:</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> It was harder to find case studies of the specific, day-to-day tactics of successful combinations of DH and libraries. So, in wanting to discuss the specific question of DH library service today, I’ll try to give some specific examples, spoken and on screen, of the types of events, workflows, and services I’m envisioning. I’d like to focus on what both the strategy and the tactics of a user-focused service ethic look like, when combined with 1) the digital humanities commitment to collaboration, and 2) recognizing scholarship in all areas of professional practice.
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>A small thing, but I like that I included an explicit reference to caring about timekeeping while outlining my talk (“I’ll be talking for around 15 minutes, after which we’ll have a lot of time for discussion”) to help the audience pace their attention.</p>

<p>Now that I know that community, I think the audience would have appreciated more time spent on what DH is and what the arguments about DH and libraries are than I gave them. It’s hard to gauge that, or know who will be at your talk! I think I did okay by defining what DH would look like locally if I were hired, but sharing a few specific projects that show the breadth of what DH can be would have improved the talk. I’d recommend focusing on what DH is to you, and what you hope for DH to be (inspired by <a href="https://twitter.com/elikaortega/status/618097310505938944">Élika Ortega</a>).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DH Cover Letters]]></title>
    <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/dh-cover-letters/"/>
    <updated>2019-10-09T10:03:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/dh-cover-letters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Co-authored with <a href="http://amandavisconti.com/">Amanda Visconti</a>. Crossposted to the <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/dh-cover-letters/">Scholars’ Lab blog</a>, <a href="https://academicjobmarketsupportnetwork.hcommons.org/2019/10/09/how-we-talk-and-write-about-dh-jobs/">the Academic Job Market Support Network</a>, and <a href="https://literaturegeek.com/2019/10/10/digital-humanities-cover-letters-job-advice">Amanda’s personal blog</a></em></p>

<p>Early this summer, we (authors Brandon and Amanda!) planned a post about job search materials, but finishing up the draft got delayed by several weeks. In the intervening time, a small Twitter debate on the subject of academic job advice occurred, and we ended up holding off this post for a few months while discussing how to do it well.</p>

<p>The debate in question: someone shared the job advice they generally give students on the academic job market, and folks responded with frustrations about the prescriptiveness, privilege, and goals of the academic job advice genre. Since then, we’ve also appreciated <a href="https://twitter.com/hralperta/status/1143557245168476160?s=21">inspiring work being done on the topic by Hannah Alpert-Abrams</a>. <a href="https://hcommons.org/groups/academic-job-market-support-network/">The Academic Job Market Support Network</a> that she spearheads shares a lot of the spirit behind what we intended to do with our job search materials, so we’re taking this as an opportunity to revisit the post we had planned. We have both uploaded cover letters from our pasts to the AJMSN (Brandon’s letter <a href="https://hcommons.org/?get_group_doc=1003473/1570202258-HeadofGraduateProgramsCoverLetter.docx">here</a> and Amanda’s letter <a href="https://hcommons.org/?get_group_doc=1003473/1570038081-CoverLetter.pdf">here</a>), and we talk a bit about our reasoning below. We’ll offer some general thoughts about job searches in digital humanities, and annotate each other’s cover letters. We thought the latter might be a useful exercise beyond just sharing them.</p>

<h2 id="slightly-better-job-advice-take-two">Slightly Better Job Advice, Take Two</h2>

<p>Framing an academic job search exclusively in terms of handy tips undervalues the degree of luck that goes into any search. <em>Do these things</em>, such advice seems to suggest, <em>and the just and right meritocracy will reward you with a job</em>. But the academic job market is anything but just, and anything but a pure measure of merit<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote">1</a></sup>. The same is true, of course, for job markets beyond academia. Digital humanities job searches, be they for faculty positions or otherwise, suffer from the same issues. Internally we’ve had a lot of conversation about how to share job advice with our students. We’re frequently called upon to do so, and we want to do it well. So we thought it worth sharing a few of the things we try to consider below. Keep in mind, of course, that this is not an exhaustive list.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>The academic job market is not identical with all job markets in academia. There is a range of different careers that engage in intellectual work, careers that might be called alt-ac (though there are good reasons for not using that term to describe them). Paths to these careers are often just as obscured as paths to professorships, and resources for how to navigate these types of job searches are scarce. Resources for finding and thinking about these kinds of careers are one of the key things we can provide students.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Students need our support. In particular, refusing to share resources about job searches, even if the act is well meaning, can reinforce privileged access to those same materials. Our initial reason for writing this post was that we noticed we were repeatedly sharing the same cover letters with folks looking for work. We found ourselves wondering how many other people at UVA or elsewhere might not know to ask for such resources.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Offers to aid in job searches, on and off the tenure track, are better when they go beyond lists of advice. In particular, we try to help folks think through backup plans and suggest talking with a career center as part of the conversation about how to seek positions in the digital humanities. We try to speak from our own experiences but also to recognize our own limitations as resources. We do not have all the answers, but we still might be able to help in some way.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Student support like this necessarily includes emotional labor. For us (the authors), this has proven unavoidable. In conversations we try to emphasize that the student is smart enough and good enough for this work, that the job market is not a reflection on them, and that our current jobs are the results of luck in a lottery system (where every time you win a lottery it makes winning future lotteries a bit more tipped in your favor…). The fact that we have jobs does not necessarily mean our advice will be helpful (CW for war: see e.g. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Survivorship_bias#In_the_military">Abraham Wald on survivorship bias</a><sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote">2</a></sup>). In short, it is not enough to tell students that they need do X and Y in order to be successful. In the Lab we believe these conversations need to engage with the messy work of what the job search entails.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Advice about any job market should come with a frank discussion about all the factors involved in being offered a job (i.e. how many factors are out of candidates’ hands), and about the precarious nature of employment in the field that the particular position may or may not play into.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>We’re not sure how we share our cover letters given this context, but it still seems worth doing; we’re going to continue advising the local students who work with us, and we’d like to help students who are elsewhere if we can. Some of the ways we try to make our advising do more good than harm include:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Thinking about intent vs. impact: job advice is often “well meaning”, but what matters is the environment it builds up or dismantles, who it tells is worthwhile as they already are vs. who it tells to change, who it empowers with information. Consider whether telling a student that <em>you</em> don’t judge them for XYZ, but that interviewers will, has the same impact as you judging them.</p>
  </li>
  <li>Not posting job ads to the SLab Slack fellows channels (where they might be regular, unwanted reminders of job market stress to folks who aren’t even looking for work right now, or otherwise want to limit when they’re thinking about jobs). We’ve moved to including a list of interesting jobs to the end of our lab newsletter instead, where students can regularly choose to look at them if they choose.</li>
  <li>Moving to a public newsletter as a means of distributing these posts means that students can opt in without self-declaring themselves as on the job market, which allows for greater transparency about the process. It becomes less about knowing who you have to ask - anyone (even non-UVA people) can get access to that newsletter if they choose.</li>
  <li>Focusing our commentary not on “what others will expect” or “the right way to do things” (e.g. how to write the salutation), but instead on examples of how to best communicate one’s personal strengths via cover letter. In this way, we hope to keep the focus on the individual person and how they can take ownership of their own background rather than on how to please an anonymous committee (this can be a moving target).</li>
  <li>Leavening advice with affirmation of students as scholars and humans; helping them think about how to do what they value in life, even if they can’t do that as their main job. In short, academia has a way of encouraging people to think about their academic work and academic “merit” as deep reflections of their “worth” as a person. We try to reaffirm the fact that every person is worthwhile</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="thoughts-on-some-specific-dh-cover-letters">Thoughts on some specific DH cover letters</h2>
<p>Below, each of us shares the text of one of our cover letters for the other to annotate. The comments below reflect what we’ve tried to do when we have served on hiring committees and reviewed cover letters: avoid the stuff we feel we <em>shouldn’t</em> evaluate on, and what we <em>do</em> look for. Of course, these should be taken with a grain of salt. Our hope is that sharing the letters in this format will offer a bit more insight into how we think about DH job searches. It’s also worth noting that we each clearly read for different things. Similarly, other people serving on DH hiring committees might look for different things. We’ll focus on the hiring experience for:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Brandon’s current role: Head of Student Programs at the University of Virginia Library’s Scholars’ Lab<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote">3</a></sup></li>
  <li>Amanda’s previous role: tenure-track assistant professor and DH specialist at Purdue University Libraries<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote">4</a></sup></li>
</ul>

<p>While our comments below are about our cover letters, you might be interested in checking out other hiring and school info we’ve shared: Brandon’s <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/in-out-across-with-collaborative-education-and-digital-humanities-job-talk-for-head-of-graduate-programs/">job talk</a> for his current role, Amanda’s job talks for <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/disrupt-the-humanities-managing-director-job-talk/">her current role</a> (with links to job talks shared by three other scholars as well!) and <a href="http://literaturegeek.com/2016/02/28/DHjobtalk">her previous faculty role</a>; and Amanda’s <a href="http://literaturegeek.com/2016/06/20/digital-humanities-dissertation-defense-talk">doctoral defense talk</a>, <a href="http://literaturegeek.com/2016/06/14/digital-humanities-dissertation-defense-advice">advice about defense talks</a>, and <a href="http://literaturegeek.com/2012/11/27/info-dump-humanities-doctoral-candidacy-exams-advice/">literature/DH PhD exams list and advice</a>. We’ve added the cover letters to <a href="https://academicjobmarketsupportnetwork.hcommons.org/">an existing effort</a> to gather and contextualize job materials led by Hannah Alpert-Abrams on <em>Humanities Commons</em>—check out their <a href="https://hcommons.org/groups/academic-job-market-support-network/documents/">files page</a> for other cover letters, various types of written statement, etc.</p>

<p>We started working at SLab on the same day and were not involved in the hiring of each other, so all comments are views from outside the search committee. You can check out the full cover letters on <em>Humanities Commons</em>, and reading them in full first might be useful: <a href="https://hcommons.org/?get_group_doc=1003473/1570202258-HeadofGraduateProgramsCoverLetter.docx">Brandon’s cover letter</a> and <a href="https://hcommons.org/?get_group_doc=1003473/1570038081-CoverLetter.pdf">Amanda’s cover letter</a>. You might wish to compare these to how the job ads described these roles: <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/are-you-our-next-head-of-graduate-programs/">Head of Graduate Programs</a> and <a href="http://literaturegeek.com/assets/DigitalHumanitiesSpecialist.pdf">Digital Humanities Specialist Assistant or Associate Professor</a>. In what follows, we intersperse inset text of our letters with short, bulleted lists of comments from the other person.</p>

<h3 id="brandons-cover-letter">Brandon’s cover letter</h3>
<p><em><a href="https://hcommons.org/?get_group_doc=1003473/1570202258-HeadofGraduateProgramsCoverLetter.docx">Brandon’s cover letter</a>, notes by Amanda</em></p>
<div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>I am writing to apply for the position of Head of Graduate Programs in the Scholars’ Lab at the University of Virginia. As an alumnus of both the Praxis Program and the Graduate Fellowship in Digital Humanities, I have a deep appreciation for the Scholars’ Lab’s commitment to experimental forms of collaborative, project-based pedagogy.
</code></pre></div></div>
<ul>
  <li>If you have past experience or knowledge of what the place does, share that! You don’t have to have worked/learned at the place (as Brandon did at UVA) to speak to what specifically draws you there. E.g. maybe you’ve gotten a sense from their social media, a project or conference talk, or a blog post about what’s important to how the place works?</li>
  <li>Brandon shows awareness and mutual commitment to some of the lab’s values here; he shares this in a way that lets the search committee learn something about <em>him</em> (that he digs experimentation, collaboration), rather than something more abstract like “I would be honored to work at such a great place” that doesn’t give the committee info but does take up some of your limited space.</li>
  <li>Most of the cover letters I’ve seen use the first paragraph to deliver information that isn’t really new—<em>this is my name, I’m not confused what position I’m applying for, I think I would be a good fit</em>—so I like how he leads with a framing that <em>does</em> tell us more about him as a candidate.
    <div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>I believe that my own extensive teaching record and my experiences as a digital humanities developer and project manager, all of which are shaped by my understanding of the Scholars’ Lab’s values, make me uniquely qualified for this position.
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>There’s limited space to tell the search committee about yourself, so rather than make his cover letter repeat his CV, Brandon connects up items in his past that could help him successfully fill this role’s goals. Rather than using himself as a reference (e.g. “I am very good at x” or “I am xyz adjectives”), Brandon points out that the past roles listed on his CV are connected as different approaches in DH, suggesting he’s both learned skills from being in a variety of different roles, and can probably work in an informed way with colleagues in those roles.</li>
  <li>He again recognizes specifics about the lab—that through our staff charter, choices, etc. we try to be attentive to how our values shape our work. Some institutions make learning about how they do work difficult, unfortunately.
    <div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Student mentoring has been my first priority for the duration of my career.
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>Brandon shares who he is as a professional and community member: articulating what matters to him, showing he understands what matters to this job, and going on to explicitly demonstrate how the two overlap.
    <div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>I have taught a number of digital humanities workshops and classes, but I am proudest of my recent work as co-administrator of the Undergraduate Digital Humanities Fellows program at Washington and Lee University, where I currently serve as Mellon Digital Humanities Fellow. This initiative attempts to adapt the principles of the Praxis Program to a liberal arts context by allowing undergraduates to engage in collaborative research projects of their own design. I serve in both supervisory and technical roles in this program, and my daily tasks range from scoping student projects to teaching technical lessons on GitHub or programming concepts in PHP. During the past year, I have worked with humanities students to design and implement digital archives, editions, and storytelling projects through a combination of hands-on training and mentoring.
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>The first half of this sentence (“I have taught a number of digital humanities workshops and classes”) could mean anything from teaching two small workshops ever, to multiple courses designed and taught himself—when hiring, readers may assume the lowest possible situation that your statement might mean, unless shown otherwise via specifics. Brandon helps us not need to guess—he doesn’t rehash his whole list of DHy skills here, but mentions a few in context in a way that suggests familiarity with other DH practices as well.</li>
  <li>Specific examples, including names of methods, tech, approaches showing familiarity. A good way to demonstrate knowledge of an area is to describe what daily work practices look like—specific tools or methods, what your involvement in a project specifically looked like.
    <div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>I recognize that the vitality of a program depends upon a student community that extends beyond the bounds of the fellowship years, so I have created an outreach plan that builds our student network by having fellows visit other courses and mentor others as digital experts.
This student community can – and should – contribute to life beyond the walls of the academy: this year I am piloting a program that sends our fellows to a local High School AP Computer Science class to collaborate on digital projects. Drawing on the lessons I learned during my own training, my efforts always aim to teach the person not the material. Helping students to find the confidence to speak, act, and sometimes fail productively in public in roles like these is as important to me as any temporary success afforded by a project.
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>Brandon states some of his values and goals, then immediately identifies how he acted on these. This both backs up claimed values in his letter, and demonstrates experience reflecting on and iterating one’s practices to bring them into line with what you identify as important.</li>
  <li>There’s use in defining commonplace terms. Everyone knows what “teaching” means, right? But is this someone who cares about “filling young minds” and also mocks their current students on social media, vs. someone who sees students as colleagues, fellow scholars, humans? Brandon’s approach in this paragraph helps the reader see if we’re actually talking about the same thing when we say “teaching” (same for “research”, “scholarship”, “service”, etc.).</li>
</ul>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>As a member of Washington and Lee’s digital humanities faculty committee, I have helped to develop the school’s digital humanities curriculum, which aims to provide students at all levels of expertise with an intellectual and practical understanding of innovative digital work. In particular, I have focused on collaborations that raise the skillsets of my colleagues as long-term investments in growing our resources. Working with Professor Sarah Horowitz and a student researcher on her interest in text analysis, for example, has led to both a co-taught class on digital history as well as a co-authored open access textbook.

The book is, foremost, a pedagogical exploration, an attempt to write an accessible introduction to digital text analysis for complete newcomers. The writing of this textbook was also, in itself, a teaching exercise: the writing process required Professor Horowitz to learn version control and Markdown in addition to a number of text analysis techniques. These experiences were part of a larger experiment that I spearheaded in collaborative writing and publishing that has led to invitations for presentations and workshops at DLF and Bucknell Digital Scholarship with our Digital Humanities Librarian.

As an experienced project manager and digital humanities developer, I also offer an advanced skillset to augment my teaching.
</code></pre></div></div>
<ul>
  <li>Brandon shows how he invests in people around him, making the place he works better for colleagues in different roles (here: student, staff, faculty).</li>
  <li>When applying for a staff job from a doctoral and/or faculty background, it can be useful to demonstrate how those experiences don’t disadvantage you—i.e.  you don’t understand what the staff position will be like. Brandon manages to both show the skills he learned from his past work experiences, while also aiming them at the kinds of work he’d be doing if hired.</li>
  <li>Brandon notes skills that might not be in the job ad, but are critical: collaboration, managing projects, a broad understanding of tech.</li>
</ul>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>I served for several years as the project manager of NINES, and I have given invited talks on project development at the University of Michigan, SUNY New Paltz, the University of Central Florida, and the Center for Networked Information. I have consistently worked to supplement this supervisory experience with the skills necessary to implement projects myself. During my time at Washington and Lee, I have deployed and maintained three Rails applications, supervised Omeka customizations, and designed text analyses in Python, in addition to carrying out my own research in machine learning and sound studies. These skills will allow me not only to lead workshops on the technical aspects of digital humanities research, but also to supplement the resources of the Scholars’ Lab by providing technical support to fellows myself.
</code></pre></div></div>

<ul>
  <li>It’s very good to share things you’re proud of! If you don’t highlight these, your search committee might never know about them. If you have trouble doing this, you might have friends or a supportive teacher who can help you remember experiences or decisions worth sharing here. Julia Evans has a good <a href="https://jvns.ca/blog/brag-documents/">blog post</a> about how to get comfortable talking about your strengths.</li>
  <li>Brandon does a good job pitching his achievements for this staff role—sharing the things faculty hiring committees value, like invited talks, but coupling those with tech skills and his broader learning from those experiences. He comes across as someone who wants to be in a staff job that’s heavy on mentoring, collaborating, experimenting, rather than someone treating this job as an alternative to another career goal.</li>
</ul>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>I know first-hand how transformative the right interventions can be in the lives of graduate students. The Scholars’ Lab’s commitment to equipping students at all levels for both the kinds of careers that they will find and the intellectual provocations they can make in the digital age has shaped my own thinking, and it continues to inform all of my work. I see this position in the Scholars’ Lab as the perfect opportunity for me to help others learn as I once did, and to use my skills and experiences to extend the excellent work of the Scholars’ Lab’s fellowship programs.

I look forward to discussing the great potential of the position with you.
</code></pre></div></div>

<ul>
  <li>I like the wording in the final sentence—”great potential” reminds me that I’ve gotten a sense from this letter that this is someone who’s thought hard about the strategy and tactics of student-focused DH, who is ready to do good in this role.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="amandas-cover-letter">Amanda’s cover letter</h3>
<p><em><a href="https://hcommons.org/?get_group_doc=1003473/1570038081-CoverLetter.pdf">Amanda’s cover letter</a>, notes by Brandon</em></p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Dear Purdue University Libraries team,

I'm a digital humanist with an Information M.S. (University of Michigan), new Literature Ph.D. (University of Maryland), and over eight years as a professional DH web developer and public-focused DH scholar, working since 2009 in multiple staff roles at the Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities (MITH). I write to apply for the Digital Humanities Specialist role.
</code></pre></div></div>
<ul>
  <li>The first thing I notice is how Amanda structured her letter differently than how I typically do so. I tend to treat cover letters like essays, where the structure of the thing to come will be laid out in the final sentence of the first paragraph. Amanda leads with her experience here, which is likely to make sure her cover letter gets past an initial quick read.</li>
  <li>It’s perhaps also worth noting how wild and varied the paths often are for digital humanists. In this field maybe more than others it is not uncommon to tie together many seemingly disconnected life experiences into a narrative about yourself. The connections between library degrees, and PhD in English, and positions at a DH center all speak to each other in clear ways. But I can easily imagine a need to pull together a variety of different experiences that might not parse so easily for people. This seems fine to me. More on diverse life experiences below!</li>
  <li>Another thing that stands out here is that Amanda does not just point out what she has done - she points out different experiences from very different contexts. Research experience as a graduate student, library experience, and hands-on experiences. It’s helpful to think in these terms when presenting yourself to a search committee. It’s not just about the work you’ve done. It’s also about the kinds of contexts and audiences to which this work exposes you.
    <div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>As an example of my work, my recent dissertation project is InfiniteUlysses.com—an interface that brings scholars, teachers, and readers of all backgrounds together in annotating and discussing a challenging book, personalizing the annotations displayed to any given reader by their backgrounds, interests, and needs. Infinite Ulysses achieved sizable impact for a literature dissertation, with over 13,000 unique visitors during its first month of open beta. The challenge of helping everyone feel empowered to participate in the humanities drives my research and project design.
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>To underscore what Amanda says above - I usually tell people to make sure their letter is not an extension of their CV. When addressing things that appear in both, I usually try to make sure the things in the letter expand or provide context that you might not otherwise get in a CV. This text is great, because she expands on a project that might otherwise only get a line and not have the same impact.</li>
  <li>I also like how she takes the work and expands upon it to describe what she learned from it. That sort of self-reflection is something I usually look for in cover letters and try to represent in my own.</li>
  <li>Amanda’s accomplishments here and as articulated in the letter are impressive, but I often think it’s a matter of selling yourself regardless of whether or not you have done a lot, whether or not your blog has thousands of hits. Take the things you have done and use them as an opportunity to spin a story about yourself.</li>
</ul>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Successfully completing a non-monograph dissertation taught me how to champion others embarking on digital scholarship, both in educating their colleagues on their digital work, and in the practical aspects of project design, technical learning, and planning for the full life cycle of the project. I dealt with this last—DH long-term thinking and digital preservation—as MITH's Webmaster, auditing our two servers full of projects, files, and databases ranging back to 1999, and in my training and experience doing digital preservation work with MITH's early e-lit collection.
</code></pre></div></div>
<ul>
  <li>Another thing I often look for - the letter is a space to offer reflections on your experience. I like that Amanda takes the experience with the dissertation and goes a step further to show what it means in the broader narrative of how she approaches people and her work. In other words - it answers the “so what?” question. These moments of reflection can also be a chance to connect yourself to the values of the institution and position for which you are applying.</li>
  <li>As a student, it can often feel like you have no experience. But you do! It’s just a matter of taking those experiences you do have and extrapolating to how they would apply to other circumstances. So in this case, Amanda does a great job of showing how working as a dissertation and webmaster apply to other circumstances and to the position for which she’s applying. I often tell students to think of it like roleplaying. If you were in the position, what experiences have you had that you could imagine helping you? Write about them. Sometimes trying to imagine yourself doing the work can help you think further about how to present yourself for the application.</li>
  <li>Lastly I would note that it’s important to consider the practical skills you gain from doing digital work as distinct from the research aspects of that work. To be sure, they’re both tightly joined in practice. But it’s all too easy to get to the end of a digital project on Victorian archives and think, “this has given me experience with Victorian research and digital archives.” But there is also a whole range of other “soft skills” that such work gives you experience in - project management, software development, project promotion, etc. These are all things you can have experience in and they are also things you can discuss critically! Reflections on these parts of the process are often of immense use to other scholar practitioners. Think of them as experiences but also as potential objects of scholarly inquiry.</li>
</ul>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>My work has always been interdisciplinary in both topic and methodology. A few of my diverse past DH projects include:

* Co-organizing the first digital humanities and games unconference (THATCamp Games)  
* Developer on the "Making DH More Open" team's Braille Wordpress plugin  
* Data visualization and topic modeling of Digital Humanities Quarterly to explore DH citation networks (recipient of the inaugural ACH Microgrant)  
* Team teaching and design of a DH course for UMD's Digital Cultures and Creativity undergrads  
* Librarian-aimed user testing and documentation for BitCurator's archival digital forensics tools  

I offer excellent communication, teaching, and presentation skills, and am especially deft at research use of social media (over 2,000 Twitter followers) and blogging (over 22,000 unique blog visitors to date). I’ve worked in a number of pertinent roles: as a librarian and digital archivist, university teacher and student, web developer, and DH center staff, as well as alongside others in these roles. This background gives me inside experience of the different needs and values of these important scholarly constituents. After working on interdisciplinary teams for six years at one of the world's top digital humanities research centers, I'm a skilled translator between tech and non-tech colleagues, and my research best thrives through collaboration.
</code></pre></div></div>

<ul>
  <li>I think the reference to social media work here is useful. When I was hired at the Lab, they specifically cited my blogging and presence on Twitter as assets. You might not think about that kind of public outreach as tangible work, but it is! It’s often helpful to think about the value you bring to the institution beyond your research and teaching. This framing can be especially useful for positions beyond the tenure track in libraries or otherwise.</li>
  <li>One thing I notice about Amanda’s letter is that it really speaks to the diverse experiences she had when she applied to the position. That’s great! In academia I think we are sometimes challenged to think of ourselves as this coherent narrative where all roads lead to a single path. But, in practice, we have all sorts of experiences. And that broad background can be part of your narrative. We don’t all fit into neat boxes.</li>
</ul>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>I'd love to discuss how my background in digital humanities service, training, research, and building would complement the Purdue University Libraries' learner-centered mission! Thank you for your time and consideration.
</code></pre></div></div>

<ul>
  <li>Small point, but it’s often quite clear when a single cover letter has been sent out to multiple institutions with the name of one simply subbed for another. There are small ways to flag that you actually are applying for this <em>specific position at this specific place</em>, and this is an example of them. That’s to say, I like that Amanda doesn’t just say she is a good fit, she connects her experience to the mission of the institution in this last moment. It can be difficult to figure out what that mission is (in the Scholars’ Lab we have an explicit statement about <a href="https://scholarslab.org/charter">our values</a>), but you could get clues from events, projects, research, and similar initiatives undertaken by the institution. If they’re committing time and energy to it, they care about it.</li>
  <li>In terms of thinking about how to find out the character of an institution, specific events or projects can help. But there are often large, general questions you could ask about a place that could help you think about their mission. Is it a small liberal arts college or an R1 institution? Is this a DH center you would be hired into or a single position apart from a larger network of support? Is the position part of a library? Is the position hired for a particular grant or is it sourced on hard money? Are we talking about an institution of teaching? higher education? cultural heritage? What sort of audience / public does the institution tend to cater to? There are a number of large buckets like these that institutions tend to fall into. While each organization is unique, thinking about large categories like these can help provide clues to what this particular one is about.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="endnotes">Endnotes</h2>
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>The coiner of the word “meritocracy” intended it to ridicule the very ideas folks now use the term to convey. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>I remember seeing a tweet recently where someone connected the infamous image of the bullet hole locations on the surviving planes to listening to some kind of job advice selectively—maybe listening to folks who got hired about what not to ask during interviews? If you know who tweeted this and wouldn’t mind, please let me know so I can cite them (@literature_geek on Twitter/visconti@virginia.edu). It’s important to record where ideas came from, even in smaller things like this post. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>Brandon’s title has been expanded over the course of his work here; at the time of hiring, it was “Head of Graduate Programs”. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p>We thought this be more broadly useful to students than the cover letter for her current job, as that fits leaving a faculty role to direct a lab, rather than locating one’s first post-PhD job. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[In, Out, Across, With: Collaborative Education and Digital Humanities (Job Talk for Scholars' Lab)]]></title>
    <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/in-out-across-with/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-02T09:31:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/in-out-across-with</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>[Crossposted on the <a href="https://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/blog/2017/03/06/in-out-across-with-collaborative-education-and-digital-humanities-job-talk-for-scholars-lab/">WLUDH blog</a> and the <a href="http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/in-out-across-with-collaborative-education-and-digital-humanities-job-talk-for-head-of-graduate-programs/">Scholars’ Lab blog</a>]</em></p>

<p>I’ve accepted a new position as the <a href="http://scholarslab.org/uncategorized/brandon-walsh-is-our-new-head-of-graduate-programs-starting-april-24-2017/">Head of Graduate Programs in the Scholars’ Lab</a>, and I’ll be transitioning into that role over the next few weeks! As a part of the interview process, we had to give a job talk. While putting together this presentation, I was lucky enough to have past examples to work from (as you’ll be able to tell, if you check out this past <a href="http://literaturegeek.com/2016/02/28/DHjobtalk">job talk</a> by Amanda Visconti). Since my new position will involve helping graduate students through the process of applying for positions like these, it only feels right that I should post my own job talk as well as a few words on the thinking that went into it. Blemishes, jokes, and all, hopefully these materials will help someone in the future find a way in, just as the example of others did for me. And if you’re looking for more, Visconti has a great list of other examples linked from her <a href="http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/disrupt-the-humanities-managing-director-job-talk/">more recent job talk</a> for the Scholars’ Lab.</p>

<p>For the presentation, I was asked to respond to this prompt:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What does a student (from undergraduate to doctoral levels) need to learn or experience in order to add “DH” to his or her skill set?  Is that an end or a means of graduate education?  Can short-term digital assignments in discipline-specific courses go beyond “teaching with technology”?  Why not refer everyone to online tutorials?  Are there risks for doctoral students or the untenured in undertaking digital projects?  Drawing on your own experience, and offering examples or demonstrations of digital research projects, pedagogical approaches, or initiatives or organizations that you admire, make a case for a vision of collaborative education in advanced digital scholarship in the arts and humanities.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I felt that each question could be a presentation all its own, and I had strong opinions about each one. Dealing with all of them seemed like a tall order. I decided to spend the presentation close reading and deconstructing that first sentence, taking apart the idea that education and/or digital humanities could be thought of in terms of lists of skills at all. Along the way, my plan was to dip into the other questions as able, but I also assumed that I would have plenty of time during the interview day to give my thoughts on them. I also wanted to try to give as honest a sense as possible of the way I approach teaching and mentoring. For me, it’s all about people and giving them the care that they need. In conveying that, I hoped, I would give the sort of vision the prompt was asking for. I also tried to sprinkle references to the past and present of the Scholars’ Lab programs to ground the content of the talk. When I mention potential career options in the body of the talk, I am talking about specific alumni who came through the fellowship programs. And when I mention graduate fellows potentially publishing on their work with the Twitter API, well, <a href="http://scholarslab.org/uncategorized/working-with-an-archive-of-the-now/">that’s not hypothetical either</a>.</p>

<p>So below find the lightly edited text of the talk I gave at the Scholars’ Lab - “In, Out, Across, With: Collaborative Education and Digital Humanities.” I’ve only substantively  modified one piece - swapping out one example for another.</p>

<p>And a final note on delivery: I have heard plenty of people argue over whether it is better to read a written talk or deliver one from notes. My own sense is that the latter is far more common for digital humanities talks. I have seen both fantastic read talks and amazing extemporaneous performances, just as I have seen terrible versions of each. My own approach is, increasingly, to write a talk but deliver that talk more or less from memory. In this case, I had a pretty long commute to work, so I recorded myself reading the talk and listened to it a lot to get the ideas in my head. When I gave the presentation, I had the written version in front of me for reference, but I was mostly moving through my own sense of how it all fit together in real time (and trying to avoid looking at the paper). My hope is that this gave me the best of both worlds and resulted in a structured but engaging performance. Your mileage may vary!</p>

<h2 id="in-out-across-with-collaborative-education-and-digital-humanities">In, Out, Across, With: Collaborative Education and Digital Humanities</h2>

<p><img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide01.jpg" alt="Title slide" /> It’s always a treat to be able to talk with the members of the UVA Library community, and I am very grateful to be here. For those of you that don’t know me, I am Brandon Walsh, Mellon Digital Humanities Fellow and Visiting Assistant Professor of English at Washington and Lee University. The last time I was here, I gave a talk that had almost exclusively animal memes for slides. I can’t promise the same robust Internet culture in this talk, but talk to me after and I can hook you up. I swear I’ve still got it.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide02.jpg" alt="Zotero slide" /> In the spirit of Amanda Visconti, the resources that went into this talk (and a number of foundational materials on the subject) can all be found in a Zotero collection at the <a href="https://www.zotero.org/bmw9t/items/collectionKey/9KAAWQGG">above link</a>. I’ll name check any that are especially relevant, but hopefully this set of materials will allow the thoughts in the talk to flower outwards for any who are interested in seeing its origins and echoes in the work of others.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide03.jpg" alt="Thank you slide" /> And a final prefatory note: no person works, thinks or learns alone, so here are the names of the people in my talk whose thinking I touch upon as well as just some – but not all – of my colleagues at W&amp;L who collaborate on the projects I mention. Top tier consists of people I cite or mention, second tier is for institutions or publications important to discussion, and final tier is for direct collaborators on this work.</p>

<p>Today I want to talk to you about how best to champion the people involved in collaborative education in digital research. I especially want to talk about students. And when I mention “students” throughout this talk, I will mostly be speaking in the context of graduate students. But most of what I discuss will be broadly applicable to all newcomers to digital research. My talk is an exhortation to find ways to elevate the voices of people in positions like these to be contributors to professional and institutional conversations from day one and to empower them to define the methods and the outcomes of the digital humanities that we teach. This means taking seriously the messy, fraught, and emotional process of guiding students through digital humanities methods, research, and careers. It means advocating for the legibility of this digital work as a key component of their professional development. And it means enmeshing these voices in the broader network around them, the local context that they draw upon for support and that they can enrich in turn. I believe it is the mission of the Head of Graduate Programs to build up this community and facilitate these networks, to incorporate those who might feel like outsiders to the work that we do. Doing so enriches and enlivens our communities and builds a better and more diverse research and teaching agenda. <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide04.jpg" alt="Title Slide 2" /> This talk is titled “In, Out, Across, With: Collaborative Education and Digital Humanities,” and I’ll really be focusing on the prepositions of my title as a metaphor for the nature of this sort of position. I see this role as one of connection and relation. The talk runs about 24 minutes, so we should have plenty of time to talk.</p>

<p>When discussing digital humanities education, it is tempting to first and foremost discuss what, exactly, it is that you will be teaching. What should the students walk away knowing? To some extent, just as there is more than one way to make breakfast, you could devise numerous baseline curricula. <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide05.jpg" alt="W&amp;L Skills" /></p>

<p>This is what we came up with at Washington and Lee for students in our <a href="http://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/initiatives/undergraduate-fellowship/">undergraduate digital humanities fellowship program</a>. We tried to hit a number of kinds of skills that a practicing digital humanist might need. It’s by no means exhaustive, but the list is a way to start. We don’t expect one person to come away knowing everything, so instead we aim for students to have an introduction to a wide variety of technologies by the end of a semester or year. They’ll encounter some technologies applicable to project management, some to front-end design, as well as a variety of programming concepts broadly applicable to a variety of situations. Lists like this give some targets to hit. But still, even as someone who helped put this list together, it makes me worry a bit. I can imagine younger me being afraid of it! It’s easy for us to forget what it was like to be new, to be a beginner, to be learning for the first time, but I’d like to return us to that frame of thinking. I think we should approach lists like these with care, because they can be intimidating for the newcomer. So in my talk today I want to argue against lists of skills as ways of thinking.</p>

<p>I don’t mean to suggest that programs need no curriculum, nor do I mean to suggest that no skills are necessary to be a digital humanist. But I would caution against focusing too much on the skills that one should have at the end of a program, particularly when talking about people who haven’t yet begun to learn. I would wager that many people on the outside looking in think of DH in the same way: it’s a big list of unknowns. I’d like to get away from that.</p>

<p>Templates like this are important for developing courses, fellowship, and degree-granting programs, but I worry that the goodwill in them might all too easily seem like a form of gatekeeping to a new student. It is easy to imagine telling a student that “you have to learn GitHub before you can work on this project.” It’s just a short jump from this to a likely student response - “ah sorry - I don’t know that yet.” And from there I can all too easily imagine the common refrain that you hear from students of all levels - “If I can’t get that, then it’s because I’m not a technology person.” From there - “Digital humanities must not be for me.”</p>

<p>Instead of building our curricula out of as-yet-unknown tool chains, I want to float, today, a vision of DH education as an introduction to a series of professional practices. Lists of skills might be ends but I fear they might foreclose beginnings. <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide06.jpg" alt="SCI Slide" /> Instead, I will float something more in line with that of the Scholarly Communication Institute (held here at UVA for a time), which outlined what they saw as the needs of graduate and professional students in the digital age. I’ll particularly draw upon their first point here (last of my slides with tons of text, I swear): graduate students need training in “collaborative modes of knowledge production and sharing.”</p>

<p>I want to think about teaching DH as introducing a process of discovery that collapses hierarchies between expert and newcomer: that’s a way to start. This sort of framing offers digital humanities not as a series of methods one does or does not know, but, rather, as a process that a group can engage in together. Do they learn methods and skills in the process? Of course! Anyone who has taken part in the sort of collaborative group projects undertaken by the Scholars’ Lab comes away knowing more than they came in with. But I want to continue thinking about process and, in particular, how that process can be more inclusive and more engaging. By empowering students to choose what they want to learn and how they want to learn it, we can help to expand the reach of our work and better serve our students as mentors and collaborators. There are a few different in ways in which I see this as taking place, and they’ll form the roadmap for the rest of the talk. <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide07.jpg" alt="Roadmap Slide" /> Apologies - this looks like the sort of slide you would get at a business retreat. All the same - we need to adapt and develop new professional opportunities for our students at the same time that we plan flexible outcomes for our educational programs. These approaches are meant to serve increasingly diverse professional needs in a changing job market, and they need to be matched by deepening support at the institutional level.</p>

<p>So to begin. One of our jobs as mentors is to encourage students to seek out professionally legible opportunities early on in their careers, and as shapers of educational programs we can go further and create new possibilities for them. At W&amp;L, we have been <a href="https://github.com/wludh/research-one-collab">collaborating with the Scholars’ Lab</a> to bring UVA graduate students to teach short-form workshops on digital research in W&amp;L classrooms. Funded opportunities like this one can help students professionalize in new ways and in new contexts while paying it forward to the nearby community. A similar initiative at W&amp;L that I’ve been working on has our own library faculty and undergraduate fellows visiting local high schools to speak with advanced AP computer science students about how their own programming work can apply to humanities disciplines. I’m happy to talk more about these in Q&amp;A.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide08.jpg" alt="Student slide" /> We also have our student collaborators present at conferences, both on their own work and on work they have done with faculty members, both independently and as co-presenters. Here is Abdur, one of our undergraduate Mellon DH fellows, talking about the writing he does for his thesis and how it is enriched by and different from the writing he does in digital humanities contexts at the Bucknell Digital Scholarship Conference last fall. While this sort of thing is standard for graduate students, it’s pretty powerful for an undergraduate to present on research in this way. Learning that it’s OK to fail in public can be deeply empowering, and opportunities like these encourage our students to think about themselves as valuable contributors to ongoing conversations long before they might otherwise feel comfortable doing so.</p>

<p>But teaching opportunities and conferences are not the only ways to get student voices out there. I think there are ways of engaging student voices earlier, at home, in ways that can fit more situations. We can encourage students to engage in professional conversations by developing flexible outcomes in which we are equal participants. One approach to this with which I have been experimenting is group writing, which I think is undervalued as a taught skill and possible approach to DH pedagogy. An example: when a history faculty member at W&amp;L approached the library (and by extension, me) for support in supplementing an extant history course with a component about digital text analysis, we could have agreed to offer a series of one-off workshops and be done with it. <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide09.jpg" alt="Gitbook slide" /> Instead, this faculty member – Professor Sarah Horowitz – and I decided to collaborate on a more extensive project together, producing <a href="http://www.walshbr.com/textanalysiscoursebook">Introduction to Text Analysis: A Coursebook</a>. The idea was to put the materials for the workshops together ahead of time, in collaboration, and to narrativize them into a set of lessons that would persist beyond a single semester as a kind of publication. The pedagogical labor that we put into reshaping her course could become, in some sense, professionally legible as a series of course modules that others could use beyond the term. So for the book, we co-authored a series of units on text analysis and gave feedback on each other’s work, editing and reviewing as well as reconfiguring them for the context of the course. Professor Horowitz provided more of the discipline-specific material that I could not, and I provided the materials more specific to the theories and methods of text analysis. Neither one of us could have written the book without the other.</p>

<p>Professor Horowitz was, in effect, a student in this moment. She was also a teacher and researcher. She was learning at the same time that she produced original scholarly contributions. Even as we worked together, for me this collaborative writing project was also a pedagogical experiment that drew upon the examples of <a href="https://openamlit.pressbooks.com/">Robin DeRosa</a>, <a href="http://workbook.craftingdigitalhistory.ca/">Shawn Graham</a>, and <a href="https://www.hastac.org/collections/field-notes-21st-century-literacies">Cathy Davidson</a>, in particular. <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide10.jpg" alt="Davidson Slide" /> Davidson taught a graduate course on “21st Century Literacies” where each of her students wrote a chapter that was then collected and published as an open-access book. For us as for Davidson, the process of knowing, the process of uncovering is something that happens together. In public. And it’s documented so that others can benefit. Our teaching labor could become visible and professionally legible, as could the labor that Professor Horowitz put into learning new research skills. As she adapts and tries out ideas, and as we coalesce them into a whole, the writing product is both the means and the end of an introduction to digital humanities.</p>

<p>Professor Horowitz also wanted to learn technical skills herself, and she learned quite a lot through the writing process. Rather than sitting through lectures or being directed to online tutorials by me, I thought she would learn better by engaging with and shaping the material directly. Her course and my materials would be better for it, as she would be helping to bind my lectures and workshops to her course material. The process would also require her to engage with a list of technologies for digital publishing. <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide11.jpg" alt="Gitbook Toolchain Slide" /> Beyond the text analysis materials and concepts, the process exposed her to a lot of technologies: command line, Markdown, Git for version control, GitHub for project management. In the process of writing this document, in fact, she covered most of the same curriculum as our undergraduate DH fellows. <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide12.jpg" alt="Fellows Skills Slide" /> She’s learning these things as we work together to produce course materials, but, importantly, the technical skills aren’t the focus of the work together. It’s a writing project! Rather than presenting the skills as ends in themselves, they were the means by which we were publishing a thing. They were immediately useful. And I think displacing the technology is helpful: it means that the outcomes and parameters for success are not based in the technology itself but, rather, in the thinking about and use of those methods. We also used a <a href="https://www.gitbook.com">particular platform</a> that allowed Professor Horowitz to engage with these technologies in a light way so that they would not overwhelm our work – I’m happy to discuss more in the time after if you’re interested.</p>

<p>This to say: the outcomes of such collaborative educations can be shaped to a variety of different settings and types of students. Take another model, <a href="https://digitalfellows.commons.gc.cuny.edu/">CUNY’s Graduate Center Digital Fellows program</a>, whose students develop open tutorials on digital tools. Learning from this example, rather than simply direct students or colleagues towards online tutorials like these, why not have them write their own documents, legible for their own positions, that synthesize and remix the materials that they already have found? <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide13.jpg" alt="Programming Historian Slide" /> The learning process becomes something productive in this framing. I can imagine, for example, directing collaboratively authored materials by students like these towards something like <a href="https://programminghistorian.org/">The Programming Historian</a>. If you’re not familiar, The Programming Historian offers a variety of lessons on digital humanities methods, and they only require an outline as a pitch to their editorial team, not a whole written publication ready to go. Your graduate students could, say, work with the Twitter API over the course of a semester, blog about the research outcomes, and then pitch a tutorial to The Programming Historian on the API as a result of their work. It’s much easier to motivate yourselves to write something if you know that the publication has already been accepted. Obviously such acceptance is not a given, but working towards a goal like this can offer student researchers something to aim for. Their instructors could co-author these materials, even, so that everyone has skin in the game.</p>

<p>This model changes the shape of what collaborative education can look like: it’s duration and its results. You don’t need a whole fellowship year. You could, in a reasonably short amount of time, tinker and play, and produce a substantial blog post, an article pitch, or a Library Research Guide (more on that in a moment).</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide14.jpg" alt="Jarvis Quote Slide" />As Jeff Jarvis has said, “we need to move students up the education chain.” And trust me - the irony of quoting a piece titled “Lectures are Bullshit” during a lecture to you is not lost on me. But stay with me.</p>

<p>Collaborative writing projects on DH topics are flexible enough to fit the many contexts for the kind of educational work that we do. After all, no one needs or values the same outcomes, and these shared and individual goals need to be worked out in conversation with the students themselves early on. Articulating these desires in a frank, written, and collaborative mode early on (in the genre of <a href="http://praxis.scholarslab.org/charter/">the project charter</a>), can help the program directors to better shape the work to fit the needs of the students. But I also want to suggest that collaborative writing projects can be useful end products as well as launching pads, as they can fit the shape of many careers. After all, students come to digital humanities for a variety of different reasons. Some might be aiming to bolster a research portfolio on the path to a traditional academic career. Others might be deeply concerned about the likelihood of attaining such a position and be looking for other career options. Others still might instead be colleagues interested in expanding their research portfolio or skillset but unable to commit to a whole year of work on top of their current obligations. Writing projects could speak to all these situations.</p>

<p>I see someone in charge of shaping graduate programs as needing to speak to these diverse needs. This person is both a steward of where students currently are – the goals and objectives they might currently have – as well as of where they might go – the potential lives they might (or might not!) lead. After all, graduate school, like undergraduate, is an enormously stressful time of personal and professional exploration. If we think simply about a student’s professional development as a process of finding a job, we overlook the real spaces in which help might be most desired. Frequently, those needs are the anxieties, stresses, and pressures of refashioning yourself as a professional. We should not be in the business of creating CV lines or providing lists of qualifications alone. We should focus on creating strong, well-adjusted professionals by developing ethical programs that guide them into the professional world by caring for them as people.</p>

<p>In the graduate context, this involves helping students deal with the academic job market in particular. <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide15.jpg" alt="Rogers Slide" /> To me in its best form, this means helping students to look at their academic futures and see proliferating possibilities instead of a narrow and uncertain route to a single job, to paraphrase the work of Katina Rogers. A sprinkler rather than a pipeline, in her metaphor. As Rogers’s work, in particular, has shown, recent graduate students increasingly feel that, while they experienced strong expectations that they would continue in the professoriate, they received inadequate preparation for the many different careers they might actually go on to have. <a href="http://praxis.scholarslab.org">The Praxis Program</a> and the <a href="http://praxis-network.org/">Praxis Network</a> are good examples of how to position digital humanities education as answers to these issues. Fellowship opportunities like these must be robust enough that they can offer experiences and outcomes beyond the purely technical, so that a project manager from one fellowship year can graduate with an MA and go into industry in a similar role just as well-prepared as a PhD student aiming to be a developer might go on to something entirely different. And the people working these programs must be prepared for the messy labor of helping students to realize that these are satisfactory, laudable professional goals.</p>

<p>It should be clear that this sort of personal and professional support is the work of more than just one person. One of the strengths of a digital humanities center embedded in a library like this one at UVA is that fellows have the readymade potential to brush up against a variety of career options that become revealed when peaking outside of their disciplinary silos: digital humanities developers and project manager positions, sure, but also metadata specialists, archivists, and more. I think this kind of cross-pollination should be encouraged: library faculty and staff have a lot to offer student fellows and vice versa. Developing these relationships brings the fellows further into the kinds of the work done in the library and introduces them to careers that, while they might require further study to obtain, could be real options.</p>

<p>To my mind the best fellowship programs are those fully aware of their institutional context and those that both leverage and augment the resources around them as they are able. We have been working hard on this at W&amp;L. We are starting to institute a series of workshops led by the undergraduate fellows in consultation with the administrators of the fellowship program. The idea is that past fellows lead workshops for later cohorts on the technology they have learned, some of which we selectively open to the broader library faculty and staff. The process helps to solidify the student’s training – no better way to learn than to teach – but it also helps to expand the student community by retaining fellows as committed members. It also helps to fill out a student’s portfolio with a cv-ready line of teaching experience. This process also aims to build our own capacity within the library by distributing skills among a wider array of students, faculty, and staff. After all, student fellows and librarians have much they could learn from one another. I see the Head of Graduate Programs as facilitating such collaborations, as connecting the interested student with the engaged faculty/staff/librarian collaborator, inside their institution or beyond.</p>

<p>But we must not forget that we are asking students and junior faculty to do risky things by developing these new interests, by spending time and energy on digital projects, let alone presenting and writing on them in professional contexts. The biggest risk is that we ask them to do so without supporting them adequately. All the technical training in the world means little if that work is illegible and irrelevant to your colleagues or committee. <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide16.jpg" alt="Fitzpatrick Slide" /> In the words of Kathleen Fitzpatrick, we ask these students to “do the risky thing,” but we must “make sure that someone’s got their back.” I see the Head of Graduate Programs as the key in coordinating, fostering, and providing such care.</p>

<p>Students and junior faculty need support – for technical implementation, sure – but they also need advocates – people who can vouch for the quality of their work and campaign on their behalf in the face of committees and faculty who might be otherwise unable to see the value of their work. Some of this can come from the library, from people able to put this work in the context of guidelines for the evaluation of digital scholarship. But some of this support and advocacy has to come from within their home departments. The question is really how to build up that support from the outside in. And that’s a long, slow process that occurs by making meaningful connections and through outreach programs. At W&amp;L, we have worked to develop an <a href="http://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/initiatives/incentive-grants/">incentive grant program</a>, where we incentivize faculty members who might be new to digital humanities or otherwise skeptical to experiment with incorporating a digital project into their course. The result is a slow burn – we get maybe one or two new faculty each term trying something out. That might seem small, but it’s something, particularly at a small liberal arts college. This kind of slow evangelizing is key in helping the work done by digital humanists to be legible to everyone. Students and junior faculty need advocates for their work in and out of the library and their home departments, and the person in this position is tasked with overseeing such outreach.</p>

<p>So, to return to the opening motif, lists of skillsets certainly have their place as we bring new people into the ever-expanding field: they’re necessary. They reflect a philosophy and a vision, and they’re the basis of growing real initiatives. But it’s the job of the Head of Graduate Programs to make sure that we never lose sight of the people and relationships behind them.</p>

<p>Foremost, then, I see the Head of Graduate Programs as someone who takes the lists, documents, and curricula that I have discussed and connects them to the people that serve them and that they are meant to speak to. This person is one who builds relationships, who navigates the prepositions of my title. <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide17.jpg" alt="Title Slide Last" /> It’s the job of such a person to blast the boundary between “you’re in” and “you’re out” so that the tech-adverse or shy student can find a seat at the table. This is someone who makes sure that the work of the fellows is represented across institutions and in their own departments. This person makes sure the fellows are well positioned professionally. This person builds up people and embeds them to networks where they can flourish. Their job is never to forget what it’s like to be the person trying to learn. Their job is to hear “I’m not a tech person” and answer “not yet, but you could be! and I know just the people to help. Let’s learn together.”</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
