<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: talks | Brandon Walsh]]></title>
  <link href="https://walshbr.com/blog/categories/talks/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://walshbr.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-05-09T07:06:46-04:00</updated>
  <id>https://walshbr.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brandon Walsh]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[In, Out, Across, With: Collaborative Education and Digital Humanities (Job Talk for Scholars' Lab)]]></title>
    <link href="https://walshbr.com/blog/2017/03/02/in-out-across-with/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-02T09:31:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://walshbr.com/blog/2017/03/02/in-out-across-with</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>[Crossposted on the <a href="https://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/blog/2017/03/06/in-out-across-with-collaborative-education-and-digital-humanities-job-talk-for-scholars-lab/">WLUDH blog</a> and the <a href="http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/in-out-across-with-collaborative-education-and-digital-humanities-job-talk-for-head-of-graduate-programs/">Scholars’ Lab blog</a>]</em></p>

<p>I’ve accepted a new position as the <a href="http://scholarslab.org/uncategorized/brandon-walsh-is-our-new-head-of-graduate-programs-starting-april-24-2017/">Head of Graduate Programs in the Scholars’ Lab</a>, and I’ll be transitioning into that role over the next few weeks! As a part of the interview process, we had to give a job talk. While putting together this presentation, I was lucky enough to have past examples to work from (as you’ll be able to tell, if you check out this past <a href="http://literaturegeek.com/2016/02/28/DHjobtalk">job talk</a> by Amanda Visconti). Since my new position will involve helping graduate students through the process of applying for positions like these, it only feels right that I should post my own job talk as well as a few words on the thinking that went into it. Blemishes, jokes, and all, hopefully these materials will help someone in the future find a way in, just as the example of others did for me. And if you’re looking for more, Visconti has a great list of other examples linked from her <a href="http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/disrupt-the-humanities-managing-director-job-talk/">more recent job talk</a> for the Scholars’ Lab.</p>

<p>For the presentation, I was asked to respond to this prompt:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What does a student (from undergraduate to doctoral levels) need to learn or experience in order to add “DH” to his or her skill set?  Is that an end or a means of graduate education?  Can short-term digital assignments in discipline-specific courses go beyond “teaching with technology”?  Why not refer everyone to online tutorials?  Are there risks for doctoral students or the untenured in undertaking digital projects?  Drawing on your own experience, and offering examples or demonstrations of digital research projects, pedagogical approaches, or initiatives or organizations that you admire, make a case for a vision of collaborative education in advanced digital scholarship in the arts and humanities.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I felt that each question could be a presentation all its own, and I had strong opinions about each one. Dealing with all of them seemed like a tall order. I decided to spend the presentation close reading and deconstructing that first sentence, taking apart the idea that education and/or digital humanities could be thought of in terms of lists of skills at all. Along the way, my plan was to dip into the other questions as able, but I also assumed that I would have plenty of time during the interview day to give my thoughts on them. I also wanted to try to give as honest a sense as possible of the way I approach teaching and mentoring. For me, it’s all about people and giving them the care that they need. In conveying that, I hoped, I would give the sort of vision the prompt was asking for. I also tried to sprinkle references to the past and present of the Scholars’ Lab programs to ground the content of the talk. When I mention potential career options in the body of the talk, I am talking about specific alumni who came through the fellowship programs. And when I mention graduate fellows potentially publishing on their work with the Twitter API, well, <a href="http://scholarslab.org/uncategorized/working-with-an-archive-of-the-now/">that’s not hypothetical either</a>.</p>

<p>So below find the lightly edited text of the talk I gave at the Scholars’ Lab - “In, Out, Across, With: Collaborative Education and Digital Humanities.” I’ve only substantively  modified one piece - swapping out one example for another.</p>

<p>And a final note on delivery: I have heard plenty of people argue over whether it is better to read a written talk or deliver one from notes. My own sense is that the latter is far more common for digital humanities talks. I have seen both fantastic read talks and amazing extemporaneous performances, just as I have seen terrible versions of each. My own approach is, increasingly, to write a talk but deliver that talk more or less from memory. In this case, I had a pretty long commute to work, so I recorded myself reading the talk and listened to it a lot to get the ideas in my head. When I gave the presentation, I had the written version in front of me for reference, but I was mostly moving through my own sense of how it all fit together in real time (and trying to avoid looking at the paper). My hope is that this gave me the best of both worlds and resulted in a structured but engaging performance. Your mileage may vary!</p>

<h2 id="in-out-across-with-collaborative-education-and-digital-humanities">In, Out, Across, With: Collaborative Education and Digital Humanities</h2>

<p><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/job-talk-slides/slide01.jpg" alt="Title slide" /> It’s always a treat to be able to talk with the members of the UVA Library community, and I am very grateful to be here. For those of you that don’t know me, I am Brandon Walsh, Mellon Digital Humanities Fellow and Visiting Assistant Professor of English at Washington and Lee University. The last time I was here, I gave a talk that had almost exclusively animal memes for slides. I can’t promise the same robust Internet culture in this talk, but talk to me after and I can hook you up. I swear I’ve still got it.</p>

<p><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/job-talk-slides/slide02.jpg" alt="Zotero slide" /> In the spirit of Amanda Visconti, the resources that went into this talk (and a number of foundational materials on the subject) can all be found in a Zotero collection at the <a href="https://goo.gl/r6MCwD">above link</a>. I’ll name check any that are especially relevant, but hopefully this set of materials will allow the thoughts in the talk to flower outwards for any who are interested in seeing its origins and echoes in the work of others.</p>

<p><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/job-talk-slides/slide03.jpg" alt="Thank you slide" /> And a final prefatory note: no person works, thinks or learns alone, so here are the names of the people in my talk whose thinking I touch upon as well as just some – but not all – of my colleagues at W&amp;L who collaborate on the projects I mention. Top tier consists of people I cite or mention, second tier is for institutions or publications important to discussion, and final tier is for direct collaborators on this work.</p>

<p>Today I want to talk to you about how best to champion the people involved in collaborative education in digital research. I especially want to talk about students. And when I mention “students” throughout this talk, I will mostly be speaking in the context of graduate students. But most of what I discuss will be broadly applicable to all newcomers to digital research. My talk is an exhortation to find ways to elevate the voices of people in positions like these to be contributors to professional and institutional conversations from day one and to empower them to define the methods and the outcomes of the digital humanities that we teach. This means taking seriously the messy, fraught, and emotional process of guiding students through digital humanities methods, research, and careers. It means advocating for the legibility of this digital work as a key component of their professional development. And it means enmeshing these voices in the broader network around them, the local context that they draw upon for support and that they can enrich in turn. I believe it is the mission of the Head of Graduate Programs to build up this community and facilitate these networks, to incorporate those who might feel like outsiders to the work that we do. Doing so enriches and enlivens our communities and builds a better and more diverse research and teaching agenda. <img src="{{ root_url }}/images/job-talk-slides/slide04.jpg" alt="Title Slide 2" /> This talk is titled “In, Out, Across, With: Collaborative Education and Digital Humanities,” and I’ll really be focusing on the prepositions of my title as a metaphor for the nature of this sort of position. I see this role as one of connection and relation. The talk runs about 24 minutes, so we should have plenty of time to talk.</p>

<p>When discussing digital humanities education, it is tempting to first and foremost discuss what, exactly, it is that you will be teaching. What should the students walk away knowing? To some extent, just as there is more than one way to make breakfast, you could devise numerous baseline curricula. <img src="{{ root_url }}/images/job-talk-slides/slide05.jpg" alt="W&amp;L Skills" /> </p>

<p>This is what we came up with at Washington and Lee for students in our <a href="http://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/initiatives/undergraduate-fellowship/">undergraduate digital humanities fellowship program</a>. We tried to hit a number of kinds of skills that a practicing digital humanist might need. It’s by no means exhaustive, but the list is a way to start. We don’t expect one person to come away knowing everything, so instead we aim for students to have an introduction to a wide variety of technologies by the end of a semester or year. They’ll encounter some technologies applicable to project management, some to front-end design, as well as a variety of programming concepts broadly applicable to a variety of situations. Lists like this give some targets to hit. But still, even as someone who helped put this list together, it makes me worry a bit. I can imagine younger me being afraid of it! It’s easy for us to forget what it was like to be new, to be a beginner, to be learning for the first time, but I’d like to return us to that frame of thinking. I think we should approach lists like these with care, because they can be intimidating for the newcomer. So in my talk today I want to argue against lists of skills as ways of thinking.</p>

<p>I don’t mean to suggest that programs need no curriculum, nor do I mean to suggest that no skills are necessary to be a digital humanist. But I would caution against focusing too much on the skills that one should have at the end of a program, particularly when talking about people who haven’t yet begun to learn. I would wager that many people on the outside looking in think of DH in the same way: it’s a big list of unknowns. I’d like to get away from that.</p>

<p>Templates like this are important for developing courses, fellowship, and degree-granting programs, but I worry that the goodwill in them might all too easily seem like a form of gatekeeping to a new student. It is easy to imagine telling a student that “you have to learn GitHub before you can work on this project.” It’s just a short jump from this to a likely student response - “ah sorry - I don’t know that yet.” And from there I can all too easily imagine the common refrain that you hear from students of all levels - “If I can’t get that, then it’s because I’m not a technology person.” From there - “Digital humanities must not be for me.”</p>

<p>Instead of building our curricula out of as-yet-unknown tool chains, I want to float, today, a vision of DH education as an introduction to a series of professional practices. Lists of skills might be ends but I fear they might foreclose beginnings. <img src="{{ root_url }}/images/job-talk-slides/slide06.jpg" alt="SCI Slide" /> Instead, I will float something more in line with that of the Scholarly Communication Institute (held here at UVA for a time), which outlined what they saw as the needs of graduate and professional students in the digital age. I’ll particularly draw upon their first point here (last of my slides with tons of text, I swear): graduate students need training in “collaborative modes of knowledge production and sharing.” </p>

<p>I want to think about teaching DH as introducing a process of discovery that collapses hierarchies between expert and newcomer: that’s a way to start. This sort of framing offers digital humanities not as a series of methods one does or does not know, but, rather, as a process that a group can engage in together. Do they learn methods and skills in the process? Of course! Anyone who has taken part in the sort of collaborative group projects undertaken by the Scholars’ Lab comes away knowing more than they came in with. But I want to continue thinking about process and, in particular, how that process can be more inclusive and more engaging. By empowering students to choose what they want to learn and how they want to learn it, we can help to expand the reach of our work and better serve our students as mentors and collaborators. There are a few different in ways in which I see this as taking place, and they’ll form the roadmap for the rest of the talk. <img src="{{ root_url }}/images/job-talk-slides/slide07.jpg" alt="Roadmap Slide" /> Apologies - this looks like the sort of slide you would get at a business retreat. All the same - we need to adapt and develop new professional opportunities for our students at the same time that we plan flexible outcomes for our educational programs. These approaches are meant to serve increasingly diverse professional needs in a changing job market, and they need to be matched by deepening support at the institutional level.</p>

<p>So to begin. One of our jobs as mentors is to encourage students to seek out professionally legible opportunities early on in their careers, and as shapers of educational programs we can go further and create new possibilities for them. At W&amp;L, we have been <a href="https://github.com/wludh/research-one-collab">collaborating with the Scholars’ Lab</a> to bring UVA graduate students to teach short-form workshops on digital research in W&amp;L classrooms. Funded opportunities like this one can help students professionalize in new ways and in new contexts while paying it forward to the nearby community. A similar initiative at W&amp;L that I’ve been working on has our own library faculty and undergraduate fellows visiting local high schools to speak with advanced AP computer science students about how their own programming work can apply to humanities disciplines. I’m happy to talk more about these in Q&amp;A.</p>

<p><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/job-talk-slides/slide08.jpg" alt="Student slide" /> We also have our student collaborators present at conferences, both on their own work and on work they have done with faculty members, both independently and as co-presenters. Here is Abdur, one of our undergraduate Mellon DH fellows, talking about the writing he does for his thesis and how it is enriched by and different from the writing he does in digital humanities contexts at the Bucknell Digital Scholarship Conference last fall. While this sort of thing is standard for graduate students, it’s pretty powerful for an undergraduate to present on research in this way. Learning that it’s OK to fail in public can be deeply empowering, and opportunities like these encourage our students to think about themselves as valuable contributors to ongoing conversations long before they might otherwise feel comfortable doing so. </p>

<p>But teaching opportunities and conferences are not the only ways to get student voices out there. I think there are ways of engaging student voices earlier, at home, in ways that can fit more situations. We can encourage students to engage in professional conversations by developing flexible outcomes in which we are equal participants. One approach to this with which I have been experimenting is group writing, which I think is undervalued as a taught skill and possible approach to DH pedagogy. An example: when a history faculty member at W&amp;L approached the library (and by extension, me) for support in supplementing an extant history course with a component about digital text analysis, we could have agreed to offer a series of one-off workshops and be done with it. <img src="{{ root_url }}/images/job-talk-slides/slide09.jpg" alt="Gitbook slide" /> Instead, this faculty member – Professor Sarah Horowitz – and I decided to collaborate on a more extensive project together, producing <a href="https://www.walshbr.com/textanalysiscoursebook">Introduction to Text Analysis: A Coursebook</a>. The idea was to put the materials for the workshops together ahead of time, in collaboration, and to narrativize them into a set of lessons that would persist beyond a single semester as a kind of publication. The pedagogical labor that we put into reshaping her course could become, in some sense, professionally legible as a series of course modules that others could use beyond the term. So for the book, we co-authored a series of units on text analysis and gave feedback on each other’s work, editing and reviewing as well as reconfiguring them for the context of the course. Professor Horowitz provided more of the discipline-specific material that I could not, and I provided the materials more specific to the theories and methods of text analysis. Neither one of us could have written the book without the other.</p>

<p>Professor Horowitz was, in effect, a student in this moment. She was also a teacher and researcher. She was learning at the same time that she produced original scholarly contributions. Even as we worked together, for me this collaborative writing project was also a pedagogical experiment that drew upon the examples of <a href="https://openamlit.pressbooks.com/">Robin DeRosa</a>, <a href="http://workbook.craftingdigitalhistory.ca/">Shawn Graham</a>, and <a href="https://www.hastac.org/collections/field-notes-21st-century-literacies">Cathy Davidson</a>, in particular. <img src="{{ root_url }}/images/job-talk-slides/slide10.jpg" alt="Davidson Slide" /> Davidson taught a graduate course on “21st Century Literacies” where each of her students wrote a chapter that was then collected and published as an open-access book. For us as for Davidson, the process of knowing, the process of uncovering is something that happens together. In public. And it’s documented so that others can benefit. Our teaching labor could become visible and professionally legible, as could the labor that Professor Horowitz put into learning new research skills. As she adapts and tries out ideas, and as we coalesce them into a whole, the writing product is both the means and the end of an introduction to digital humanities.</p>

<p>Professor Horowitz also wanted to learn technical skills herself, and she learned quite a lot through the writing process. Rather than sitting through lectures or being directed to online tutorials by me, I thought she would learn better by engaging with and shaping the material directly. Her course and my materials would be better for it, as she would be helping to bind my lectures and workshops to her course material. The process would also require her to engage with a list of technologies for digital publishing. <img src="{{ root_url }}/images/job-talk-slides/slide11.jpg" alt="Gitbook Toolchain Slide" /> Beyond the text analysis materials and concepts, the process exposed her to a lot of technologies: command line, Markdown, Git for version control, GitHub for project management. In the process of writing this document, in fact, she covered most of the same curriculum as our undergraduate DH fellows. <img src="{{ root_url }}/images/job-talk-slides/slide12.jpg" alt="Fellows Skills Slide" /> She’s learning these things as we work together to produce course materials, but, importantly, the technical skills aren’t the focus of the work together. It’s a writing project! Rather than presenting the skills as ends in themselves, they were the means by which we were publishing a thing. They were immediately useful. And I think displacing the technology is helpful: it means that the outcomes and parameters for success are not based in the technology itself but, rather, in the thinking about and use of those methods. We also used a <a href="https://www.gitbook.com">particular platform</a> that allowed Professor Horowitz to engage with these technologies in a light way so that they would not overwhelm our work – I’m happy to discuss more in the time after if you’re interested. </p>

<p>This to say: the outcomes of such collaborative educations can be shaped to a variety of different settings and types of students. Take another model, <a href="https://digitalfellows.commons.gc.cuny.edu/">CUNY’s Graduate Center Digital Fellows program</a>, whose students develop open tutorials on digital tools. Learning from this example, rather than simply direct students or colleagues towards online tutorials like these, why not have them write their own documents, legible for their own positions, that synthesize and remix the materials that they already have found? <img src="{{ root_url }}/images/job-talk-slides/slide13.jpg" alt="Programming Historian Slide" /> The learning process becomes something productive in this framing. I can imagine, for example, directing collaboratively authored materials by students like these towards something like <a href="http://programminghistorian.org/">The Programming Historian</a>. If you’re not familiar, The Programming Historian offers a variety of lessons on digital humanities methods, and they only require an outline as a pitch to their editorial team, not a whole written publication ready to go. Your graduate students could, say, work with the Twitter API over the course of a semester, blog about the research outcomes, and then pitch a tutorial to The Programming Historian on the API as a result of their work. It’s much easier to motivate yourselves to write something if you know that the publication has already been accepted. Obviously such acceptance is not a given, but working towards a goal like this can offer student researchers something to aim for. Their instructors could co-author these materials, even, so that everyone has skin in the game.</p>

<p>This model changes the shape of what collaborative education can look like: it’s duration and its results. You don’t need a whole fellowship year. You could, in a reasonably short amount of time, tinker and play, and produce a substantial blog post, an article pitch, or a Library Research Guide (more on that in a moment). </p>

<p><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/job-talk-slides/slide14.jpg" alt="Jarvis Quote Slide" />As Jeff Jarvis has said, “we need to move students up the education chain.” And trust me - the irony of quoting a piece titled “Lectures are Bullshit” during a lecture to you is not lost on me. But stay with me. </p>

<p>Collaborative writing projects on DH topics are flexible enough to fit the many contexts for the kind of educational work that we do. After all, no one needs or values the same outcomes, and these shared and individual goals need to be worked out in conversation with the students themselves early on. Articulating these desires in a frank, written, and collaborative mode early on (in the genre of <a href="http://praxis.scholarslab.org/charter/">the project charter</a>), can help the program directors to better shape the work to fit the needs of the students. But I also want to suggest that collaborative writing projects can be useful end products as well as launching pads, as they can fit the shape of many careers. After all, students come to digital humanities for a variety of different reasons. Some might be aiming to bolster a research portfolio on the path to a traditional academic career. Others might be deeply concerned about the likelihood of attaining such a position and be looking for other career options. Others still might instead be colleagues interested in expanding their research portfolio or skillset but unable to commit to a whole year of work on top of their current obligations. Writing projects could speak to all these situations.</p>

<p>I see someone in charge of shaping graduate programs as needing to speak to these diverse needs. This person is both a steward of where students currently are – the goals and objectives they might currently have – as well as of where they might go – the potential lives they might (or might not!) lead. After all, graduate school, like undergraduate, is an enormously stressful time of personal and professional exploration. If we think simply about a student’s professional development as a process of finding a job, we overlook the real spaces in which help might be most desired. Frequently, those needs are the anxieties, stresses, and pressures of refashioning yourself as a professional. We should not be in the business of creating CV lines or providing lists of qualifications alone. We should focus on creating strong, well-adjusted professionals by developing ethical programs that guide them into the professional world by caring for them as people. </p>

<p>In the graduate context, this involves helping students deal with the academic job market in particular. <img src="{{ root_url }}/images/job-talk-slides/slide15.jpg" alt="Rogers Slide" /> To me in its best form, this means helping students to look at their academic futures and see proliferating possibilities instead of a narrow and uncertain route to a single job, to paraphrase the work of Katina Rogers. A sprinkler rather than a pipeline, in her metaphor. As Rogers’s work, in particular, has shown, recent graduate students increasingly feel that, while they experienced strong expectations that they would continue in the professoriate, they received inadequate preparation for the many different careers they might actually go on to have. <a href="praxis.scholarslab.org">The Praxis Program</a> and the <a href="http://praxis-network.org/">Praxis Network</a> are good examples of how to position digital humanities education as answers to these issues. Fellowship opportunities like these must be robust enough that they can offer experiences and outcomes beyond the purely technical, so that a project manager from one fellowship year can graduate with an MA and go into industry in a similar role just as well-prepared as a PhD student aiming to be a developer might go on to something entirely different. And the people working these programs must be prepared for the messy labor of helping students to realize that these are satisfactory, laudable professional goals.</p>

<p>It should be clear that this sort of personal and professional support is the work of more than just one person. One of the strengths of a digital humanities center embedded in a library like this one at UVA is that fellows have the readymade potential to brush up against a variety of career options that become revealed when peaking outside of their disciplinary silos: digital humanities developers and project manager positions, sure, but also metadata specialists, archivists, and more. I think this kind of cross-pollination should be encouraged: library faculty and staff have a lot to offer student fellows and vice versa. Developing these relationships brings the fellows further into the kinds of the work done in the library and introduces them to careers that, while they might require further study to obtain, could be real options. </p>

<p>To my mind the best fellowship programs are those fully aware of their institutional context and those that both leverage and augment the resources around them as they are able. We have been working hard on this at W&amp;L. We are starting to institute a series of workshops led by the undergraduate fellows in consultation with the administrators of the fellowship program. The idea is that past fellows lead workshops for later cohorts on the technology they have learned, some of which we selectively open to the broader library faculty and staff. The process helps to solidify the student’s training – no better way to learn than to teach – but it also helps to expand the student community by retaining fellows as committed members. It also helps to fill out a student’s portfolio with a cv-ready line of teaching experience. This process also aims to build our own capacity within the library by distributing skills among a wider array of students, faculty, and staff. After all, student fellows and librarians have much they could learn from one another. I see the Head of Graduate Programs as facilitating such collaborations, as connecting the interested student with the engaged faculty/staff/librarian collaborator, inside their institution or beyond. </p>

<p>But we must not forget that we are asking students and junior faculty to do risky things by developing these new interests, by spending time and energy on digital projects, let alone presenting and writing on them in professional contexts. The biggest risk is that we ask them to do so without supporting them adequately. All the technical training in the world means little if that work is illegible and irrelevant to your colleagues or committee. <img src="{{ root_url }}/images/job-talk-slides/slide16.jpg" alt="Fitzpatrick Slide" /> In the words of Kathleen Fitzpatrick, we ask these students to “do the risky thing,” but we must “make sure that someone’s got their back.” I see the Head of Graduate Programs as the key in coordinating, fostering, and providing such care. </p>

<p>Students and junior faculty need support – for technical implementation, sure – but they also need advocates – people who can vouch for the quality of their work and campaign on their behalf in the face of committees and faculty who might be otherwise unable to see the value of their work. Some of this can come from the library, from people able to put this work in the context of guidelines for the evaluation of digital scholarship. But some of this support and advocacy has to come from within their home departments. The question is really how to build up that support from the outside in. And that’s a long, slow process that occurs by making meaningful connections and through outreach programs. At W&amp;L, we have worked to develop an <a href="http://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/initiatives/incentive-grants/">incentive grant program</a>, where we incentivize faculty members who might be new to digital humanities or otherwise skeptical to experiment with incorporating a digital project into their course. The result is a slow burn – we get maybe one or two new faculty each term trying something out. That might seem small, but it’s something, particularly at a small liberal arts college. This kind of slow evangelizing is key in helping the work done by digital humanists to be legible to everyone. Students and junior faculty need advocates for their work in and out of the library and their home departments, and the person in this position is tasked with overseeing such outreach. </p>

<p>So, to return to the opening motif, lists of skillsets certainly have their place as we bring new people into the ever-expanding field: they’re necessary. They reflect a philosophy and a vision, and they’re the basis of growing real initiatives. But it’s the job of the Head of Graduate Programs to make sure that we never lose sight of the people and relationships behind them.</p>

<p>Foremost, then, I see the Head of Graduate Programs as someone who takes the lists, documents, and curricula that I have discussed and connects them to the people that serve them and that they are meant to speak to. This person is one who builds relationships, who navigates the prepositions of my title. <img src="{{ root_url }}/images/job-talk-slides/slide17.jpg" alt="Title Slide Last" /> It’s the job of such a person to blast the boundary between “you’re in” and “you’re out” so that the tech-adverse or shy student can find a seat at the table. This is someone who makes sure that the work of the fellows is represented across institutions and in their own departments. This person makes sure the fellows are well positioned professionally. This person builds up people and embeds them to networks where they can flourish. Their job is never to forget what it’s like to be the person trying to learn. Their job is to hear “I’m not a tech person” and answer “not yet, but you could be! and I know just the people to help. Let’s learn together.”</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hearing Silent Woolf]]></title>
    <link href="https://walshbr.com/blog/2015/03/23/woolf-huskey/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-23T16:37:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://walshbr.com/blog/2015/03/23/woolf-huskey</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>[This week I presented at the <a href="http://gradcouncil.com/2015-sessions/">2015 Huskey Research Exhibition</a> at UVA. The talk was delivered from very schematic notes, but below is a rough recreation of what I discussed. The talk I gave is a crash course in a new project I’ve started working on with the generous help of the <a href="http://scholarslab.org">Scholars’ Lab</a> that thinks about sound in Virginia Woolf’s career using computational methods. <a href="http://www.ericrochester.com/">Eric Rochester</a>, especially, has been endlessly giving of his time and expertise, helping me think through and prototype work on this material. The talk wound up receiving first prize for the digital humanities panel of which I was a part. The project is still very much inchoate, and I’d welcome thoughts on it.]</em></p>

<p>When I talk to you, you make certain assumptions about me as a person based on what you’re hearing. You decide whether or not I might be worth paying attention to, and you develop a sense of our social relations based around the sound of my voice. The voice conveys and generates assumptions about the body and about power: am I making myself heard? Am I registering as a speaking voice? Am I worth listening to?</p>

<p><a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Day_14_Occupy_Wall_Street_September_30_2011_Shankbone_2.JPG "><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/occupy.jpg" width="60%" class="left" /></a></p>

<p>The human microphone, made famous by Occupy Wall Street, nicely encapsulates the social dimensions of sound that interest me: one person speaks, and the people around her repeat what she says more loudly, again and again, amplifying the human voice without technology. Sound literally moves through multiple bodies and structures the social relations between people, and the whole movement is an attempt to make a group of people heard by those who would rather not listen.</p>

<p>As a literary scholar, I am interested in how texts can speak in similar ways. The texts we read frequently contain large amounts of speech within them: conversations, monologues, poetic voice, etc. We talk about sound in texts all the time, and the same social and political dimensions of sound still remain even if a text appears silent on the page. If who can be heard and who gets to speak are both contested questions in the real world, they continue to structure our experiences of printed universes.</p>

<p>All of this brings me to the quotation mark. The humble piece of punctuation does a lot of work for us every day, and I want to think more closely about how it can help us understand how texts speak. The quotation mark is the most obvious point at which sound meets text. Computational methods tend to focus on the vocabulary of a text as the building blocks of meaning, but they can also help us turn quotation marks into objects of inquiry. Quotation marks can tell us a lot about how texts engage with the human voice, but there are <em>lots</em> of them in texts. Digital methods can help us make sense of the scale.</p>

<p><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/woolf.jpg" width="40%" class="right" />I examine Virginia Woolf’s quotation marks, in particular, for a number of reasons. Aesthetically, we can see her bridging the Victorian and modernist literary periods, though she tends to fall in with the latter of the two. Politically, she lived through periods of intense social and political upheaval at the beginning of the twentieth century. Very few recordings of Woolf remain, but she nonetheless thought deeply about sound recording. The worldwide market for gramophones exploded during her lifetime, and her texts frequently featured technologies of sound reproduction. Woolf’s gramophones frequently malfunction in her novels, and I’m interested in seeing how her quotation marks might analogously be irregular or broken intentionally. Woolf is especially good for thinking about punctuation marks in this way: she owned a printing press, and she often set type herself. </p>

<p>The following series of histograms gives a rough estimation of how Woolf’s use of quotation changes over the course of her career. <a href="https://github.com/erochest/woolf/commits/master">On GitHub</a> you can find the script I’ve been working on with Eric to generate these results. The number of quotations is plotted on the y-axis against their position in the novel on the x-axis, so each histogram represents more quoted speech with higher bars and more concentrated darknesses. If you have an especially good understanding of a particular novel, <em>Mrs. Dalloway</em>, say, you could pick out moments of intense conversation based on sudden spikes in the number of quotations. The histograms are organized in such a way that to read chronologically through Woolf’s career you would read left to right line by line, as you would the text of a book. The top-left histogram is Woolf’s earliest novel, the bottom-right corner her last.</p>

<p><a href="{{ root_url }}/images/huskey-histograms/1915_the_voyage_out.jpg"><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/huskey-histograms/1915_the_voyage_out.jpg" width="32%" /></a>
<a href="{{ root_url }}/images/huskey-histograms/1919_night_and_day.jpg"><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/huskey-histograms/1919_night_and_day.jpg" width="32%" /></a>
<a href="{{ root_url }}/images/huskey-histograms/1922_jacobs_room.jpg"><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/huskey-histograms/1922_jacobs_room.jpg" width="32%" /></a>
<a href="{{ root_url }}/images/huskey-histograms/1925_mrs.dalloway.jpg"><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/huskey-histograms/1925_mrs.dalloway.jpg" width="32%" /></a>
<a href="{{ root_url }}/images/huskey-histograms/1927_to_the_lighthouse.jpg"><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/huskey-histograms/1927_to_the_lighthouse.jpg" width="32%" /></a>
<a href="{{ root_url }}/images/huskey-histograms/1928_orlando.jpg"><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/huskey-histograms/1928_orlando.jpg" width="32%" /></a>
<a href="{{ root_url }}/images/huskey-histograms/1931_the_waves.jpg"><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/huskey-histograms/1931_the_waves.jpg" width="32%" /></a>
<a href="{{ root_url }}/images/huskey-histograms/1937_the_years.jpg"><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/huskey-histograms/1937_the_years.jpg" width="32%" /></a>
<a href="{{ root_url }}/images/huskey-histograms/1941_between_the_acts.jpg"><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/huskey-histograms/1941_between_the_acts.jpg" width="32%" /></a></p>

<p>To my eye, the output suggests high concentrations of conversation in the novels at the beginning and ending of Woolf’s career. We can see that her middle period, especially, appears to have a significant decrease in the amount of quoted speech. In one sense, this might make sense to someone familiar with Woolf’s career. Her first two novels feel more typically Victorian in their aesthetics, and she really gets into the thick of modernist experiment with her third novel. One way we often describe the shift from Victorian to the modernist period is as a shift inward, away from society and towards the psychology of the self. So it makes sense that we might see the amount of conversation between multiple speaking bodies significantly fall away over the course of those novels. <a href="{{ root_url }}/images/huskey-histograms/1931_the_waves.jpg">The seventh histogram</a> is especially interesting, because it suggests the least amount of speech of anything in her corpus. But if we visualize things a different way, we see that this novel, <em>The Waves</em>, actually shows a huge spike in punctuated speech. This graph represents the percentage of each text that is contained within quotation marks, the amount of text represented as punctuated speech.</p>

<p><a href="{{ root_url }}/images/huskey-histograms/percentage-quoted.jpg"><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/huskey-histograms/percentage-quoted.jpg" class="right" /></a></p>

<p>This might look like a problem with the data: how could the text with the fewest number of quotations also have the highest percentage of quoted speech? But the script is actually giving me exactly what I asked for: <em>The Waves</em> is a series of monologues by six disembodied voices, and the amount of non-speech text is extremely small. More generally, charting the percentage of quoted speech in the corpus appears to support my general readings of the original nine histograms: roughly three times as much punctuated speech in the early novels as in the middle period, with a slight leveling off in the end of her career. </p>

<p>We could think of <em>The Waves</em> as an anomaly, but I think it more clearly calls for a revision of such a reading of speech in Woolf’s career. The spike in quoted speech is a hint that there is something else going on in Woolf’s work. Perhaps we can use the example of <em>The Waves</em> to propose that there might be a range of discourses, of types of speech in Woolf’s corpus. Before I suggested that speech diminished in the middle of Woolf’s career, but that’s not exactly true. My suspicion is that it just enters a different mode. Consider these two passages, both quoted from <em>Mrs. Dalloway</em>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Mrs. Dalloway said she would buy the flowers herself.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Times without number Clarissa had visited Evelyn Whitbread in a nursing home.  Was Evelyn ill again?  Evelyn was a good deal out of sorts, said Hugh, intimating by a kind of pout or swell of his very well-covered, manly, extremely handsome, perfectly upholstered body (he was almost too well dressed always, but presumably had to be, with his little job at Court) that his wife had some internal ailment, nothing serious, which, as an old friend, Clarissa Dalloway would quite understand without requiring him to specify.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In each case, the text implies speech by Mrs. Dalloway and by Hugh without marking it as such with punctuation marks. Discourse becomes submerged in the texture of the narrative, but it doesn’t disappear entirely. Moments like these suggest a range of discourses in Woolf’s corpus: dialogue, monologue, conversation, punctuated, implied, etc. All of these speech types have different implications, but it’s difficult to get a handle on them because of their scale. I began the project by simply trying to mark down moments of implied speech in <em>Mrs. Dalloway</em> by hand. Once I got to about two hundred, it seemed like it was time to ask the computer for help.</p>

<p>The current plan moving forward is to build a corpus of test passages containing both quoted speech and implied speech, train a python script against this set of passages, and then use this same script to search for instances of implied speech throughout Woolf’s corpus. Theoretically, at least, the script will search for a series of words that flag text as implied speech to a human reader - said, recalled, exclaimed, etc. Using this lexicon as a basis, the script would then pull out the context surrounding these words to produce a database of sentences meant to serve as speech. At Eric’s suggestion, I’m currently exploring the <a href="http://www.nltk.org/index.html">Natural Language Toolkit</a> to take a stab at all of this. My own hypothesis is that there will be an inverse relationship between quoted speech and implied speech in her corpus, that the amount of speech left unflagged by quotation marks will increase in the middle of Woolf’s career. Once I have all this material, I’ll be able to subject the results to further analysis and to think more deeply about speech in Woolf’s work. Who speaks? What about? What counts as a voice, and what is left in an ambiguous, unsounded state? </p>

<p>The project is very much in its beginning stages, but it’s already opening up the way that I think about speech in Woolf’s text. It tries to untangle the relationship between our print record and our sonic record, and further work will help show how discourse is unfolding over time in the modernist period.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Collation and Writing Pedagogy]]></title>
    <link href="https://walshbr.com/blog/2015/01/17/collation/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-17T09:41:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://walshbr.com/blog/2015/01/17/collation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[The following is the talk that I gave at the 2015 MLA Conference on a panel on “Pedagogy and Digital Editions.” The Google Docs section is a slight reworking and recontextualization of a <a href="http://walshbr.github.io/blog/2013/09/25/writing-out-loud/">previous post</a> on the subject. I’m especially grateful to <a href="https://twitter.com/damozel_">Sarah Storti</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/andrew_stauffer">Andrew Stauffer</a> for their suggestions and comments on how to use Juxta Commons to teach writing.]</p>

<p><strong>Collation and Writing Pedagogy with Juxta Commons and Google Docs</strong></p>

<p>We typically think about using digital collation to compare those documents that already exist. The usual model gathers multiple copies, multiple witnesses, of the same text, and juxtaposes them to gather a sense of the very small, micro changes that have been made to a document. We use these changes to deconstruct our sense of a complete and unified final whole. Instead, we get a sense of a series of related texts, of a work manifesting in different forms, and of stages of a revision process for which we were not present. I am especially interested in the last of these categories: collation tools allow us to uncover revision histories that might be otherwise obscured. They help us to uncover past stages of the writing process, breaking apart a text that might seem concrete and fixed and make it appear fluid and subject to change. </p>

<p>The illusion of a final unified text is a problem for textual editing, and collation tools have helped us to solve it for decades. This same problem, the tendency to think of texts as final objects with no prior histories, is at its core one of the key difficulties facing student writers. There is a danger for students to think of writing as crafting a marble structure – you chip away at it piece by piece until it forms a perfect, fixed form – the form it was meant to possess all along. Instead, I want to argue that collation tools can be used by teachers to help students conceive of writing as a kind of assemblage, a piecing together that instantiates one possible combination among many of a set of textual components. This mode of writing is, by contrast, characterized by play, transformation, and fluidity.  </p>

<p>I will talk about two tools today in this context - <a href="http://juxtacommons.org/">Juxta Commons</a> and <a href="http://www.google.com/docs/about/">Google Docs</a> – and the exercises I use with each. The former is a collation tool proper, and, while the latter is more typically used for collaborative writing, it lends itself quite readily to the practice. So my focus here is on the practical – how to think about and use these tools for to teach writing and revision. I hope to tease out more of their implications in the discussion.</p>

<p><strong>Juxta Commons</strong></p>

<p>Juxta Commons, probably familiar to many, is the latest iteration of Juxta, a piece of software that allows a user to upload multiple textual witnesses and, at a glance, discern the differences. The tool’s digital nature means that the process is quantified and streamlined – no laboring over the collator. It also has the benefit of offering a number of visualizations for graphically understanding the differences between two witnesses, a fact that I find helpful for talking about student writing. </p>

<p>A potential writing exercise for use with Juxta is simple: a student writes a paragraph, and they then rewrite that paragraph several times. Finally, the student uploads each version to Juxta before writing a brief reflection on the differences between the drafts. What remains constant? Where do changes cluster? Do these edits indicate any special anxiety or concern with any one particular element of the writing process – transitional sentences, thematic chaining, logic, etc.? Do the ideas themselves stay the same? Fixating on these details can allow students to conceive of writing as an assemblage of various components that result in the illusion of a coherent whole. </p>

<p><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/variants.jpg" width="100%" /></p>

<p>In the example above, the student is writing a grant proposal for his tennis team. In an early draft, the class noted that the writing held the team at too much of a remove when the author wanted to stress its importance to him as a second family. Such a charge can seem like a big task, but processing the paragraph through the Juxta assignment throws into sharp relief the minute edits created in a revision to create such systemic change. Comparing the two revisions in Juxta, we can see that, by and large, the student revised the subjects of this first paragraph. “I” becomes “we,” and “friends” will become a “family.” He works to increase the sense of unity among the group of people he describes, a unity that will later become essential in his argument that the organization provides more to the community than just a place to play sports. The Juxta assignment allows a student better insight into how each of these component pieces can easily be sent into motion and radically change the character of the whole document. A large, sweeping suggestion like “adjust your tone” becomes revision by way of a thousand moving pieces. Much more doable.</p>

<p>Juxta Commons has the added bonus of being envisioned as a commons - an online community of textual scholars. It is quite easy to share sets with others, and it would take little effort to set up a repository of shared collation sets among a classroom. To encourage objective reflection as a component of writing, I would ask each student to write a short reflection on a different student’s collation set, observing the differences and reflecting on the minute changes that got them there.</p>

<p>Juxta’s strength as a collation tool is also its limitation for the sort of teaching exercise that I am describing. Juxta has the benefit of being quantitative: its visualizations can offer users quick and accurate depictions of things that might otherwise go unrecognized – a missing comma, or a single different word. Juxta works best with large documents that are largely the same. But if the corresponding passages become too different Juxta will be thrown into disarray. </p>

<p><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/too_much_difference.jpg" width="100%" /></p>

<p>While it is very good at processing texts to find small differences, the software does not quite work if the documents are too different from one another. Its system allows for either exact similarity or difference at the level of character. It cannot tell, for example, if you have reworded a particular phrase or removed it entirely. The paragraph in this example was heavily rewritten, with only a few words in common between the two drafts. While this sort of at a glance collation could be useful to identify revised sections in longer documents, it does little to unsettle the idea of writing as a search for a fully realized whole. Juxta Commons works best for helping students to see the massive change that can be wrought by a collection of small changes.</p>

<p><strong>Google Docs</strong></p>

<p>One of the difficulties with using Juxta to collate is that it relies on a student’s already extant drafts – revision must already have taken place, which seems to defeat the whole purpose of an exercise designed to unsettle the writing process. Google Docs is not a tool made for collation, but I do think that it can helpfully generate just those many witnesses that <strong>could</strong> be collated. By using Google Docs as a collaborative writing space, classmates can help another generate different textual possibilities for a single sentence. My use of Google Docs in conjunction with a discussion of writing first came about in an advanced course on Academic and Professional Writing. We talked a lot about editing in the class, and many of the conversations about style took this shape:</p>

<p>Student A: “Something about this word feels strange, but I don’t know what it is.” <br />
Student B: “What if we moved the phrase to the beginning of the sentence?”<br />
Student C: “We could get rid of that word and use this phrase instead.”  </p>

<p>Those statements are hard to wrap your head around. Just imagine if those conversations were spoken. Talking about writing can only get you so far: writing is graphic, after all. As I write and edit, I try out different options on the page. I model possibilities, but I do so <em>in</em> writing. Discussing the editing process without visual representations of suggested changes can make things too abstract to be meaningful for students. They need to see the different possibilities, the different potential witnesses. I developed an exercise that I call “Writing Out Loud” that more closely mirrors my actual editing process. Using a Google Doc as a collaborative writing space, students are able to model alternate revisions visually and in real time for discussion.</p>

<p>The setup requires a projector-equipped classroom and that students bring their laptops to class. Circulate the link to the Google Doc ahead of time, taking care that anyone with the link can edit the document. The template of the Google Doc consists of a blank space at the top for displaying the sentence under question and a series of workspaces for each student consisting of their name and a few blank lines. Separate workspaces prevent overlapping revisions, and they also minimize the disorienting effects of having multiple people writing on the same document.</p>

<p><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/WOL_template.jpg" width="40%" class="right" /></p>

<p>We usually turn to the exercise when a student feels a particular sentence is not working but cannot articulate why. When this happens, I put the Writing Out Loud template on the projector with the original version of the sentence at the top. Using their own laptops, students sign onto the Doc and type out alternative versions of the sentence, and the multiple possible revisions show up on the overhead for everyone to see and discuss. After each student rewrites the sentence to be something that they feel works better, ask for volunteers to explain how the changes affect meaning. The whole process only takes a few minutes, and it allows you to abstract writing principles from the actual process of revision rather that the other way around. How does the structure of a sentence matter? How can word choice change everything? What pieces of a sentence are repetitive?</p>

<p><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/WOL_filled.jpg" width="100%" /></p>

<p>I especially like this exercise because it asks multiple students to engage in the revision process. It is always easier to revise when you have critical distance on a piece of writing, and outside editors with no attachment to a particular word or phrase can offer just that. In the above example, the sentence under discussion contained the colloquial phrase “get the word out.” The class offered a range of alternatives that range in their formality. Instead of receiving an edict to professionalize their tone, the student gets a glimpse of many possibilities from which he can choose. The exercise also allows the choices to exist side by side, making collation possible in a way that the usual revision process makes difficult. Most students, I would wager, work with one or, at most, two drafts open at a single time. Google Docs can allow a number of possibilities to emerge.</p>

<p>The Google Docs exercise works better on micro-edits, revisions at the level of the sentence. The standard process of the exercise—write, collate, and discuss—would take far too long with anything longer than a few lines. The exercise can be particularly useful for those sentences that carry a lot of importance for entire arguments: thesis statements, topic sentences, the first sentences of the document, etc. Where Juxta is entirely quantitative and offers hand graphic visualizations of textual difference, this Google Docs exercise relies on you and the students to collate the materials yourselves. You can recognize subtle differences – a reworded idea vs. a dropped idea, for example. It trains students to internalize the practice of collation and reflect on the interpretive possibilities offered by such differences.</p>

<p><strong>Closing Analysis</strong></p>

<p>I find that students often think of editing as an intense, sweeping process that involves wholesale transformation from the ground up. Modeling multiple, slightly different versions of the same sentence can allow for a more concrete discussion of the sweeping rhetorical changes that even the smallest edits can make. In this sense, I think using these tools in the classroom allows students to conceive of a single composition as one instantiation among many. Forcing them to compose several different models means that the writing process will be looser. Collation as composition offers students a subjunctive space wherein they dwell in possibilities. It is a vision of composition as de and reconstruction, as a process that is constantly unfolding.</p>

<p>Digital tools uncover how writing is really always already such a fluid process, and they can allow students to see their own composition process in this way while they are still in the thick of it. Digital collation can offer students the chance to think of their own works as messy, subjunctive spaces, as things in flux. By allowing multiple possible versions of the same text to exist alongside and in relation to one another, they can allow students to slip between different textual realities. Most importantly, the process severs the link between the quality of an idea and the manner of its presentation. Instead of one right answer, students can see that there are many possible solutions to any writing difficulty.</p>

<p>I have touched on how exercises like these can also encourage students to distill writing principles from the process rather than the other way around. They can also help students to discover editorial principals through their own writing. I am imagining here a praxis-oriented approach to teaching textual editing where practice leads to principal, one where scholarly readings might come after a student has written an essay, revised it, and, in effect, produced their own edition of their text. An exercise with Juxta might lead to a discussion of eclectic editions, while Google Docs could lead to a fruitful discussion of accidentals and substantives. I am not suggesting that these sorts of exercises replace the good work performed by studying classic editions, reading about editorial practices, or producing one’s own edition by carrying out the steps of the editorial process. But in a class that has an explicit focus on composition, exercises with tools like Juxta Commons and Google Docs can help connect textual criticism with writing pedagogy.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Devil in the Recording]]></title>
    <link href="https://walshbr.com/blog/2015/01/12/deformance-talk/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-12T10:29:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://walshbr.com/blog/2015/01/12/deformance-talk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[The following is an only slightly modified version of the talk I gave at the <a href="http://ach.org/">ACH</a>’s panel on “Digital Deformance and Scholarly Forms” at the 2015 MLA conference. For more details on how to reverse audio recordings, see my <a href="http://walshbr.github.io/blog/2015/01/05/deformance/">previous post on the subject</a>.]</p>

<p><strong>The Devil in the Recording: Deformative Listening and Sound Reproduction</strong></p>

<p>It’s a well-known fact that you can find the devil in popular music. Simply take Led Zeppelin’s “Stairway to Heaven,” play it backwards, and voila. You’ll get messages for, if not by, the Lord of the Flies. Obviously I’m being facetious. Few, if any, take this claim seriously, but it does offer serious ways to think about deformance in the context of sound recordings, particularly those with linguistic or literary content. The digital method of deformance I’ll speak about today, then, is a simple one. Using open source tools like <a href="http://audacity.sourceforge.net/">Audacity</a>, it’s easier than ever to play recordings backwards, to reverse a sound clip with the flip of a switch. I’ll touch just a bit on the history of such methods as they pertain to music and then speculate as to what they can tell us about approaches to thinking about literary sound recordings. I’m a modernist, and my examples will reflect this bias. My ultimate conclusions are as follows. First: reading backwards juxtaposed against audio reversal reveals the unique character of literary sound recordings to be simultaneously sounded and print, to be audiotextual objects as I call them. Second: deformance can offer us new modes for thinking about media failures and malfunctions that actually do exist constantly and all around us. In particular, audio deformance is something that the modernists were keenly interested in, and deformance as a practice can get us closer to the relationships they had with media.</p>

<p>So here is part of “Stairway to Heaven” backwards. 			</p>

<audio controls=""><source src="{{ root_url }}/mp3s/mla-2015/zeppelin_reversed.mp3" type="audio/mpeg" /><source src="{{ root_url }}/ogg/mla-2015/zeppelin_reversed.ogg" type="audio/ogg" />Your browser does not support this audio format.</audio>

<p>Source: <a href="http://youtu.be/zGsUcPdPWBg?t=47s">http://youtu.be/zGsUcPdPWBg?t=47s</a> </p>

<p>Can’t you hear the devil? The “Stairway to Satan,” as I will call it, suggests that we can find new linguistic content in an already extant sound message. Detractors of the “Stairway to Satan” narrative (numerous on Youtube if you care to check them out) suggest that this is just a function of our minds wanting to make sense of chaos. Is this gibberish? Or is it a collection of scattered sound components that can be reconstituted into a whole? In <a href="http://www2.iath.virginia.edu/jjm2f/old/deform.html">Lisa Samuels and Jerome McGann’s essay on deformance</a> from which this panel takes its cue, they discuss reading Emily Dickinson’s poetry backwards in a mode not too far removed from this discussion. Reading backwards can throw into sharp relief the linguistic components, the very pieces that make up a poem, and at the end of the day, you still have the lines, the words, or even the component letters. It’s possible to reassemble these into semantic meanings. </p>

<p>But sound recordings are something different. They are bound in time in a different way. Daniel Albright in <em>Untwisting the Serpent</em> describes music by way of “Lessing’s famous distinction between the spatially juxtapositive arts of <em>nebeinander</em>, such as painting, sculpture, and architecture, and the temporally progressive arts of <em>nacheinander</em>, such as poetry and music” (9). Our experience of music and poetry depend upon their ability to move forward in time. To put the distinction in the context of deformance: you can move around a sculpture and view it from different angles, but it remains the same sculpture. Deform a musical recording by reversing its waveform, however, and you end with a different musical artifact entirely, one with different component parts. Hence, it can sound like gibberish. </p>

<p><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/waveform-large.jpg" width="50%" class="right" /></p>

<p>Here is the waveform for the Zeppelin clip. The waveform here is a charting of intensity over time, and the reversal literally changes the original artifact. It’s a mirror image, but our ears are hard-pressed to be able to reconnect the new object to its original. Many kinds of deformance you can do on an audio recording would work in the same way – alter the pitches, smash them tighter, stretch them out, etc. You alter that wave, and you get something else entirely. At what point does it become something new?</p>

<p>But some reversed audio still sounds like a recognizable tune. Behind the “Stairway to Satan” claim is a long history behind it of musical reversal and mirroring. Musicians and listeners have been fascinated with the vectored nature of sound for centuries, and composers have experimented with reversal as a spur to creativity for ages. Take this melody. </p>

<video width="320" height="240" controls="">
  <source src="{{ root_url }}/videos/canon-retrogrado.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
Your browser does not support the video tag.
</video>

<p>Source: <a href="http://www.teoria.com/en/reference/q-r/retrograde.php">http://www.teoria.com/en/reference/q-r/retrograde.php</a></p>

<p>The melody of the first ten measures is followed by a retrograde repetition of itself, meaning that it is a musical palindrome. All of the intervals of this first section become reversed and, if you were to fold the melody in upon itself, it would perfectly line up. Playing backwards is itself built into the creative process. The playback reflects this as the bouncing ball literally moves backwards on the page, but, if you were to write it out, it would look quite different. The kind of deformance that I am describing, that Zeppelin conspiracy theorists lament, and that Samuels and McGann suggest – it’s built into the music itself.</p>

<p>The melodic reversal of music like this works because, as Walter Pater taught us, music can be thought of as a “perfect identification of matter and form.” Flip the melody and you do not lose information, you get a new melody. The new object is still discernible as music because it is new music. The addition of linguistic content complicates the question - phonemes when reversed do not necessarily and easily coordinate with other phonemes. A recorded object with linguistic content has two distinct characters, each of which overlap with the other. It’s an obvious point, but one that I think has profound implications. </p>

<p>In Langston Hughes’s 1958 recording of “Motto” in collaboration with Charles Mingus and Leonard Feather, we can start to approach some useful conclusions about what this might all mean. The excerpt starts with an instrumental section and then Hughes comes in. So keep in mind that, in the reversal, we’ll hear the poetry first and then the instrumental part. </p>

<p>“Motto”</p>

<audio controls=""><source src="{{ root_url }}/mp3s/mla-2015/motto.mp3" type="audio/mpeg" /><source src="{{ root_url }}/ogg/mla-2015/5_motto.ogg" type="audio/ogg" />Your browser does not support this audio format.</audio>

<p>“Motto” Reversed</p>

<audio controls=""><source src="{{ root_url }}/mp3s/mla-2015/motto_reversed.mp3" type="audio/mpeg" /><source src="{{ root_url }}/ogg/mla-2015/motto_reversed.ogg" type="audio/ogg" />Your browser does not support this audio format.</audio>

<p>The recording is a useful analogy for vocal sound recordings more generally in that it has two distinct pieces – a musical (non-verbal sound) component, and a recorded voice (with linguistic content). The two elements often intertwine and are not easily separated (this example not withstanding). You can hear, I think, the stark difference between the reversed poetic content by Hughes and the reversed instrumental content. Hughes reversed sounds like nonsense, while the saxophone in particular still sounds like something of a melody. The digital reversal of sound recordings treats them both as waveforms with no semantic content – it reverses them just as easily and happily as it would any other sound recording. </p>

<p>We might expect the practice of deformance to throw into sharp relief the status of these recordings as sound objects. The pops, silences, and phonetic meanings of a reading suddenly become especially salient, and we might expect this reversal to make us hyper-aware of their sounded nature. In theory the deformance of these recordings more easily allows us to practice what Charles Bernstein has called “close listening,” examining the sounded nature of these objects. But, as the sounds themselves become distorted almost beyond recognition, the method can only provide clues towards such a practice. We might gain general senses, as with the Hughes, of the general prominence of certain registers or frequencies, silences and gaps, or of sections that are particularly filled with sonic activity. All of these might provide hints of content that might bear out fruitful analysis when put forwards again. </p>

<p>Deformance of poetic recordings forces us to consider the nature of recorded literary recordings anew. We might extrapolate from the character of this recording that all recorded voices contain a linguistic element as well an audible one. Not fully audio nor fully textual artifacts, I want to say that they are, instead something we might call audiotextual, a term that Jason Camlot has recently used in relation to the classification of Victorian literary recordings as an expansion of McGann’s own historicist approach to textual criticism. </p>

<p><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/audiotextual.jpg" width="40%" class="right" /></p>

<p>I want to use the term as a play on audiovisual to describe the state of such sound recordings. Like the Hughes recording, with both an instrumental, sound component as well as a linguistic one, audiotextual recordings exist in sound as well as in print. It’s a fairly simple idea, but I think it is one that often gets concerned as we discuss sound recordings. Literary sound recordings are not reducible to their relationship with a print text: they have both sounded <em>and</em> print components. Audiobooks, in particular, not being “poetic” often seem to get left out of close listenings and treated as mere reproductions of print texts. If you read the reviews of any Amazon audiobook or <a href="http://www.librivox.org">LibriVox</a> recording, you will see hundreds of people who expect an audiobook to be an unmediated, honest representation of the print origin. Audiotextual might be used equally to describe both Hughes’s literary sound recordings as well as Hughes’s poetry itself, saturated as it is with traces of the live performance techniques of jazz and blues musicians. </p>

<p>More profoundly, I think sound recording during the modernist period is an especially good candidate for deformative acts of listening and interpretation. It is well-known and often-noted that modernist authors were obsessed with the gramophone, but consider the nature of such representations. The gramophones are most often marked by the materiality of their failures. In the “Hades” episode of <em>Ulysses</em>, the machine disintegrates into parody at the very moment at which it is meant to revive the voice of a dead relative:  “After dinner on a Sunday. Put on poor old greatgrandfather Kraahraark! Hellohellohello amawfullyglad kraark awfullygladaseeagain hellohello amawf krpthsth” (114). Sound reproduction during the period was not marked by the high fidelity, by the ability to authentically reproduce a deceptively “real” recording of life. It is a flawed act marked, as in Joyce’s case, by skipping needles, locked grooves, and hissing machines. For Joyce, this means uncovering a renewed sense that sound recordings were imperfect things, themselves subject to deformation by their own young technology. Joyce thinks of the gramophone recording as an object that can reach back into the past. He does not play it backwards as such, but the very act of playing the voice reverses time itself. And it does so in a manner that deforms the recording, altering its shape and transmission as a natural and comical part of the playback process.</p>

<p>Woolf’s failing gramophone in <em>Between the Acts</em> draws the elements of my short talk together nicely and can act as a closing image. During the pageant play at the heart of the text, a malfunctioning gramophone provides musical and narrative accompaniment: “The gramophone gurgled Unity-Dispersity. It gurgled Un…dis…And ceased” (201). The words themselves break apart into component syllables; semantic meaning evaporates as the grain of language pushes to the surface, and the heard word gives way to the gurgling materiality of the record itself. Woolf makes us hear the sound of the words as bound with their meanings. Her gramophone falls into locked grooves throughout the novel, transfixing its listeners and forming a community out of the audience of listeners by expanding the time with which they engage with each other. Not reversing time, certainly, but she does meditate on the ability of a malfunctioning gramophone to create anew through performance and deformance.</p>

<p>For Joyce and Woolf, the machines fail as often as they succeed. Deformance is thoroughly entwined with such performances. We may even go so far as to say that sound reproduction of this sort is a always kind of deformance, that no media form provides a pure, unaltered transmission of its content. As a critical practice, deformance, a systematic and intentionally disruptive form of engagement with materials, actually gets us closer to the kinds of media relationships that these authors would have known. The practice can offer us new perspective on literary and sonic materials, sure, but it can also provide us with something older. Deformative listening then, might be a practice of recovery, of attempting to recreate the phenomenological experience of a 1920s gramophone listening. The devil in the recording proves to be not the sort that conspiracy theorists would have you believe. The darkness lurking beneath sound recordings, be they musical or literary in nature, is the shadow of the materials, their very real failures, and the deformance that has always been present anytime we put needle to disc. </p>

<p><strong>Works Cited</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Albright, Daniel. <em>Untwisting the Serpent: Modernism in Music, Literature, and Other Arts</em>. Chicago, Ill: University of Chicago Press, 2000. Print.</li>
<li>Bernstein, Charles, ed. <em>Close Listening: Poetry and the Performed Word</em>. Oxford University Press, USA, 1998. Print.</li>
<li>Hughes, Langston, Leonard Feather, and Charles Mingus. <em>Weary Blues</em>. MGM, 1959. CD.</li>
<li>Joyce, James. <em>Ulysses</em>. Vintage, 1990. Print.</li>
<li>Pater, Walter. “<a href="http://www.victorianweb.org/authors/pater/renaissance/7.html">The School of Giorgione</a>.” <em>The Renaissance: Studies in Art and Poetry</em>. 1873. Web.</li>
<li>Woolf, Virginia. <em>Between the Acts</em>. New York: Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, 1969. Print.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Deformance]]></title>
    <link href="https://walshbr.com/blog/2015/01/05/deformance/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-05T10:18:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://walshbr.com/blog/2015/01/05/deformance</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[The following post is crosslisted on the <a href="http://ach.org/">ACH</a>’s blog. The post details the methods used in putting together a talk for MLA 15 that takes place in 212 VCC West at 12:00 PM on Friday, January 9th.]</p>

<p>My talk for the ACH’s panel at MLA 15 is entitled “The Devil in the Recording: Deformative Listening and Poetry.” I will be talking about the problems and affordances for deformance in the context of audio recordings, specifically those that have literary content. The particular method I will focus on is the reversal of audio recordings, taking my cue from the infamous claim that you can hear Satanic lyrics in Led Zeppelin’s “Stairway to Heaven” if you play the recording backwards. In the example below I will show how to reverse an audio file, and I will be working with Langston Hughes’s reading of “Motto” with Charles Mingus and Leonard Feather on his 1958 recording <em>Weary Blues</em>.</p>

<p>Professional-grade sound-editing software like <em><a href="http://www.avid.com/us/products/family/pro-tools/">Pro Tools</a></em> or <em><a href="https://www.apple.com/logic-pro/">Logic</a></em> give you the capacity to do a lot in the way of sound mixing and work with music, but I often find myself drowning in their limitless options. They are also quite expensive. <em><a href="http://audacity.sourceforge.net/">Audacity</a></em> is my audio editing software of choice: the tool is open source and, most importantly, fairly intuitive and easy to use. Audacity is somewhat more limited than other options, but it does what it can cleanly and intuitively.</p>

<p>To reverse an audio file, begin by opening that clip in <em>Audacity</em> in the same way that you would open a file in any other piece of software. You will get something that looks like this:</p>

<p><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/waveform.jpg" width="40%" class="right" /></p>

<p>What you see here is a <a href="http://manual.audacityteam.org/o/man/audacity_waveform.html">waveform</a>, a way of graphically representing the audio file in way that allows you to manipulate it. The y-axis of the waveform corresponds to volume – the taller the waveform, the louder the sound file’s contents are at that particular moment in time. This can be a quick and easy way to identify chunks of activity by looking for spikes in the volume.</p>

<p><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/axes.jpg" /></p>

<p>The x-axis represents time – the Hughes file I have sliced out is 46” long, and the program gives you a timeline along the top of the segment to situate you in the file. Clicking anywhere on the waveform will set the file playback to begin at that point, and you can click and drag to highlight a selection of the clip for processing.</p>

<p>To process the file, highlight the section that you want reversed. In this case, since we are working with the entire file, we will just select everything. Under the “effect” menu, <em>Audacity</em> gives you a range of options for remixing your sound data, but we want the “reverse” function. </p>

<p><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/reverse.jpg" width="40%" class="right" /></p>

<p>Now you have a reversed file at your disposal. Sound tends to work in attack and decay, and much of the strangeness of a reversed recording comes from sounds increasing rather than fading in intensity over time. And, as I will discuss in my talk, the process throws into sharp relief the distinct character of recorded linguistic content. </p>

<p><em>Audacity</em> saves files in <em>Audacity</em> project formats by default, so you will need to export your file to a different file format if you want to play it in a media player. I tend to use both .ogg and .mp3 files for browser compatibility. <em>Audacity</em> will also give you the opportunity to input light metadata for your file before it exports in case you want to curate your file for inclusion in an archive or home-library.</p>

<p><img src="{{ root_url }}/images/export.jpg" width="40%" class="right" /></p>

<p><em>Audacity</em> gives many other options for experimenting with sound remixing, distortion, and deformance that I would encourage you to explore. The software also gives you many options for working with sound files more generally. I have written <a href="http://walshbr.github.io/blog/2013/11/13/audio-at-thatcampva/">elsewhere</a> about using Audacity to prepare sound files for research and presentation. Check out my other post if you want to learn more about how to slice out clips, mix together two sound files, or process DRM files.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
